<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "teixlite.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/teihtml.xsl"?>
<TEI.2>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Early Modern Literary Studies</title>
				<editor>Ray Siemens</editor>
				<funder>Conversion from HTML to TEI.2 conformant markup funded by the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council of Canada, Aid to Research and Transfer Journals Program, Special Initiatives Grant # 647-98-0040.</funder>
				<sponsor>Sheffield Hallam University and the University of Toronto Electronic Publishing Centre</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Conversion from HTML to TEI.2 conformant markup:</resp>
					<name>Kathryn Harvey</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<extent>approx. 249k</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>University of Toronto Electronic Publishing Centre and Sheffield Hallam University</publisher>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Copyright 2000.</p>
				</availability>
				<pubPlace>Sheffield, UK, and Toronto, Canada</pubPlace>
				<idno>ISSN 1201-2459</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl>
					<title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title>, Volume 3, Issue 2 (September 1997)</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Early Modern Literary Studies (ISSN 1201-2459) is a refereed journal serving as a formal arena for scholarly discussion and as an academic resource for researchers in the area. Articles in EMLS examine English literature, literary culture, and language during the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries; responses to published papers are also published as part of a Readers' Forum. Reviews evaluate recent work as well as academic tools of interest to scholars in the field. EMLS is committed to gathering and to maintaining links to the most useful and comprehensive internet resources for Renaissance scholars, including archives, electronic texts, discussion groups, and beyond.</p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p>The entire contents of EMLS issues have been converted from HTML with the exception of the Table of Contents page.</p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<p>Quotations: All quotation marks have been converted to "q," "title," or other tags and have not been retained as data.  Some attempt has been made to provide finer distinctions among quoted and mentioned passages.</p>
				<p>Corrections: The conversion from HTML has been manually performed and every attempt has been made not to introduce errors into the text.</p>
			</editorialDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<p>The id attributes contain canonical references in the following form: JournalAbbrevVol-IssueAuthorTitleAbbrevExtension, where the journal abbreviation is "EMLS," followed by the volume and issue number.  The author and title abbreviations take the form of the first four letters of the author's last name and first three or four letters of a word identifying the content of the article (usually taken from a word in the title, or in the case of a review "rev" is often used).  The extension refers to the type of reference.  For example, the id for the first annotation of the article "King Lear in its Own Time: The Difference that Death Makes" by Ben Ross Schneider Jr. would be "EMLS1-1schnlearn1," where the "n1" indicates note 1.</p>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>23 January 2000</date>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>SGML edited by</resp>
					<name>Kathryn Harvey</name>
				</respStmt>
				<item>converted HTML</item>
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>28 January 2000</date>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>SGML edited by</resp>
					<name>Kathryn Harvey</name>
				</respStmt>
				<item>converted HTML</item>
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>29 January 2000</date>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>SGML edited by</resp>
					<name>Kathryn Harvey</name>
				</respStmt>
				<item>converted HTML</item>
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>30 January 2000</date>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>SGML edited by</resp>
					<name>Kathryn Harvey</name>
				</respStmt>
				<item>converted HTML</item>
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>13 February 2000</date>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>SGML edited by</resp>
					<name>Kathryn Harvey</name>
				</respStmt>
				<item>updated to new dtd</item>
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>25 June 2000</date>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>SGML edited by</resp>
					<name>Kathryn Harvey</name>
				</respStmt>
				<item>tag clean-up</item>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="issuesection">
				<head>
					<title level="j">EMLS</title> 3.2 (September, 1997)</head>
				<head>Articles</head>
				<div2 id="emls3-203-2abs" type="articleabstracts">
					<head>
						<!-- <img src="../header2.gif" alt="early" width="283" height="87" modern literary studies> -->Article Abstracts / R&eacute;sum&eacute;s des Articles</head>
					<p>(Translations from English courtesy of Luc Borot, Centre d'Etudes et de Recherches sur la Renaissance Anglaise, Universit&eacute; Paul-Valery, Montpellier, France.)</p>
					<div3 type="text">
						<p>
							<list>
								<item>Marlowe, Edward II, and the Cult of Elizabeth.</item>
								<item>Dennis Kay, University of North Carolina, Charlotte.</item>
								<item>[<ref target="emls3-2kaymarlabs-e">English</ref> | <ref target="emls3-2kaymarlabs-f">French</ref>]</item>
							</list>
						</p>
						<p>
							<list>
								<item>The Poetic Nocturne: From Ancient Motif to Renaissance Genre.</item>
								<item>Chris Fitter, Rutgers University, Camden.</item>
								<item>[<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctabs-e">English</ref> | <ref target="emls3-2fittnoctabs-f">French</ref>]</item>
							</list>
						</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<div4 id="emls3-2kaymarlabs-e" type="text">
							<head>
								<ref target="emls3-2kaymarl">Marlowe, <title level="m">Edward II</title>, and the Cult of Elizabeth</ref>. Dennis Kay, University of North Carolina, Charlotte.</head>
							<p>This paper seeks to relate <title level="m">Edward II</title> to the cult of Elizabeth, suggesting that it participates fully in the discursive procedures that surrounded the Tudor monarchy. At the most basic level, I will propose that in Marlowe's play the image of the King may be construed as a negative exemplum, being in effect defined negatively in terms of the well established cult of Queen Elizabeth. Likewise Shakespeare's <title level="m">King Lear</title> establishes a pointed contrast between the assiduously promoted public image of King James as judge, patriarch and unifier of the Kingdoms of Britain, and Shakespeare's depiction of Lear, the Last ruler of the whole island, as one who judges foolishly, fragments his family and carves up his realm. Like that of <title level="m">Lear</title>, the world of <title level="m">Edward II</title> is constructed as an admonitory negative example for the present. The parallels extend beyond the age to the more specific question of the ruler as an individual, and that, of course, was a question that could hardly be considered -- or even imagined -- outside the terms of reference of Elizabeth's cult.</p>
						</div4>
						<div4 id="emls3-2kaymarlabs-f">
							<head>
								<ref target="emls3-2kaymarl">Marlowe, <title level="m">Edward II</title>, and the Cult of Elizabeth</ref>. Dennis Kay, University of North Carolina, Charlotte.</head>
							<p>Le but de cet article est d'&eacute;tablir un lien entre l'<title level="m">&Eacute;douard II</title> de Marlowe et le culte de la reine &Eacute;lisabeth, en sugg&eacute;rant qu'il rel&egrave;ve pleinement des proc&eacute;dures discursives qui entouraient la monarchie tudor. Au niveau le plus &eacute;l&eacute;mentaire, j'&eacute;mets l'hypoth&egrave;se que dans la pi&egrave;ce de Marlowe, on peut comprendre l'image du roi comme <emph rend="italics">exemplum</emph> n&eacute;gatif, &eacute;tant d&eacute;fini en effet n&eacute;gativement dans les termes du culte bien &eacute;tabli de la reine &Eacute;lisabeth. De m&ecirc;me, <title level="m">Le roi Lear</title> de Shakespeare &eacute;tablit un contraste aigu entre l'image publique si couramment diffus&eacute;e du roi Jacques comme juge, patriarche et unificateur des royaumes de Grande Bretagne, d'une part, et de l'autre la description par Shakespeare de Lear, dernier gouvernant de l'&icirc;le toute enti&egrave;re, comme l'homme qui juge stupidement, fragmente sa famille, et d&eacute;coupe son royaume en morceaux. Comme celui de <title level="m">Lear</title>, le monde d'<title level="m">&Eacute;douard II</title> est construit comme un exemple n&eacute;gatif cens&eacute; servir d'avertissement pour le pr&eacute;sent. Les parall&eacute;lismes se prolongent au-del&agrave; de l'&eacute;poque elle-m&ecirc;me pour embrasser la question sp&eacute;cifique du gouvernant comme individu, question qu'il &eacute;tait difficile, bien s&ucirc;r, d'envisager --ou m&ecirc;me d'imaginer-- sans se r&eacute;f&eacute;rer aux termes du culte d'&Eacute;lisabeth.</p>
						</div4>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<div4 id="emls3-2fittnoctabs-e">
							<head>
								<ref target="emls3-2fittnoct">The Poetic  Nocturne: From Ancient Motif to Renaissance Genre</ref>. Chris Fitter, Rutgers University, Camden.</head>
							<p>The genre of poetic nocturne needs dating not to the eighteenth century and the verse of such as Parnell, Young and Gray as has literary history hitherto, but to the Renaissance: whose poetry, masques and painting, in revaluing night as a time of beauty and profundity, overturn, I will argue, the construction predominant in classical and medieval traditions. Those earlier approaches themselves, Greek, Roman, biblical, patristic and medieval, have never been systematically investigated for their representation of night. This paper, accordingly, will seek to sketch a basic poetic tradition, and its elevation to independent genre, hitherto uncharted: from whose Renaissance productions eighteenth-century and Romantic writing will often derive, and at whose heart lie Shakespeare, Jonson, and perhaps above all, the lyric but combative genius of Milton.</p>
						</div4>
						<div4 id="emls3-2fittnoctabs-f">
							<head>
								<ref target="emls3-2fittnoct">The Poetic  Nocturne: From Ancient Motif to Renaissance Genre</ref>. Chris Fitter, Rutgers University, Camden.</head>
							<p>Ce n'est pas au dix-huiti&egrave;me si&egrave;cle et &agrave; la po&eacute;sie d'auteurs comme Parnell, Young et Gray qu'il faut faire remonter le genre du nocturne po&eacute;tique, comme l'histoire litt&eacute;raire l'a fait jusqu'ici, mais &agrave; la Renaissance. Je soutiendrai ici que c'est sa po&eacute;sie, ses masques et sa peinture qui, en r&eacute;&eacute;valuant la nuit comme moment de beaut&eacute; et de profondeur, a renvers&eacute; la construction pr&eacute;dominante des traditions classiques et m&eacute;di&eacute;vales. En fait, ces approches ant&eacute;rieures, grecques, romaines, bibliques, patristiques et m&eacute;di&eacute;vales, n'ont jamais &eacute;t&eacute; syst&eacute;matiquement examin&eacute;es du point de vue de leurs repr&eacute;sentations de la nuit. Dans cette optique, cet article va chercher &agrave; esquisser le cheminement encore jamais d&eacute;crit, d'une tradition po&eacute;tique fondamentale jusqu'&agrave; son &eacute;l&eacute;vation au rang de genre ind&eacute;pendant; c'est de ces oeuvres de la Renaissance que la litt&eacute;rature du dix-huiti&egrave;me si&egrave;cle et du romantisme s'inspirera souvent, et au coeur de cette tradition que se trouvent Shakespeare, Jonson, et peut-&ecirc;tre au-dessus de tous, le g&eacute;nie lyrique mais combatif de Milton.</p>
						</div4>
					</div3>
					<byline>
						<!-- <a href="../emlshome.html" alt="emls home page"> -->
						<!-- <img src="../button.gif" width="124" height="47"> -->
						<!-- </a> -->
						<!-- <a href="../emlscopy.html"> -->&copy;<!-- </a> --> 1997-, R.G. Siemens (Editor, <title level="j">EMLS</title>). (LB, RGS, 4 September 1997)</byline>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls3-2kaymarl" n="1" type="article">
					<head>Marlowe, <title level="m">Edward II</title>, and the Cult of Elizabeth</head>
					<opener>
						<name>Dennis Kay</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>University of North Carolina, Charlotte </addrLine>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href="mailto:denniskay@aol.com"> -->denniskay@aol.com<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
						<!-- <img src="../header2.gif" alt="early" width="283" height="87" modern literary studies> -->
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Kay, Dennis. <title level="a">Marlowe, <title level="m">Edward II</title>, and the Cult of Elizabeth.</title>
						<title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 3.2 (September, 1997): 1.1-30 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/03-2/kaymarl.html"> --> http://purl.oclc.org/emls/03-2/kaymarl.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;. </p>
					<div3>
						<head>Introduction</head>
						<p n="1">I recognise my title may appear an archaic reversion to the critical discourse of the later 1980's: after all, <title level="m">Edward II</title> is one of a select group of Elizabethan literary performances that has so far failed to arouse much critical interest in such terms. This state of affairs is surprising for several reasons. There was, for instance, a strong and continuing Elizabethan and Jacobean curiosity about the reign of Edward II and the years immediately following his death -- I have in mind the writings of Heywood, Jonson, and, above all, Michael Drayton, not to mention the important account of Edward's Queen, Isabel of France, in Foxe's <title level="m">Actes and Monumentes</title>, and Elizabeth Carey's <title level="m">Edward II</title>. </p>
						<p n="2">On the other hand, the play's relative neglect is understandable. Like Shakespeare's <title level="m">Love's Labour's Lost</title> or <title level="m">King John</title>, for example, <title level="m">Edward II</title> represents power relations in ways that may seem, at first sight, to be unassimilable to some contemporary interpretive procedures, or at least inconsistent with some venerable and resilient assumptions. We have only to recall the very powerlessness of the rulers depicted in these plays, together with the scrutiny and questioning to which their words are routinely subjected by other speakers. Claude Summers has located the play's heterodoxy in its <q direct="y">refusal to subscribe to a comforting Tudor political myth</q>: in the words of Marlowe's Edward <q direct="y">Am I a king and must be overruled?</q> (1.1.134).<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln1">[1]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="3">An important element in the context of <title level="m">Edward II</title> is the widespread 1590's interest in Mortimer and in the Barons' Wars, but I do not wish to elaborate on this phenomenon; rather, I seek to relate <title level="m">Edward II</title> to the cult of Elizabeth, suggesting that it participates fully in the discursive procedures that surrounded the Tudor monarchy. Let me state my argument at its starkest: I propose that in Marlowe's play the image of the king may be construed as a negative exemplum, being defined negatively in terms of the well established cult of Queen Elizabeth. Similarly, Shakespeare's <title level="m">King Lear</title> establishes a pointed contrast between the assiduously promoted public image of King James as judge, patriarch and unifier of the kingdoms of Britain, and Shakespeare's depiction of Lear, the last ruler of the whole island, as one who judges foolishly, fragments his family and carves up his realm. Like the world of <title level="m">Lear</title>, that of <title level="m">Edward II</title> is constructed as an admonitory negative example for the present.<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln2">[2]</ref> Moreover, the parallels extend beyond the age to the more specific question of the ruler as an individual, and that, of course, was a question that could hardly be considered -- or even imagined -- outside the terms of reference of Elizabeth's cult. </p>
						<p n="4">Allow me to cite another negative example. In Shakespeare's <title level="m">Twelfth Night</title> (a text which operates, as Marlowe's does, through gender reversal), Orsino seems designed almost as an anthology of many of the personal inadequacies that might hamstring a ruler. More specifically, his failings are those conventionally associated in Tudor misogynist discourse with a female ruler. He is, as women were held to be by such writers, changeable, governed by his moods and passions. And he falls in love with one of his followers, who thereby becomes specially favoured among his entourage, consequently threatening the political system and the delicate balance of relationships among his subjects. He is therefore, like Edward II, the antithesis of Queen Elizabeth: it is against the ideal of the ruler as enshrined in her cult that he is judged and found wanting.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>Culture of the Early 1590's </head>
						<p n="5">By the early 1590's, Elizabeth might have been forgiven for thinking that such issues had been thoroughly ventilated a generation before, at the time of her accession and in the question of her marriage. But one of the features of the Elizabethan settlement was that nothing was ever finally settled: there was always room for renegotiation, revaluation, changes of emphasis. Alan Sinfield has argued for an understanding of the Elizabethan state <q direct="y">not as a static totality whose power structure is revealed in the ideology of monarchy, but as diverse and changing, a site of profound contradictions.</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln3">[3]</ref> Certainly, it was a site of conflicts, checks and balances, not just between the aristocracy and an emergent, upwardly mobile <q direct="y">middling sort,</q> but also between groups within the nobility.<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln4">[4]</ref> Elizabeth had evolved a strategy for dealing with the competitive pack of nobles who served her: Sir Robert Naunton observed that <q direct="y">The principal note of her reign will be, that she ruled much by faction and parties, which she herself both made, upheld, and weakened, as her own great judgement advised</q> -- he commented that <q direct="y">we find no Gaveston, Vere, or Spencer to have swayed alone during forty-four years.</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln5">[5]</ref> Elizabeth's cult had a purpose: its central image of singleness and immutability -- the Queen's motto was <emph rend="italics">Semper eadem</emph>, <q direct="y">always the same</q> -- was constructed in response to threats of fracture, disruption, and rebellion. And its most extreme manifestations in the 1590's imply profound anxieties both about the current political climate and about the unknowable -- almost literally unthinkable -- future that would unfold after Gloriana's death. </p>
						<p n="6">Marlowe constantly nudges the spectator to find contemporary parallels. Thus, although the historical Edward had been in his early forties at his death, Marlowe explicitly makes him an old man -- he is <q direct="y">aged</q> at 5.2.118, <q direct="y">Old Edward</q> at 5.2.23, and is compared to an <q direct="y">old wolf</q> at 5.2.7. The world of the play is that of the money economy, in which the crown's finances were under increasing strain. It is a site of conflict between an old aristocracy and a new one. It is a world like that of the 1590's, in which financing wars in France empties the treasury coffers. Leah Marcus has recently shown how Shakespeare's Joan La Pucelle in <title level="m">1 Henry VI</title> is presented as part of critique of the Queen's hesitations in foreign polity, and there is a similar contemporary implication in the depiction of Edward's failure to meet his financial obligations.<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln6">[6]</ref> By 1592, there was a disruptive influx of deserters from the French wars, some of whom were reported as <q direct="y">using most slanderous speeches of . . . her Highness</q>: in the following year, these wretched men crowded round the Queen and petitioned her at every opportunity: a contemporary wrote, <q direct="y">The Queen is troubled wherever she takes the air with these miserable creatures.</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln7">[7]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="7">Leicester had died in 1588, Walsingham in 1590, and Burghley was not in good health. It was clear that the Queen would have to listen to the voices of the younger generation, and that the question of the succession would lie beneath her dealings with them, just as the question of marriage had informed her relations with the older generation at the time of her accession. So the controversies and tensions of the 1560's surfaced again a quarter of a century later, in the time of confusion and trepidation that followed the scarcely believable victory over the Spanish Armada.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>Courtly Performances</head>
						<p n="8">The courtly behaviours that we see in the play are recognisably Elizabethan. To cite some relatively trivial instances, early in the second act, Edward compares himself to Danae's lover, Gaveston to the shepherd seeing the first shoots of spring. Their self-presentation relates them to the fashions of Ovidian and pastoral writing in the 1590s. While earlier Mortimer had left the court like a disaffected 1590's melancholic,<q type="block">
								<lg type="line verse">
									<l>Unto the forest . . . </l>
									<l>To live in grief and baleful discontent, </l>
									<l>For now my lord the king regards me not . . . .</l>
								</lg>
							</q>This represents the typical behaviour of the political exile, or disaffected lord -- the Earl of Essex regularly acted in this way in the 1590's. Marlowe's Isabella likewise declares -- <q direct="y">I will endure a melancholy life, And let him frolic with his minion</q> (1.2.66-7). </p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>Gaveston the Elizabethan Courtier</head>
						<p n="9">The most striking example, however, is Gaveston himself, who is figured as the quintessential Elizabethan Courtier. He is praised by Spencer, for instance, as <q direct="y">the liberal earl of Cornwall</q> -- recalling Elyot's observation that liberality <q direct="y">resteth not in the quantity or quality of things that be given, but in the natural disposition of the giver.</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln8">[8]</ref> When in the first scene of the play Gaveston anticipates the performance of his new role as royal favourite, he uses terms that explicitly echo the behaviours and discourses of royal celebration under Elizabeth. At least one Elizabethan political theorist mounted a defence of Gaveston, arguing that although he may have been personally proud, he did little harm, and was certainly not an argument against the hereditary principle.<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln9">[9]</ref> One recent critic compares the King and Gaveston at their window to courtiers on the Elizabethan stage (1.4.416-8).<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln10">[10]</ref> Like Essex and Leicester, Gaveston is characterised as an impresario of courtly entertainments (10). In the early scenes of the play there is a sense that the nobles are mainly moved by snobbery and that Gaveston is in his anarchic way on the crowd's side against entrenched privilege. Complaints about Gaveston's promotion focus on the honour code -- <q direct="y">What man of noble birth can brook this sight?</q> The nobles say the king is <q direct="y">bewitched</q> (1.2.55); that he is <q direct="y">light-brained</q> (5.2.2). But what we see and hear paints a rather different picture. Gaveston takes over the property of the Bishop of Coventry -- <q direct="y">let him complain unto the see of hell</q> -- and displays, like the Bastard in <title level="m">King John</title>, an obviously crowd pleasing anti-clericalism (<q direct="y">what should a priest do with so fair a house</q> [190, 205]). What is more, Gaveston is exactly like the favourites of Henry VIII, the fathers and grandfathers of the great men of Elizabethan England. </p>
						<p n="10">The mythological entertainments he imagines, with Italian masques and water pageants (1.1.60-69) -- are wholly characteristic of Elizabethan shows. In 1564 Robert Dudley the Earl of Leicester staged, ostensibly for the Queen's entertainment, a debate between Juno and Diana <q direct="y">on the question of marriage.</q> The Queen's response (gleefully reported by the Spanish ambassador) was <q direct="y">This is all against me.</q> The cruel queen Zabeta in Dudley's Kenilworth entertainment of 1575 was another version of Elizabeth -- a type which is found in pageants and shows staged for the Queen throughout her reign. In the last two decades of her reign, Elizabeth was praised increasingly as a type of the Goddess Cynthia/Diana.<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln11">[11]</ref> The irony here of course is that in Elizabethan usage the story of Diana and Actaeon is conventionally told not to arouse the monarch but to warn her subjects against excessive familiarity. An obvious example is the treatment of Faunus in the mutability cantos. Gaveston seems not to perceive the show as a prefiguring of his own fate.<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln12">[12]</ref>
						</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>Eroticisation of Politics</head>
						<p n="11">It would be a mistake to view Gaveston in isolation. If Marlowe makes him behave as if he were a version of the typical Elizabethan court favourite, then the stage on which he plays his role was axiomatically fraught with problems and anxieties for those who sought to play it, as well as for those whose lives would be affected by its outcome. The work of Marie Axton, Arthur Marotti, and Louis Montrose, among others, has made us familiar with the Elizabethan phenomenon of the eroticisation of political discourse and the simultaneous politicisation of erotic discourse, and <title level="m">Edward II</title> clearly exemplifies the inseparability of these discursive modes. </p>
						<p n="12">Elizabeth's career seems almost to have been designed as a repudiation of the misogynistic commonplaces that had been rehearsed around the time of her accession. A conventional view (articulated by Becon, Calvin, and others) had been that a woman ruler was a sign of divine displeasure. In Bullinger's analysis, the restraining presence of a husband, or else a good assembly of counsellors, was desirable in a woman ruler.<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln13">[13]</ref> We should recall that Henry VIII's will provided that if his daughters married without the consent of the Council they would exclude themselves from the succession. Over the course of Elizabeth's reign, the tone of such political courtship underwent several changes. By the 1590's, courtiers -- with the exception of Essex -- were figured less crudely as the Queen's suitors. Their desire for the Queen, a desire upon which their actions were declared to be predicated, had become redefined, desexualised, and conventionalised. </p>
						<p n="13">Queen Elizabeth had initially been besieged by royal suitors from all over Europe. Cecil recorded that, <q direct="y">Here is great resort of wooers and controversy amongst lovers . . . . ten or twelve ambassadors competing for her favour . . . courting at a most marvellous rate</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln14">[14]</ref>; but her apparent infatuation with Robert Dudley was seized upon for scandalised comment. Dudley, of course, was already married, was not royal, and was from a family of whom several had in recent generations been executed for treason. The example of Gaveston was one of those cited against Dudley and the Queen. Much more alarming to contemporaries was the inversion of properties and the distortion of power relations within the council. The Count of Feria said in 1559 that Dudley is so much in favour that <q direct="y">he does whatever he likes with affairs</q> (that is, he could act without reference to the Council) and that <q direct="y">her Majesty visits him in his chamber day and night</q> -- not the way for a monarch to behave. Throughout her reign, the Queen's sexuality and marital possibilities informed political culture, as factions sought to place a husband with the Queen in order to strengthen their own position. </p>
						<p n="14">But changes did occur over time. Courtship became more allegorical, and more controlled. An example is found in Lyly's <title level="m">Endimion</title> (1591). Endimion loves the moon-goddess, and intends to possess her: <q direct="y">Sweet Cynthia,</q> he asks, <q direct="y">how wouldst thou be pleased, how possessed? . . . Desirest thou the passions of loue . . .?</q> (2.1.4). The play unfolds by teaching him the lesson that his desire can never be achieved. Eventually Cynthia kisses the sleeping Endimion, in a gesture that would have been recognised as chaste, indeed as a token of the absence of sexual desire. When Endimion awakes, his address to the Queen typifies the officially sanctioned, morally defensible, pose of the abject courtier: <q type="block">Such a difference hath the Gods sette betweene our states, that all must be dutie, loyalitie, and reuerence; nothing . . . be termed loue. My vnspotted thoughts, my languishing bodie, my discontented life, let them obtaine by princelie fauour impossibilities; with imagination of which, I will spend my spirits, and to my selfe that no creature may heare, softlie call it loue. And if any vrge to vtter what I whisper, then will I name it honour. (5.3.170-5)</q>When he came reflect upon Elizabeth's reign, Francis Bacon addressed the question of propriety raised by the eroticisation of political discourse at her court. He observed that although the Queen had <q direct="y">allowed herself to be wooed and courted, and even to have love made to her,</q> nevertheless, such <q direct="y">dalliances detracted but little from her fame and nothing at all from her majesty.</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln15">[15]</ref> It is of course in both of these aspects, fame -- i.e., reputation -- and majesty that Marlowe's Edward is shown to fall down. Where Elizabeth had controlled courtship up to the early 1590's through obliquity, metaphor, indirection, deferral, obfuscation, and systematic denial of satisfaction, Marlowe's play shows what can happen when the control slips.</p>
						<p n="15">The chief inversion of Marlowe's play, the central deviation from Elizabethan discursive practice, does not reside in figuring the monarch in the male person of Edward, nor indeed in the fact that the relationship between the King and Gaveston is homosexual: rather it is the fact that when Edward falls in love with Gaveston, the King becomes a subject in and to love.<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln16">[16]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="16">And that was precisely what Elizabethan politicians had feared would happen if the Queen chose one of their number to be her husband. The dreaded inversion would have had the further inevitable consequence of distorting the power relationships. Edward's creation of new peers, his disruption of aristocratic hierarchies (<q direct="y">He that I list to favour shall be great</q>), would have been a further illustration of the same fear.<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln17">[17]</ref> In Elizabethan terms, Edward's elevation of Gaveston would have seemed deeply shocking. It was a species of behaviour utterly distinct from Queen Elizabeth's. Her frugality in the matter of honours was reported as an abstemiousness from which the whole body politic might benefit. As Essex discovered just a few years later, when he doled out knighthoods in a way that aroused the Queen's anger at a devaluation of the currency of honours, one of the features of her rule was a parsimoniousness about honours, a restraint or modesty that parallelled her own honour.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>Leicester and Pembroke</head>
						<p n="17">An almost incidental contemporary element is found in the hereditary titles and court offices borne by characters in Marlowe's play. What would an Elizabethan theatre audience have made of the fact that both Gaveston and Spencer are created Lord Chamberlain (3.2.146), for example? In two cases, Marlowe seems to take pains to tread very carefully. </p>
						<p n="18">The play's Earl of Leicester is given a markedly gentle ride. We are told of the regret with which Leicester fulfills his instructions. He declares himself moved to compassion by the sigh of the King: <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Alas, see where he sits and hopes unseen </l>
									<l>T'escape their hands that seek to reave his lie . . . (4.6.51-2).</l>
								</lg>
							</q>In the next act, Leicester tries to console the captive monarch, urging him to <q direct="y">Imagine Killingworth Castle were your court.</q> And his words draw praise from the King: <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Leicester, if gentle words might comfort me, </l>
									<l>Thy speeches long ago had eased my sorrows, </l>
									<l>For kind and loving hast thou always been (5.1.1-4)</l>
								</lg>
							</q>As the action unfolds, it is Leicester who persuades Edward to abdicate, in the interest of his son -- <q direct="y">speak them fair, / For if they go the prince shall lose his right</q> (5.1.91-2). And then at a crucial moment the queen relieves Leicester of his command (5.1.135), thereby distancing him from direct involvement in Edward's death. It is later reported (5.2.35) that Leicester laments over the king's fate.</p>
						<p n="19">The Earl of Pembroke, like Leicester, is placed at a remove from actual rebellion, and from the execution of plots against an anointed King. He appears as a peacemaker, as a person trusted by all parties, a stature presumably confirmed by the numerous sententious and semi-proverbial utterances he is given to say (for example, <q direct="y">Can kingly lions fawn on creeping ants?</q> [1.5.15]), and by the way his words gain acceptance: Pembroke throughout is figured as a representative of an older nobility (in the battle, for example, he fights against Spencer Junior, whom he calls an <q direct="y">upstart</q> [3.4.20]), but he is made to exhibit none of the class-hostility to Gaveston that the other nobles show. He is punctilious in his greeting to Gaveston at 2.2.68 -- <q direct="y">Welcome master Secretary.</q>
						</p>
						<p n="20">In the space of a few dozen lines we are apprised of (a) Pembroke's support for the crown, when Edward says <q direct="y">Pembroke shall bear the sword before the King,</q> and the Earl replies, <q direct="y">And with this sword Pembroke will fight for you</q> (1.4.352); (b) Pembroke's support for the killing of Gaveston in his taking an oath to that effect (2.2.108); and (c) his sensitivity to popular opinion, <q direct="y">This will be good news to the common sort</q> (1.4.92). </p>
						<p n="21">In the debate in 2.5 where the lords consider how they should respond to the King's request for Gaveston's return, it is Pembroke who proposes a solution: <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Because his majesty so earnestly </l>
									<l>Desire to see the man before his death, </l>
									<l>I will upon mine honour undertake </l>
									<l>To carry him and bring him back again . . . (78-81).</l>
								</lg>
							</q>
						</p>
						<p>And his disinterest is stressed: <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>My lords, I will not over-woo your honours, </l>
									<l>But if you dare trust Pembroke with the prisoner, </l>
									<l>Upon mine oath I will return him back. (87-9)</l>
								</lg>
							</q>Lancaster is given words that confirm the trust reposed in Pembroke's honesty -- <q direct="y">I say, let him go on Pembroke's word</q> (91). Pembroke subsequently rebukes Arundel with a breach of chivalric honour in abducting Gaveston: <q direct="y">Your lordship doth dishonour to your self / And wrong our lord, your honourable friend</q> (3.1.9-10). Arundel's narrative of these events includes a defence of Pembroke's behaviour -- saying he <q direct="y">said least</q> during the debate on rebellion and then reporting that <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>The Earl of Pembroke mildly thus bespake -- . . . </l>
									<l>I will this undertake, to have him hence </l>
									<l>And see him redelivered to your hands. (3.2.108-112)</l>
								</lg>
							</q>Blame is specifically not attached to Pembroke -- Arundel goes out of his way to identify Warwick as the dishonourable and untrustworthy villain. </p>
						<p n="22">It is at such moments that we recall the words on the title page informing us that Marlowe's play had been <q direct="y">publiquely acted by the right honorable the Earle of Pembrook his seruantes,</q> and there are episodes when this fact is reflected in the script very crudely. So, for instance, when Warwick appears in the first moments of the third act to say: <q direct="y">My lord of Pembroke's men, / Strive you no longer</q> (3.1.7- 8), the words would have had a special resonance in performance.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>Ambiguity</head>
						<p n="23">Spencer's advice to Baldock about how he should turn himself from a scholar into a courtier has some relevance to Marlowe's own situation. It is not servility that gains favour, Spencer says, <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>You must be proud, bold, pleasant, resolute, </l>
									<l>And now and then stab as occasion serves (42-3)</l>
								</lg>
							</q>
						</p>
						<p n="24">If we look at the important scene (2.2) which features the devices by Mortimer and Lancaster, Mortimer's device of the diseased cedar may recall the use of a tree to represent the state (<emph rend="italics">res publica</emph>) during Elizabeth's entry pageant in the City of London in 1559. It is parallelled by Lyly's use of the image in <title level="m">Sapho and Phao</title>, but is also fairly commonplace.<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln18">[18]</ref> Lancaster's emblem of the flying fish that faces death whether it flies or swims is hardly more complex or ambiguous. It may well be the crudity of the images, their lack of teasing ambiguity or subtlety, that makes them unsuitable. </p>
						<p n="25">As is now widely recognised, ambiguity was a feature of Elizabethan courtly performance. In the <title level="m">Arte of Rhetorique</title>, Thomas Wilson had described how <q direct="y">the miseries of the courtier's life</q> could be <q direct="y">described</q> by the use of <q direct="y">similitudes, examples, comparisons from one thing to another, apte translacions, and heaping of allegories.</q> And one of the most famous allegorical performances of Elizabeth's reign occurred at Kenilworth, where the Queen was entertained by Robert Dudley from 9 July 1575.<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln19">[19]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="26">Marlowe collapses history, reminding us of this episode when he has Leicester say to the King in the fourth act -- <q direct="y">Your majesty must go to Killingworth</q> (4.4.81). Dudley had collapsed history too, in a way that connects his show with Marlowe's play. When Elizabeth entered the castle precincts, she made her way into the newly-constructed tiltyard by passing under an edifice called <q direct="y">Mortimer's Tower.</q> William Dugdale in his antiquities of Warwickshire reports that Leicester caused the tower to be decorated with <q direct="y">the Arms of Mortimer . . . cut in stone.</q> Now Leicester was clearly invoking the memory of a previous owner of Kenilworth, Roger Mortimer, who had staged a great pageant based on the idea of the round table in 1279, and his own diversions for the Queen explicitly tapped into the same Arthurian myth. But Dugdale -- and he cannot have been alone -- took the arms to be those of a different Mortimer, grandson of the above, namely our and Marlowe's Mortimer, the Earl of March, lover of a Queen who shared Elizabeth's name, and therefore, in Dugdale's view, a precedent of sorts for Dudley himself.<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln20">[20]</ref> Perhaps the inscription on the tower participates in the same strategy of obliquity that Marlowe's Mortimer deploys with his letter to the murderers. The application of the inscription could be taken as a powerful declaration of desire, of courtship: but it could equally plausibly be glossed as an act of courtesy, as a fulsome welcome by a generous host.<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln21">[21]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="27">Like most Elizabethan treatments of political questions, <title level="m">Edward II</title> is necessarily oblique, constructed (like Mortimer's letter or Dudley's inscription) on the basis of what Annabel Patterson in <title level="m">Censorship and Interpretation</title> (following Pierre Bourdieu) refers to as <q direct="y">functional ambiguity.</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln22">[22]</ref> The play's commentators have connected such ambiguity with its tendency to question, to qualify, to undermine.<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln23">[23]</ref> They might also have connected them with Elizabeth's crab-wise journey towards signing the death-warrant of Mary Queen of Scots. The play seems designed to prevent comparisons from hardening into allegory, allusions from implying applications. </p>
						<p n="28">If Edward is a negative example of Elizabeth, what are we to make of Isabella? Her very name would have had a special resonance for an Elizabethan audience, and there were many attempts in the period to analyse her behaviour, to ask if her rebellion was justified, to investigate the power-relations in her involvement with Mortimer.<ref target="emls3-2kaymarln24">[24]</ref> In Marlowe's version, her subjection to Mortimer also constitutes a warning, and involves the danger of a Protectorate: he tells her, <q direct="y">erect your son with all the speed we may . . . that I may be protector over him</q> (5.2.11-12). </p>
						<p n="29">The focus of the play is partly on the king himself, of course. And as such it poses a negative example, an opposite model of monarchy from the one Elizabeth was acting out. But it also investigates the predicament of those who have to live under a monarch who thwarts expectations and repudiates convention. Marlowe's play is an anthology of career moves for the Elizabethan courtier: the range stretches from those who are presented as honourably negotiating the conflicts of loyalty implicit in the courtier's life -- Pembroke and Leicester -- through those who succumb to their pressures -- Warwick, Kent, Arundel -- to those who are fatally drawn to the centres of power, in order to literalise the metaphoric eroticism of service and duty. For Gaveston, Spencer and Mortimer, the opening allegory of Actaeon is actualised in their experience as a salutary warning to future ages. </p>
						<p n="30">But as Debra Belt has shown, Marlowe's is a highly self-conscious art, in which acts of speech and of interpretation are shown to be complex and interlocking. If one version of the Elizabethan ideal in the play is the young Edward III, virginal, ruthless, and decisive, then perhaps Marlowe's own ambiguities are understandable. It is as if he has taken to heart Spencer's advice to Baldock <q direct="y">You must cast the scholar off / And learn to court it like a gentleman</q> (2.1.31-2). Marlowe approaches Diana more obliquely than Mortimer or Gaveston; in so doing he produces in <title level="m">Edward II</title> one of the most charged and subtle dramatic engagements on the public stage with the cult of Elizabeth.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>Notes</head>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln1">1. Summers, <q direct="y">Sex, Politics, and Self-Realisation in <title level="m">Edward II</title>
							</q> (222). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln2">2. My focus will therefore be rather different from that of such writers as James Voss (522-3), which draws attention to the indications of the development of a money economy, as in the giving Mortimer the seal to raise cash for the ransom, using up treasury fund so that he can't support armies. </note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln3">3. Alan Sinfield, <q direct="y">Power and Ideology.</q>
						</note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln4">4. See Williams' <title level="m">The Tudor Regime</title> (428-51). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln5">5. See Naunton's <title level="m">Fragmenta Regalia</title> (40-41). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln6">6. In Marcus' <title level="m">Puzzling Shakespeare.</title>
						</note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln7">7. Somerset (490). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln8">8. <q direct="y">liberality (as Aristotle saith) is a measure, as well in giving as in taking of money and goods. And he is only liberal, which distributeth according to his substance, and where it is expedient . . . liberality taketh his name of the substance of the person from who it proceedeth; for it resteth not in the quantity or quality of things that be given, but in the natural disposition of the giver</q> (Elyot, <title level="m">The Governor </title>130). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln9">9. Sir Thomas Craig, <title level="m">The Right of Succession to the Kingdom of England</title> (1603; 1703 ed.; 179); cited by Collins (108). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln10">10. Belt (138). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln11">11. See, among others, King's <title level="m">Spenser's Poetry and the Reformation Tradition</title> (151-2), and also his <title level="m">Tudor Royal Iconography</title> (259-61). For connections between the cult of Diana and the idea of empire see Knapp's <title level="m">An Empire Nowhere (</title>42-3, 47-9, 55, 57, 90). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln12">12. Sometime a lovelie boy in Dians shape With haire that gilds the water as it glides, Crownets of pearle about his naked armes, And in his sportfull hands an Olive tree, To hide those part which men delight to see, Shall bathe him in a spring, and there hard by, One like Actaeon peeping through the grove, Shall by the angire goddesse be transformde, And running in the likenes of an Hart, By yelping houndes pulde downe, and seeme to die. </note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln13">13. Lindsay had argued that man's natural role was to have <q direct="y">preheminens And wemen vnder obediens</q> (<title level="m">Dialogue of Monarchy</title> 106). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln14">14. Cited by Williams (70). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln15">15. Francis Bacon, <title level="m">In Felicem Memoriam</title> (vi. 317). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln16">16. Summers (221-40) argues eloquently for the power and intensity of the relationship between the King and Gaveston as a <q direct="y">world well lost.</q> He cites Edward's and Gaveston's words of love <q direct="y">Despite of time, despite of enemies;</q>
							<q direct="y">Because he loves me more than all the world,</q> and sees Edward as a tragic victim of an <q direct="y">anal crucificion,</q> in contrast to the <q direct="y">cynical world of power politics symbolized by Mortimer and Isabella, whose love </q>hatcheth death and hate.<q direct="y"> His approach is altogether more sophisticated than the simple moralism of Sharon Tyler, who concludes that </q>disaster results when politics becomes an extension of sex<q direct="y"> (66). </q>
						</note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln17">17. In <title level="m">Edward II</title>, the promise of social mobility challenges the traditional assumptions of a natural congruence between social and real identity, <q direct="y">. . . a world of social fluidity and class conflict . . . .</q>
						</note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln18">18. More specifically, the cedar was commonly used by James I (as in <title level="m">Cymbeline</title>). Later Mortimer hubristically asserts <q direct="y">I stand as Jove's huge tree.</q>
						</note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln19">19. Berry (95-100); see also Axton and Bates. </note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln20">20. Dudgale (i.249a). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln21">21. See Bates' <title level="m">The Rhetoric of Courtship in Elizabethan Language and Literature</title>. </note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln22">
							<lg>
								<l>22. This letter written by a friend of ours</l>
								<l>Contains his death yet bids them save his life. </l>
								<l>
									<q direct="y">Edwardum occidere nolite timere bonum est</q>: </l>
								<l>
									<q direct="y">Fear not to kill the king, 'tis good he die.</q>
								</l>
								<l>But read it thus, and that's another sense </l>
								<l>
									<q direct="y">Edwardum occidere nolite timere bonum est</q>: </l>
								<l>
									<q direct="y">Kill not the king, 'tis good to fear the worst.</q>
								</l>
								<l>Unpointed as it is, thus shall it go, </l>
								<l>That being dead, if it chance to be found, </l>
								<l>Matrevis and the rest may bear the blame, </l>
								<l>And we be quit that caused it to be done. (5.4) </l>
							</lg>
							<p>Patterson (Chapter I), Bourdieu (5-9), and Bates (12-14); I also have in mind studies like Marcus' <q direct="y">Textual Indeterminacy and Indeterminacy and ideological Difference: The Case of <title level="m">Doctur Faustus</title>
								</q> and Bartels' <q direct="y">Authorizing Subversion: Strategies of Power in Marlowe's <title level="m">Doctor Faustus.</title>
								</q>
							</p>
						</note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln23">23. A recent instance is found in Debra Belt's <q direct="y">Anti-Theatricalism and Rhetoric in Marlowe's <title level="m">Edward II</title>
							</q>; she argues for <q direct="y">a play about rhetoric and its effects on audience</q> (135), and calls it <q direct="y">an examination of how speaking acts on audiences (among whom the King is the principal but not the only target)</q> (142ff.). Further, she notes that <q direct="y">Practically all the major secular charges levelled against the drama . . . find their way into <title level="m">Edward II</title>
							</q> (150). <q direct="y">The play seems deliberately constructed to demonstrate the complexity of the issue and so to challenge the assumptions of all parties to the controversy</q> (156). <q direct="y">The experience of <title level="m">Edward II</title> . . . gives the viewer both a felt sense of the need for informed judgement on the part of spectator and an awareness of what that process entails. The viewer's task, deciding which factions to favour and why, bears a striking resemblance to that facing the young Prince; consequence of the critique of antitheatricality through the device of a concession is to discourage symplistic or reductive judgments.</q>
						</note>
						<note id="emls3-2kaymarln24">24. See Levin (113-33).</note>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<listBibl>
							<head>Works Cited </head>
							<bibl>Axton, Marie. <title level="m">The Queen's Two Bodies: Drama and the Elizabethan Succession</title>. London: The Royal Historical Society, 1977.</bibl>
							<bibl>Bacon, Francis. <title level="m">In Felicem Memoriam</title>. [Volume 6 of <title level="m">The Works of Francis Bacon</title>.] London: Longmans, 1870.</bibl>
							<bibl>Bartels, Emily C. <title level="a">Authorizing Subversion: Strategies of Power in Marlowe's <title level="m">Doctor Faustus</title>.</title>
								<title level="m">Renaissance Papers</title> (1989): 65-74.</bibl>
							<bibl>Bates, Catherine. <title level="m">The Rhetoric of Courtship in Elizabethan Language and Literature</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1992.</bibl>
							<bibl>Belt, Debra. <title level="a">Anti-Theatricalism and Rhetoric in Marlowe's <title level="m">Edward II</title>.</title>
								<title level="j">English Literary Renaissance</title> 21 (1991): 134-66.</bibl>
							<bibl>Berry, Edward I. <title level="m">Shakespeare's Comic Rites</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1984.</bibl>
							<bibl>Bourdieu, Pierre. <title level="m">Les regles de l'art: genese et structure du champ litteraire</title>. Paris: Editions du seuil, 1992.</bibl>
							<bibl>Collins, Stephen L. <title level="m">From Divine Cosmos to Sovereign State: An Intellectual History of Consciousness and the Idea of Order in Renaissance England</title>. New York: Oxford UP, 1989.</bibl>
							<bibl>Dudgale, William. <title level="m">The Antiquities of Warwickshire Illustrated</title>. Vol. 1. Ed. William Thomas. [2 vols.] London, 1730.</bibl>
							<bibl>Elyot, Thomas. <title level="m">The Boke Named the Governor</title>. Ed. S. G. Lehmberg. Everyman 227. London: Dent, 1962.</bibl>
							<bibl>King, John N. <title level="m">Spenser's Poetry and the Reformation Tradition</title>. Princeton: Princeton UP, 1990.</bibl>
							<bibl>---. <title level="m">Tudor Royal Iconography</title>. Princeton: Princeton UP, 1990.</bibl>
							<bibl>Knapp, Jeffrey. <title level="m">An Empire Nowhere: England, America and Literature from <title level="m">Utopia</title> to <title level="m">The Tempest</title>
								</title>. Berkeley: U of California P, 1992.</bibl>
							<bibl>Levin, Carole. <title level="a">John Foxe and the Responsibilities of Queenship.</title>
								<title level="m">Women in the Middle Ages and the Renaissance: Literary and Historical Perspectives</title>. 13-33 in Mary Beth Rose, ed. Syracuse: Syracuse UP, 1986.</bibl>
							<bibl>Lindsay, David. <title level="m">Dialogue of Monarchy</title>. Ed. J. Small. London, 1883.</bibl>
							<bibl>Marcus, Leah. <title level="a">Textual Indeterminacy and Ideological Difference: The Case of <title level="m">Doctor Faustus</title>.</title>
								<title level="j">Renaissance Drama</title> 20 (1989): 1-29.</bibl>
							<bibl>---. <title level="m">Puzzling Shakespeare: Local Reading and Its Discontents</title>. Berkeley: U of California P, 1988.</bibl>
							<bibl>Naunton, Robert. <title level="m">Fragmenta Regalia or Observations on Queen Elizzabeth, Her Times and Favourites</title>. Ed. John S. Cerovski. Washington: Folger Shakespeare Library, 1985.</bibl>
							<bibl>Patterson, Annabel. <title level="m">Censorship and Interpretation</title>. Madison: U of Wisconsin P, 1984.</bibl>
							<bibl>Sinfield, Alan. <title level="a">Power and Ideology: An Outline Theory and Sidney's Arcadia.</title>
								<title level="j">English Literary History</title> 52 (1985): 259-77.</bibl>
							<bibl>Somerset, Anne. <title level="m">Elizabeth I</title>. 2nd edition. London: Weidenfeld and Nicolson, 1992.</bibl>
							<bibl>Summers, Claude J. <title level="a">Sex, Politics, and Self-Realisation in <title level="m">Edward II</title>.</title> 221-40 in K. Friedenreich, R. Gill and C. Kuriyama, eds. <title level="m">
									<title level="a">A Poet and a Filthy Play-Maker</title>: New Essays on Christopher Marlowe</title>. New York: AMS P, 1989.</bibl>
							<bibl>Tyler, Sharon. <title level="a">Bedfellows make Strange Politics: Christopher Marlowe's <title level="m">Edward II</title>.</title> 55-68 in J. Redmond, ed. <title level="m">Drama, Sex, and Politics</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1985.</bibl>
							<bibl>Voss, James. <title level="a">
									<title level="m">Edward II</title>: Marlowe's Historical Tragedy.</title>
								<title level="j">English Studies</title> 63 (1982): 517-30.</bibl>
							<bibl>Williams, Penry. <title level="m">The Tudor Regime</title>. Oxford: Oxford UP, 1979.</bibl>
							<bibl>Williams, Neville. <title level="m">All the Queen's Men: Elizabeth I and Her Courtiers</title>. 2nd edition. London: Cardinal, 1974.</bibl>
						</listBibl>
						<p>Responses to this piece intended for the Readers' Forum may be sent to the Editor at <!-- <a href="mailto:emls@ualberta.ca"> -->EMLS@UAlberta.ca<!-- </a> -->.</p>
					</div3>
					<byline>
						<!-- <a href="../emlshome.html" alt="emls home page"> -->
						<!-- <img src="../button.gif" width="124" height="47"> -->
						<!-- </a> -->
						<!-- <a href="../emlscopy.html"> -->&copy;<!-- </a> --> 1997-, R.G. Siemens (Editor, <title level="j">EMLS</title>). (DK, SL, RGS, 6 October 1997) </byline>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls3-2fittnoct" n="2" type="article">
					<head>The Poetic Nocturne: From Ancient Motif to Renaissance Genre</head>
					<opener>
						<name>Chris Fitter</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>Rutgers University, Camden</addrLine>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href="mailto:fitter@crab.rutgers.edu"> -->fitter@crab.rutgers.edu<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
						<!-- <img src="../header2.gif" alt="early" modern literary studies height=87 width=283> -->
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Fitter, Chris. <title level="a">The Poetic Nocturne: From Ancient Motif to Renaissance Genre.</title>
						<title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 3.2 (September, 1997): 2.1-61 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/03-2/fittnoct.html"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/03-2/fittnoct.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;.</p>
					<div3>
						<head>Introduction</head>
						<p n="1">
							<q direct="y">Wizards know their times,</q> Bolingbroke assures Dame Eleanor, in <title level="m">2 Henry VI</title>, as they prepare to conjure a Spirit from hell. <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Deep night, dark night, the silent of the night,</l>
									<l>The time when screech-owls cry, and bandogs howl,</l>
									<l>And spirits walk, and ghosts break up their graves;</l>
									<l>That time best fits the work we have in hand.</l>
								</lg>
							</q>Less than a century later, in stunning contradiction, John Norris of Bemerton's <q direct="y">Hymn to Darkness</q> (published 1687) serenely lauds night as rapturous and benign, agent equally of highest holiness and poetic inspiration.<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>But thee I now admire, thee would I chuse</l>
									<l>For my Religion or my Muse.</l>
									<l>Tis hard to tell whether thy reverend shade</l>
									<l>Has more good Votaries or Poets made,</l>
									<l>From thy dark caves were Inspirations given</l>
									<l>And from thick groves went vows to Heaven.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn1">[1]</ref>
									</l>
								</lg>
							</q>Norris is here celebrating (and consolidating) the emergence of a new literary genre, the poetic nocturne: one intent on refiguring those cold, dead and sunless hours feared by most of mankind over millennia into an order of exquisite and numinous experience. The genre of poetic nocturne, then, needs dating not to the eighteenth century and the verse of such as Parnell, Young and Gray as has literary history hitherto, but to the Renaissance: whose poetry, masques and painting, in revaluing night as a time of beauty and profundity, overturn, I will argue, the construction predominant in classical and medieval traditions. Those earlier approaches themselves, Greek, Roman, biblical, patristic and medieval, have never been systematically investigated for their representation of night. This paper, accordingly, will seek to sketch a basic poetic tradition, and its elevation to independent genre, hitherto uncharted: from whose Renaissance productions eighteenth-century and Romantic writing will often derive, and at whose heart lie Shakespeare, Jonson, and perhaps above all, the lyric but combative genius of Milton.</p>
						<p n="2">The survey discovers a standard repertoire of nocturnal motifs, and a quintessential ambivalence, which each maintain substantial continuity across ancient and Christian literatures into the Renaissance, although not without historical permutation. Fundamental shifts of emphasis are to be expected, after all, since presentations of natural reality are not mere reflections of deep-seated ecological values, even though some lines may suggest so: dependence on light and fear of darkness, for instance, well caught in Spenser's <q direct="y">Our life is day, but death with darknesse doth begin,</q> in <title level="m">The Faerie Queene</title>, 3.4.59.9. Art's representations derive, rather, from the mediation of such fundamentals through historical social formations. <q direct="y">Natural</q> appearances, as I have suggested elsewhere, and borrowing Reader-Response terminology, are in fact <q direct="y">read</q> by mutable <q direct="y">interpretive communities,</q> each with its distinct <q direct="y">horizons of expectation,</q> no less than are texts. Historical communities, each with their own complex of working material relations with nature, project upon the external world varied structures of attention, <q direct="y">fresh priorities of need and desire, and attendant new fronts</q> of visual acuity and familiarity in the manifold of landscapes.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn2">[2]</ref>
							<q direct="y">Ecological</q> responses, in life and art, are thus filtered through <q direct="y">nature-sensibilities</q> formed by social practices, class location and literary convention.</p>
						<p n="3">
							<q direct="y">Night-walking</q> for instance is a crime for the medieval commoner (a royal charter of 1347 granted Bristol the right to imprison nightwalkers, for their motivation could only be felonous), but becomes a pious and aesthetic convention for the well-to-do, urban scholar in the century that invented the recreative stroll: as is evident from <title level="m">II Penseroso</title>. Again, we shall see how, in antiquity, sophisticated, metropolitan poets of the Hellenistic and Roman imperial period pen an <q direct="y">aesthetic</q> refiguring of night, along with other elemental experience, reworking mythological themes within a poised, sceptical climate: precisely as Elizabethan and Stuart writers will confect primitive medieval horrors with self-consciously suave rational superiority into a field of delicate antiquarian whimsy. With the decline of humanistic self-confidence in late antiquity, however, a <q direct="y">vertical imagination</q> develops, majestically acclaiming the starry spaces in derogation of this puny, sinful earth. When, with the Renaissance, humanism is reborn, construction of night's meaning, moral status and empiric appearances will in England be caught up in the ideological collisions of that era, and articulated increasingly along adversarial lines of <q direct="y">Puritan</q> and <q direct="y">courtly</q> discourse. It is, perhaps, precisely in attempted transcendence of such sectarian division that Norris' poem quoted above, seeks, like the philosophy of the Cambridge Platonists with whom he was affiliated, to establish an eirenic, common ground of sacramentality: one he attempts to locate in the mystery of holiness, diffidently occult, encountered in nocturnal darkness. <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>The Vision of the Deity is made</l>
									<l>More sweet and Beatifick by thy shade.</l>
									<l>But we poor tenants of this Orb below</l>
									<l>Don't here thy excellencies know,</l>
									<l>Till Death our understandings does improve,</l>
									<l>And then our Wiser ghosts thy silent <emph rend="italics">night-walks love</emph>. [italics mine]</l>
								</lg>
							</q>Night-walking, then, once criminalised as a menace to social order, may now prove a ground of its conciliative recovery.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>Classical Traditions</head>
						<p n="4">The ancient Mediterranean peoples generally retired to bed soon after sunset in order to rise with the sun. Street lighting seems not to have been common, though we know some large cities (like Antioch) attempted it in some measure. Terminating each day's life, and with an abruptness unfamiliar to more northerly climes, night is consequently and very deeply associated with death. In the <title level="m">Iliad</title>, Apollo, arrows clanging on his back as he drops from Olympus in fury to slaughter Danaans, is said to fall <q direct="y">like the night.</q> When the Trojans hem the Greeks against their ships and Hector breaches their ramparts, to the terrified enemy he bursts in <q direct="y">with a look like nightfall on his face.</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn3">[3]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="5">By logical extension, night is associated with the horror of the underworld, Tartarus, and brings to mortals not only sleep but a twin-brother, Death: siblings familiar long after to Renaissance philosophers and sculpted by Michelangelo.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn4">[4]</ref> Along with death-like darkness, night stands as the master-metaphor for a range of fears: she gave birth, says Hesiod, to Pain and Deceit, Murder and Lawlessness, sad Age and Strife. Further associations include demonology (the time of witches like Horace's Canidia in <title level="m">Epode</title> five or the cannibalistic Erictho of Lucan's <title level="m">Pharsalia</title> who <q direct="y">never appeared abroad in daylight and quitted the tombs only on wet or cloudy nights, when she went to catch and bottle whatever lightning happened to fall</q>), and criminality. Night is the time for thieves, daylight for honesty, notes Euripides; and Horace concurs: <q direct="y">By nightime sin, and cloak thy sin with clouds.</q> The very stillness of the world of night induces fear, states Valerius Flaccus.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn5">[5]</ref> In Roman Republican poetry, virtually the only references to night come in Tragedy, where it represents the condition of misfortune.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn6">[6]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="6">Counterposing these four motifs of negative night -- criminality, demonology, darkness, and night as a general figure of oppression -- are a number, however, of positive motifs. In a society moving upon simple agricultural rhythms, the failing of light means the ending of toil, the grateful homeward trudge of dispersed workers and family. In a surviving fragment Sappho praises Hesperus, the evening star, for <q direct="y">bringing back all things which bright dawn scattered; you bring the sheep, you bring the goat, you bring the child back to its mother.</q> Praise of night as the hours of comfort, in which the labourer bathes his limbs in the bliss of sleep, will become standard to Roman evocation of the exemplary <emph rend="italics">vetus colonus</emph>. Moreover in Archaic Greece, whose nature-sensibility <q direct="y">read</q> natural and human life as an essential continuum of energies, their processes interacting and mutually articulating, sleep could be projected across nocturnal landscape itself. <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Asleep are the peaks and watercourses of the mountains,</l>
									<l>the headlands and ravines, all creeping things which</l>
									<l>the black earth feeds, wild beasts and the race of the</l>
									<l>bees, and monsters in the depths of the dark sea; asleep</l>
									<l>are the tribes of the broad-winged birds.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn7">[7]</ref>
									</l>
								</lg>
							</q>In so unified a conception of the world, it is in metaphor that reality is transcribed.</p>
						<p n="7">Respite from labour, sleep, peace: night's deep calm of health is so deeply felt that nocturnal description may turn ironic backdrop to pain and peril -- to precisely the qualities, parodoxically, that in the negative topoi it had itself figured. In Sappho's lyrics, for instance, nocturnal peace highlights the lonely anguish of the lovelorn: <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Now she is preeminent among the Lydian women, as</l>
									<l>when the sun has set, the rosy-fingered moon surpasses</l>
									<l>all the stars. It throws its light over the salt sea, and</l>
									<l>equally over the richly flowered fields. The lovely dew</l>
									<l>falls, the roses bloom . . . And often she walks up and down</l>
									<l>remembering gentle Atthis with desire in her tender heart,</l>
									<l>and her soul is devoured by longing.</l>
								</lg>
							</q>Objectifying the delicate rapture of the lover's feeling, such nocturne simultaneously establishes the pitch of her suffering, by constituting night as the order of natural harmony from which she is sleeplessly in exile. Virgil likewise draws night as a paradise of health hushed in the serenity of sleep from which lonely Dido is expelled. <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>it was night, and tired creatures all over the world</l>
									<l>were enjoying kindly sleep. Forests and fierce seas were</l>
									<l>at rest, as the circling constellations glided in their</l>
									<l>midnight course. Every field, all the farm animals, and the</l>
									<l>colourful birds were silent, all that lived across</l>
									<l>miles of glassy mere and in the wild country's ragged</l>
									<l>brakes, lying still, under the quiet night in a sleep which</l>
									<l>smoothed each care away from hearts which had forgotten</l>
									<l>life's toil. But not so the Phoenician queen . . . .</l>
								</lg>
							</q>This passage is the direct inspiration of sonnets by Petrarch and Surrey, a millennium and a half later.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn8">[8]</ref> The genius of Homer merges both traditions of feeling, night as a state of siege and as a bliss of suspended animation, in a single dazzling simile closing book eight of the <title level="m">Iliad</title>:<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>There are nights when the upper air is windless and</l>
									<l>the stars in heaven stand out in their full splendour</l>
									<l>round the bright moon; when every mountain-top, headland</l>
									<l>and ravine starts into sight, as the infinite depths of</l>
									<l>the sky are torn open to the very firmament; when every</l>
									<l>star is seen, and the shepherd rejoices. Such and so many</l>
									<l>were the Trojans' fires, twinkling in front of Ilium midway</l>
									<l>between the ships and the streams of Xanthus.</l>
								</lg>
							</q>The ambiguity which Homer masterfully constructs here, windless nocturnal peace fused with rousing, abnormal brilliance, connects just the ambivalence we have seen toward night, with the conflicting feelings of the combatants: grateful for calm and respite, they are also pierced by a drama sharp upon the nerves.</p>
						<p n="8">Kindred in tone to this state of enchanted expectation is the association of night with deep mystery, and with a certain religious emotion. The Muses go by night to hymn the supreme gods, declares Hesiod in the <title level="m">Theogony</title> (10). Dionysus explains to Pentheus in the <title level="m">Bacchae</title> (485) that by night the Maenads celebrate, since darkness promotes religious awe. Mystic rites, echoes Horace, four hundred years later, are to be performed in night's deep silence (<title level="m">Epode</title> 5, 49-52).</p>
						<p n="9">A cluster of positive motifs, then -- night as signifying respite from toil, the luxury of sleep, an order of peace often the foil to lovers' woe, and the occasion of religious rite or vision -- proves stable and recurrent in classical literature from Archaic Greece to Rome. With Hellenistic Greece and early imperial Rome, however, a very new cultural climate has transformed relations with nature, and with them, established both the primacy of <q direct="y">positive</q> night and an altered field of nocturnal tones. Briefly and very generally, as is inescapable in an overview, one may say that the nature-sensibility of Archaic Greece, in which <q direct="y">amechania</q> or the sense of helplessness in a world of uncontrollable and mysterious natural forces left deep impress on literature, gave way in the Classical period to the confidence of an emergent scientific rationalism, which diminished nature from a volatile, semi-animate ocean of forces to <q direct="y">physis</q>: a finite corpus of laws open to human apprehension and control. The catastrophic end of the Peloponnesian wars gave a final blow to the Archaic concept of the coherence of the physical and moral worlds, so that with the rise of the intensely urban Hellenistic civilisation and of a certain technological mastery of nature, the earth dwindled into the <q direct="y">countryside</q>: a welcome complement to human life and a pristine space of metropolitan recreation.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn9">[9]</ref> The temper of the cultivated class was now intensely sceptical: <q direct="y">Determined efforts were made to define the gods in terms acceptable to men who were basically sceptical about their existence.</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn10">[10]</ref> Demystifying mythology as simply a sublimation of long-past mortal action and character, the Greek philosopher Euhemerus became a classical equivalent of the best-seller; Juvenal would observe in his second satire that not even children believed in Hades any more. What we might call <q direct="y">post-mythic night</q> was now crafted, in veins of elegance and soft primitivism, by <q direct="y">neoteroi,</q> the same <q direct="y">revolutionizing</q> poets who introduced pastoral verse and materialist landscape description. These three novelties, I suggest, are cognate epistemic and poetic developments: each the product of urban rationalism's confident, secular and sentimentalising nostalgia for the elemental.</p>
						<p n="10">Pastoral verse, developed by Theocritus and Virgil for sophisticated courts, portrayed rustic scenes with an artful and artificial affection. Virgil's <title level="m">Eclogues</title> (1, 2, 6, 10) establish a conventional nightfall close for pastoral that will be echoed over millennia (still found in Spenser's <title level="m">Shepherd's Calendar</title>, for instance, and Milton's <title level="m">Lycidas</title>): they concretize the old theme of gratitude for concluded labour in poignant homely images of lengthening mountain shadows, returning oxen, the folding of flocks and smoke rising from cottage chimneys. Panofsky finely notes the new tone here, observing that Virgil's evenings settle silently <q direct="y">in that vespertinal mixture of sadness and tranquillity which is perhaps Virgil's most personal contribution to poetry.</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn11">[11]</ref> Evening in the <title level="m">Georgics</title> is likewise mellow and unthreatening, a new music of humanism: sunset brings welcome cool, the evening star dew, and the moon rises quietly over shores whose copses ring with the notes of kingfisher and finches (3.336-38).</p>
						<p n="11">Moon and stars had traditionally enjoyed significance in antiquity as markers of annual time. In Homer's era, the period of the full moon was a time for festivals; with the first full moon of the summer solstice came the Olympian Games; and a full moon was long considered an auspicious time for marriages. Calendar verse such as Hesiod's <title level="m">Works and Days</title> and treatises on agriculture by Cato and Varro timed their tasks by the rising and setting of stars and constellations rather than by the months of the calendar, which could never be precisely counted upon. But with the <q direct="y">aestheticising</q> culture of poets like Apollonius Rhodios, busily developing landscape description and imitating the celebrated delicacy of <emph rend="italics">chiaroscuro</emph> effects by painters like Antipholus, moonlight touches came to service a vogue for the exquisite. Hylas is pulled to his death by a naiad when she sees him suddenly transformed into a radiant image by the full moon shining from a cloudless sky. As Jason hugs his golden fleece, its shimmer throws a glow on his cheeks and forehead, and he rejoices as a girl who catches sudden moonlight on her silken gown in her lonely attic. Virgil evokes moonlight dancing on a rippling sea; and the thoughts of his Aeneas leap like the flash of a moon's rays from water swaying in a basin. Such fastidious nocturnal optics contrast sharply with a certain traditional insouciance: Homer, for instance, had conceived the Palace of Alcinous as lit by a radiance <q direct="y">like that of the sun <emph rend="italics">or the moon</emph>
							</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn12">[12]</ref> [italics mine]. From a Hellenistic poet, such indiscrimination would have been taken as barbarous.</p>
						<p n="12">The new nocturne of the urbanely poised finds particular frisson in night's old occult deeps. Mis-en-sc&egrave;ne of magic and theophany, night is the medium by which Tiber makes his momentous appearance to Aeneas. Theocritus' Simaetha casts a sinister folk-spell on her faithless lover by the light of the moon, while the barking of dogs tells of Hecate's approach. Ovid's Medea, up to similar business, apostrophises likewise night, stars and Hecate, and supplies an occasion for extended description. <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>All alone she wandered out into the deep stillness</l>
									<l>of midnight. Men, birds and beasts were sunk in profound</l>
									<l>repose; there was no sound in the hedgerows; the leaves</l>
									<l>hung mute and motionless; the dewy air was still. Only</l>
									<l>the stars twinkled. Stretching up her arms to these, she</l>
									<l>turned thrice about, thrice sprinkled water . . . and thrice</l>
									<l>gave tongue in wailing cries. <ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn13">[13]</ref>
									</l>
								</lg>
							</q>
						</p>
						<p n="13">The scepticism underlying such agreeable baroque, along with the Trimalchian nightlife of the great Roman courts, freed empiric nocturnal definition for the new positive motif of night as carousing time. Theocritus' lads come drunkenly visiting lasses by torchlight, and mystic Dionysus is shrunk by bibulous Rome to <q direct="y">jolly Bacchus</q> and a riotous crew of nymphs and satyrs.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn14">[14]</ref>
							<emph rend="italics">This</emph>
							<q direct="y">night-haunting god,</q> in Seneca's phrase (<title level="m">Oedipus</title> 490), presides over a colourfully festive night that the Renaissance eventually revived; one whose eroticism moreover established with Ovid one further new motif of great future currency: the <emph rend="italics">aubade</emph>. Ovid's lament of stealthy lovers over night's cruel brevity would be greatly elaborated from a few lines in the <title level="m">Amores</title> (1.13.110-19) by such master-poets as Chaucer and Donne.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn15">[15]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="14">Finally, in late antiquity, influenced by a sense, in Dodds' words, of <q direct="y">the progressive withdrawal of divinity from the material world,</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn16">[16]</ref> Christianity and many pagan religions alike reconceived night yet again. Orphism exposited night as holy to the supreme deity of secret wisdom, the universal first cause, hidden in blackness and to be worshiped only in the sanctity of silence. Christianity's <emph rend="italics">contemptus mundi</emph> similarly exalted the night as revealing to humanity the celestial landscape of the heavens, contrasting dark sublunar misery with God's stupendous cosmic frame and brilliant luminaries. Monastic tradition was to admire moonlight not for its scenic effects but because the moon symbolized the highest mysteries. Late Stoicism's worship of the stars combined with a widely shared reverence for astrology. Plato, Seneca and Boethius, among others, bequeathed Christianity superb passages on the mighty spaces above our heads, the splendid and religious order of the starry heavens. In this climate, the emperor Julian records his ecstasy in walking in starlight as a stimulus that helped convert him to paganism, whilst for Christians God became <figure entity="fitterm"/>
							<!-- <img src="fitter_mh.gif" alt="'most high'" height=17 width=58> -->, the <q direct="y">Most High.</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn17">[17]</ref> As such, it became possible for the question whether day or night is better, to develop as a standard debating topic in medieval universities. Centuries later, Cambridge would require Milton to adopt a stance on this for his first Prolusion.</p>
						<p n="15">As the Roman empire broke gradually apart, however, amid escalating demonological and barbarian terrors, night's overwhelmingly predominant meaning in the common imagination was active as a time of ghosts, witches and assault, the realm of Lucifer, Prince of Darkness. As an advanced commercial and rational civilisation relapsed into the archaic political economy of agrarian regionalism, Christian culture resumed the intensely negative construction of night produced in early, agrarian Greece.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>Biblical and Medieval Traditions</head>
						<p n="16">Biblical tradition supplied the same deeply negative assessment of the hours of darkness, although within the familiar ambivalence of sharply subordinate positive motifs. <q direct="y">A servant earnestly desires the shadow</q> notes <title level="a" rend="italics">Job</title> 7.2, mindful of the evening respite from toil for which <title level="a" rend="italics">Psalm</title> 104.23 also gives thanks; as does Ambrose in a hymn which comforts Augustine in <title level="m">The Confessions</title> (9.12). <title level="m">Canticles</title> sings of night as the time of holy love, praising the fairness of the moon (4.2, 6.10). Night is the time of divine visitation or the granting of religious wisdom: for <q direct="y">night unto night sheweth knowledge</q> (<title level="a" rend="italics">Psalm</title> 19.2). <q direct="y">When I consider thy heavens, the work of thy fingers</q> meditates the Psalmist, with dramatic eloquence, <q direct="y">The moon and the stars, which thou hast ordained; / What is man that thou art mindful of him?</q> (<title level="a" rend="italics">Psalm</title> 8.3-4).<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn18">[18]</ref> But the fear of evening and nightfall is frequently expressed:<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn19">[19]</ref> they may bring <q direct="y">the thief in the night</q> (1 <title level="a" rend="italics">Thessalonians</title> 5.2) or worse, divine retribution as in <title level="a" rend="italics">Job</title> 36.20. Worst of all, by night was Christ betrayed by Judas; night thus connotes the distinct agonies of hell (eternal darkness) and of Gethsemane.</p>
						<p n="17">Predictably, Anglo-Saxon culture, agrarian, war-swept and melancholy, is haunted by nightfear. In <title level="m">Beowulf</title>, Grendel is characterised as <q direct="y">greatest of night-evils</q> (<q direct="y">niht-bealwa maest</q>). He glides, we are twice told, toward Heorot for slaughterous spree with the onset of night. In <q direct="y">The Dream of the Rood,</q> it is with nightfall that the Christ-Earl's corpse is lamented over, his thanes <q direct="y">earme on &thorn;a &aelig;fentide</q> (<q direct="y">wretched in the evening</q>).<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn20">[20]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="18">Indeed virtually no-one, it seems (with the exception of Virgil), was ever able prior to the Renaissance to enjoy the onset of evening for its physical reality. In Middle English, whilst <q direct="y">este</q> could mean <q direct="y">pleasant</q> as well as <q direct="y">east,</q>
							<q direct="y">weste</q> meant not only <q direct="y">west</q> but <q direct="y">desolate</q> (see ll. 999-1000 of <title level="m">The Owl and the Nightingale</title>.) The Greeks and Romans had never been moved to imagine and revere a goddess of eve, to match Aurora goddess of dawn. They looked forward only, and eagerly, to Vesper, the evening star, restorative of perished light. Indeed tellingly in the <title level="m">Iliad</title>, it had been Achilles' spearpoint, searching out Hector's flesh in their terminal combat, that was said to scintillate like the evening star: the last, literally poignant point of light before the great engulfing blackness. It took, as Aretino<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn21">[21]</ref> confessed, Titian's genius for colour for poets to <q direct="y">discover</q> the sunset: classical and medieval sunsets were purely mythological, the horses of the sun plunging inexorably into the Western waters. The sole, mild exception known to me lies in a lyric of Stesichorus, which has the sun descend into the <q direct="y">golden bowl</q> of the ocean. In the <title level="m">Silvae</title> (2.2.47-48), Statius had praised a certain villa for boasting rooms that could view both sunrise and sunset; yet even he presented the latter merely as lengthening (Virgilian) shadows, not in colourific terms. Rosy light is reserved for dawn. In English, the earliest coloured sunset I have been able to discover is by Gavin Douglas, (circa 1513), in lines 12-15 of his prologue to book 13 of his translation of the <title level="m">Aeneid</title>: where the sun <q direct="y">byrnand red</q> in the evening sky as <q direct="y">The son enfyrit haill</q>: an observation opening an astonishingly anamalous evocation of nocturnal beauty. Shakespeare's <q direct="y">Light thickens; and the crow / Makes wing to th'rooky wood; / Good things of Day begin to droop and drowse, / While Night's black agents to their preys do rouse</q> represents the characteristic vespertinal unease.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn22">[22]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="19">Curfew was imposed in most medieval towns, while in the country, <q direct="y">with hearths smothered for fear of fire . . . the night was spent in a state of physical and mental siege.</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn23">[23]</ref> The Middle Ages well understood why the Bible, in <title level="m">Canticles</title> 3.8 and <title level="a" rend="italics">Psalm</title> 91.5, had spoken evocatively of the terror that grips by night. <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Nou goth sonne under wod </l>
									<l>Me reweth, &thorn;i faire rode;</l>
									<l>Nou goth sonne under tre</l>
									<l>Me reweth, Marie, &thorn;i sone and &thorn;e.</l>
								</lg>
							</q>Only evil things travel by night, as the Nightingale tartly reminds the Owl; and a <q direct="y">nightwalker</q> was one who roamed at night for criminal purposes: like Grendel, defined as a <q direct="y">sceadu-genga.</q> Shakespeare's Falstaff and Autolycus thus make merry of their profession as <q direct="y">Diana's foresters, gentlemen of the shade</q> who as <q direct="y">The pale moon shines by night . . . wander here and there</q>; and <q direct="y">night-walking</q> is used as a term for thieving or possibly prostitution in <title level="m">Richard III</title>.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn24">[24]</ref> By night Tarquin rapes Lucrece, when <q direct="y">pure thoughts are dead and still.</q>
						</p>
						<p n="20">
							<q direct="y">Night-spells</q> or popular charms were recited at doors and windows at nightfall as protection against harm from <q direct="y">elves or wights,</q> as glimpsed in Chaucer's <q direct="y">Miller's Tale</q> (3480-860) and E.K.'s gloss on Spenser's <title level="m">Shepherd's Calendar</title> (to <q direct="y">March</q> line 54). In the streets outside, the night watch was sometimes expressly prohibited by medieval guilds from trying to summon ghosts. As late as the 16th and 17th centuries, peasant agrarian cults in backward areas of Italy, Switzerland and Germany were still dispatching vigilante <q direct="y">benandanti</q> or <q direct="y">good</q> nightwalkers, (perhaps in dreams or cataleptic states), to confront assumed witches in symbolic nocturnal battles four times a year.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn25">[25]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="21">Conventional complaints against night recur in <title level="m">The Faerie Queene</title> (3.4.55-58) and <title level="m">The Rape of Lucrece</title> (764-805); Sidney and Spenser are still cataloguing the customary physical and ghoulish ills in <title level="m">Astrophil and Stella</title> (sonnet 96) and <title level="m">Epithalamion</title>: <q direct="y">Let not the shriech oule, nor the storke be heard: / Nor the night Raven that stil deadly yels, / Nor damned ghosts cald up with mighty spels, / Nor griesly vultures make us once afeard . . .</q> (stanza 19). The topos of ugly creatures and howling spirits is widely current (similar passages occur for instance in Marston and Ascham); and the tradition of night as kingdom of the damned finds its way as a lurid melodrama of blasted trees and fitfully lit graves even into the painting of so normally placid an artist as Jacob van Ruisdael, in his seventeenth century <emph rend="italics">Jewish Cemetary</emph>. </p>
						<p n="22">In summary, we can see that the Renaissance inherited from biblical and medieval traditions a mixed lineage, but one overwhelmingly weighted toward the negative. <q direct="y">When any poet would describe a horrible tragic accident,</q> notes Thomas Nashe, <q direct="y">to add the more probability and credence unto it, he dismally beginneth to tell how it was dark night when it was done and cheerful daylight had quite abandoned the firmament . . . Well have the poets termed night the nurse of cares, the mother of despair, the daughter of hell.</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn26">[26]</ref>
						</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>Renaissance Revaluations</head>
						<p n="23">Yet in the English Renaissance, heavily influenced as we shall see by Italian and Dutch pictorialism, night also and paradoxically soared to a cult status of bewitching beauty. Surrey, following the example of Petrarch (<title level="m">Rime</title> 164) lovingly reworked Virgil's nocturnal setting for lovesick Dido as the basis for a still and delicate sonnet (<q direct="y">Alas, so all things now do hold their peace</q>). And from the 1590s we find ravishing syllables on starlight entrancement thronging Shakespeare's plays, for instance, in <title level="m">A Midsummer Night's Dream</title>, <title level="m">The Merchant of Venice</title> and <title level="m">Romeo and Juliet</title>.</p>
						<p n="24">Moreover, night now developed, I think, an independent poetical form of her own: a tradition became a cult, and a topos a genre. From the repertoire of diverse classical, biblical and medieval night themes, hitherto scattered across narratives and lyric poems as subordinate motifs, Milton's <title level="m">Il Penseroso</title>, Vaughan's <q direct="y">The Night</q> and Norris' <q direct="y">Hymn to Darkness</q> cull motifs of peace, contemplation, mortality and serene celestial bodies, and consolidate them into the earliest instances in English of <q direct="y">nocturne</q> as a self-substantial genre.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn27">[27]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="25">To accommodate the enthusiasm, new generic terms were devised. According to the OED, Donne's poem <q direct="y">A Nocturnall upon St. Lucies Day</q> is the first to use the word <q direct="y">nocturnal</q> as a proper noun (deriving perhaps from the <q direct="y">nocturne,</q> late Latin and French, which had been one of the divisions of the office of matins. The adjective <q direct="y">nocturnall</q> usually meant simply <q direct="y">pertaining to the night,</q> and is dated to Caxton and 1485). Likewise, Herrick's <q direct="y">Night-piece, to Julia</q> in <title level="m">The Hesperides</title> (1648) is the first recorded use of the term <q direct="y">night-piece</q> as a title of a literary composition. Ben Jonson had first coined the term <q direct="y">night-piece</q> in 1605 to refer to a painting of night scenery, produced by Inigo Jones for the Queen's <title level="m">Masque of Blacknesse</title>; and Vaughan in <title level="m">Silex Scintillans II</title> (published 1655) compares the melancholy beauty of a friend's recollected death with viewing <q direct="y">some meek night-piece.</q>
						</p>
						<p n="26">Medieval people had never so much enjoyed the living world of the senses as to be fascinated by its mysterious nocturnal transformation, its irregular play of moonlight and suggestive atmospherics; they -- if virtuous -- simply slept through it, taking their <q direct="y">hailsum nychtis rest.</q> The change of attitude, we shall see, owes much to the emergence of a new metropolitan, sceptical and rationalising culture in London and at court; and I would argue that a broad cultural parallel with Hellenistic and Roman antiquity can clearly be established here. <q direct="y">Post-mythic night</q> once more purveys archaic mythological character and motif with delicate ingenuity, recasting an earlier world of the elemental and fearful as a field of ornamental archaism. Vogue for the <q direct="y">romancey</q> and exquisite, haunts both paintings and literary fairy-land: Herrick, for instance, conceives Oberon's grove as <q direct="y">tinseld with Twilight</q> and Queen Mab as <q direct="y">moon-tann'd,</q> while Drayton subjects the casting of midnight spells to parody as Mab trysts with the handsome fairy Pigwiggen.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn28">[28]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="27">Even the character of night melancholy sweetens with the seventeenth century. For Chapman, her <q direct="y">palace</q> had been of <q direct="y">black shades and desolations,</q> but Milton files her habitat as <q direct="y">trim gardens</q> and <q direct="y">glimmering bowers.</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn29">[29]</ref> As <title level="m">Il Penseroso</title> saunters among oaks to observe the riding moon, reminiscing of Greek drama and medieval knight-errantry, his educated calm is that of a Stuart citizen unthreatened by god or ogre, wolf or bear. The night-watchman, he knows, will <q direct="y">bless the doors from nightly harm,</q> and he may thus continue his safe and sophisticated reverie <q direct="y">till civil-suited Morn appear</q> and he re-enter the un-romancey sceptical metropolis.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn30">[30]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="28">Three lines of influence promoting Renaissance poetic nocturne are, I think, the cultural prestige of pictorial breakthroughs in painting night scenery; developments in mystical thought; and the fashionable cult of solitary melancholy. </p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>Pictorialism and the New Empiricism</head>
						<p n="29">With the sixteenth century, European painting could boast bravura studies of night-time <emph rend="italics">chiaroscuro</emph>, and their tone was tender. Panofsky categorises a three-part evolution in naturalism, from the <q direct="y">nocturne negative</q> (pictures giving the effect of night through the omission of colour, like the <q direct="y">Betrayal</q> and the <q direct="y">Crucifixion</q> in the Limbourgs' <emph rend="italics">Tres Riches Heures du Duc de Berri</emph>); through the intermediate stage of the <q direct="y">nocturne positive</q> (where night is suggested through colours different from those of day); to the complete optical authenticity of the <q direct="y">nocturne absolute</q>: for example Geertgen tot Sint Jan's <emph rend="italics">Nativity</emph>.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn31">[31]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="30">The mysterious interim dubiety of dusk had exercised since the late middle ages a comparable emotive and symbolic interest as a zone of transition: both for painters, like the Boucicaut Master, who shows St. Denis martyred before a twilight Paris, and for the <title level="m">Pearl</title>-poet, who in these half-lit minutes witnessed the procession of maidens being led by the Lamb into the Holy City (<title level="m">Pearl</title> 1093-96). But in the sixteenth century, night itself could focus religious piety and aesthetic delight. In Venice, the poetical scene which artists called <q direct="y">un notte</q> provided regular income for a new breed of moonlight specialists. To the north, El Greco's <title level="m">Christ on the Mount of Olives</title> caught a thrilling, gloomy piety, of just the sort inspired in Sidney's <title level="m">Arcadia</title> by Philoclea's moonlit grove, that <q direct="y">might breede a fearful kind of devotion to look upon it.</q>
						</p>
						<p n="31">For a radical example of the new pictorial night-piece, its chiaroscuro virtuosity propelling sacred moments from dawn back into the darkness, one may contrast versions of <title level="m">The Agony in the Garden</title>. Mantegna's version presents a daylit, morning scene, and Bellini's too is clearly lighted, its spiritual suggestion located in the distant white brilliance of Jerusalem at dawn. But some sixty years later, in 1510, the Netherlandish painter Gossaert floods Gethsemane with sacramental moonlight, from a subtly and radiantly naturalistic sky. For another instance of the baptism of night, its conversion from terror to the softer ways of Christianity, one can contrast the fourteenth-century nocturne of Simone Martini, depicting <title level="m">Guidoriccio da Fogliano</title>, with the uses of night of Titian and Tintoretto. The former shows the <emph rend="italics">condottierre</emph> crossing on horseback a deserted, barren, nightbound landscape, featuring two towns captured by him for Siena and the tents of his encamped army. One town is shown as circled by a dreadful palisade of javelins, and the bare lunar terrain appears to represent the fearful might, the martial <emph rend="italics">terribilit&agrave;</emph>, of the warlord of Siena. Stars are omitted, but horse and rider in their proud trappings are harsh with light. One might compare this psychology of night, as fit setting for the irresistible conqueror, with Tamburlaine, switching his colours to black at the third stage of his sieges. By contrast is Titian's early sixteenth-century St. Jerome, the old saint rapt in the light of a moon rising directly behind a tree, that touches the woodland scene with a silvery-green and <q direct="y">endows the canvas with an ineffable sense of the fantastic.</q> The conception is evidently in the classical tradition of the visionary night. Bernardo Tasso, commenting on the painting soon after its completion, wrote <q direct="y">Never . . . did heaven see a more tranquil and serene night; beneath its wing silence bore sweet sleep to the animals, and the shadowed horrors, fearing the light of the beautiful night, stayed concealed within the savage grottoes, and did not wander forth, but only the pilgrim summer breezes played about the slopes and shores.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn32">[32]</ref>
							</q>
						</p>
						<p n="32">In seventeenth-century England, it is hard to know what night paintings were like, though they were certainly popular. In a table compiled from auction catalogues in the Restoration, almost one in ten was listed as a moonlight piece<q direct="y"> or a </q>night piece.<q direct="y"> H.V.S. Ogden, the foremost authority on English landscape paintings of the period, suggests that they probably resembled those of Aert van der Neer (1603-73) who was famed as the Dutch moonlight specialist, and whose work displayed lunar light on calm river scenes, and variously lit sky and cloud. Two nocturnes that we do know of in the seventeenth-century collections, copies of pictures by Rubens and Elsheimer, are likewise images of serenity and repose, with soft lighting over open countryside, and devoid of human figures. Davenant's instructions for the designs of <title level="m">Luminalia</title>, the Stuart masque of 1638, specify an open landscape with a calme River, that tooke the shadowes of the Trees by the light of the moon.</q> Inigo Jones directly imitated Elsheimer's <title level="m">Flight into Egypt</title> for <title level="m">Luminalia</title>'s scenery, in the full moon standing over a woodland lake.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn33">[33]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="33">This ready symbol shone not only from painting to painting, but from poem to poem: in <title level="m">The Shepherd's Calendar</title>, <title level="m">A Midsummer Night's Dream</title> and <title level="m">The Winter's Tale</title>, for example, Phoebe beholds <q direct="y">Her silver visage in the wat'ry glass.</q> There was good reason for this. Description of night scenery had developed with difficulty in literature, just as it had in art. Landscape painters had been handicapped by the lack of guidance here from their usual and deeply normative sources: there existed no inventory of nocturnal features in classical painting theory (in Vitruvius and Pliny), and there was but slight precedent in Calendar traditions. (The deficiency may actually have helped prompt the innovation: Renaissance pioneers in the rebirth of pictorial space may have revelled in the opportunity here to outgo the ancients in the <emph rend="italics">dimostratione</emph> of a further encapsulation of natural reality upon canvas). For poets, literary traditions had proven equally unhelpful. In the conventional nightfall close to the Virgilian eclogue, <emph rend="italics">chronographia</emph> made only terse allusions to lengthening shadows and the evening star; the Aeneid references to moonlight seem to have been ignored by medieval writers. Even the troubadours, in their lyric verse of sleepless yearning and illicit nocturnal <emph rend="italics">amour</emph>, do not present the night-time beyond an occasional one word reference to the nightingale. Moonlight does not enter the verse of the troubadours and trouveres, and I find only a single, cryptic reference to the existence of stars in Goldin's five hundred page anthology. Late medieval and early Renaissance evocations of night were generally mythological rather than descriptive, making reference to black wings, sable mantles, or more majestically in Marlowe, to a rising head: <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>The air with sparks of living fire was spangled, </l>
									<l>And Night, deep-drenched in misty Acheron, </l>
									<l>Heaved up her head, and half the world upon </l>
									<l>Breathed darkness forth.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn34">[34]</ref>
									</l>
								</lg>
							</q>
						</p>
						<p n="34">For descriptions of night landscape to emerge in English literature, they had to demystify the centuries-old tradition by which exaltations of the night (including the seminal Genesis 1.16-18) had always flattered her through a paradoxical stress on her brightness. <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Now the Ocean Tytan quencht his flame, </l>
									<l>And summoned Cynthya to set up her light, </l>
									<l>The heavens with their glorious starry frame,</l>
									<l>Preparde to crowne the sable-vayled night.</l>
								</lg>
							</q>
						</p>
						<p n="35">Regular identifications of Queen Elizabeth with Cynthia of course intensified this approach: <q direct="y">Thou that mak'st a day of night, / Goddess excellently bright</q> warbled Jonson. Yet in the late sixteenth and earlier seventeenth centuries, night was complimented on all those swaying shadows previously indispensable to felons, murderers and suicides. <q direct="y">Sweet umbrage</q> sighs John Norris of night's <q direct="y">dark Caves.</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn35">[35]</ref> After a millennium and a half, there are now indications that below the inevitable moon and stars exists, not damp vacancy and owls, but a fascinating <emph rend="italics">landscape</emph>. This provision of landscape evocation in positive nocturnal writing is of considerable novelty. It is this topographic restitution that defines, I feel, the transforming transition from conventional <emph rend="italics">impresa</emph> to promenade, from recited catalogue of nightingale, stars and moon, to <q direct="y">pictorial</q> provision of spatial relations. It is precisely in the seventeenth century that, according to the OED, the word <q direct="y">stroll</q> is first recorded, to mean an indirected, recreative walk. </p>
						<p n="36">
							<title level="m">Il Penseroso</title> proceeds from <q direct="y">glimmering bowrs and glades,</q> through woodland, to the <q direct="y">accustomed oak.</q> above which Cynthia checks her dragon yoke. <q direct="y">And missing thee, I walk unseen / On the dry smooth-shaven green.</q> The Thoughtful Man has to raise his head to notice the moon overhead, <q direct="y">Oft, as if her head she bowed / Stooping through a fleecy cloud,</q> as he continues engrossed onward through the lower world:<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Oft on a plot of rising ground </l>
									<l>I hear the far-off curfew sound </l>
									<l>Over some wide-watered shore </l>
									<l>Swinging slow with sullen roar. (65-66, 71-72, 73-76)</l>
								</lg>
							</q>The eye travels downward, among satisfactions that are sublunar. Lorenzo's romantic eye is scenic: <q direct="y">How sweet the moonlight <emph rend="italics">sleeps upon this bank!</emph>
							</q>
							<q direct="y">The moon shines bright. In such a night as this, / When <emph rend="italics">the sweet wind did gently kiss the trees</emph>, / <emph rend="italics">And they did make no noise</emph> . . .</q> [italics mine]. The period abounds in evidence of a new and empiric descriptive particularity. If Fulke Greville can only remark, traditionally, how <q direct="y">In Night . . . colours all to blacke are cast, / Distinction lost,</q> Spenser notes that <q direct="y">starry light / . . . sparckling on the starry waves, does seem more bright.</q> If Habington, affirming in an ancient tradition that the stars' eternalism confutes mortal pride in brief achievement, invokes them only derivatively as <q direct="y">rich . . . jewels hung, that night / Doth like an Aethiop bride appeare</q> (apparently with Romeo in mind), Cotton, in a splendid burst of demystification, will accurately debunk the entire tradition:<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>No Ray of Light the Heart to cheer, </l>
									<l>But little twinkling Stars appear; </l>
									<l>Which like faint dying embers ly, </l>
									<l>Fit nor to work, nor travel by. </l>
								</lg>
								<l/>
								<lg>
									<l>Perhaps to him they Torches are, </l>
									<l>Who guides Night's sovreign's drowsy Car, </l>
									<l>And him they may befriend so near, </l>
									<l>But us they neither light, nor cheer.</l>
								</lg>
							</q>William Browne expands magnificently, with the help of a hint from Ovid, the old topic of night's desertedness and silence:<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>All the upper world lay in a trance. </l>
									<l>Only the curled streams soft chidings kept; </l>
									<l>Dry summer's dust, in fearful whisp'rings stirr'd,</l>
									<l>As loath to waken any singing bird.</l>
								</lg>
							</q>This new detailed materiality in portrayal of the night is to be borrowed by the Countess of Winchelsea for her <emph rend="italics">chronographia</emph> in the <q direct="y">Nocturnal Reverie,</q> and by Keats, in <q direct="y">Hyperion.</q>
						</p>
						<p n="37">The rapture in stellar brightness, in <q direct="y">spangled starlight sheen</q> extends and develops through the seventeenth century. Vaughan and Herbert observe their light with Galilean closeness. Vaughan addresses his star: <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>What ever 'tis, whose beauty here below</l>
									<l>Attracts thee thus and makes thee stream and flow,</l>
									<l>And wind and curl, and wink and smile,</l>
									<l>Shifting thy gate and guile . . . </l>
								</lg>
							</q>Elsewhere he records starlit dusk over a nocturne painted across the ceiling of a tavern: <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l> . . . that blue space below</l>
									<l>Is fired with many stars; mark how they break</l>
									<l>In silent glances o'er the hills, and speak</l>
									<l>The evening to the plains; where shot from far,</l>
									<l>They meet in dumb salutes, as one great star. </l>
								</lg>
							</q>The feeling is particularly strong in Vaughan's verse, which finds <q direct="y">the dark was gay, / And gilt with stars, more trim than day,</q> and perhaps reflects his Hermeticist assurance of constant commerce between skies and earth, of earth's inseparable involvement in the physical circuit of spiritual energy through the universe. But the recovery of the sublunar zone at night extends, as we have seen, to much in contemporary poetry. This new nocturnal <q direct="y">bridall of the earth and sky,</q> this supplementation of the vertical imagination by a horizontal one, had been expressed in an early state of ambivalence in <title level="m">The Merchant of Venice</title>. There in a single passage glows the sense of heaven's rays on earth -- <q direct="y">How sweet the moonlight sleeps upon this bank</q> -- together with the sterner medieval stratification, the subordination of our little world: <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>There's not the smallest globe which thou beholdest</l>
									<l>But in his motion like an angel sings,</l>
									<l>Still quiring to the young-ey'd cherubims;</l>
									<l>Such harmony is in immortal souls,</l>
									<l>But whilst this muddy vesture of decay</l>
									<l>Doth grossly close it in, we cannot hear it. </l>
								</lg>
							</q>The focus here is precisely midway between, on the one hand, the vertical aspiration, the old ascetic flight from black earth to the transcendent brightness of the immutable spheres, and on the other, the eighteenth-century and Romantic verse, (influenced by <title level="m">Il Penseroso</title>), with their <q direct="y">terrestrialised</q> starscapes, where the night-sky figures as backdrop to country walks and meditations. The dual focus of this transitional phase is the poignant framework of Vaughan's earthbound twilight:<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>They are all gone into the world of light! </l>
									<l>And I alone sit longing here; </l>
									<l>Their very memory is clear and bright, </l>
									<l>And my sad thoughts doth clear. </l>
									<l>It glows and glitters in my cloudy breast </l>
									<l>Like stars upon some gloomy grove, </l>
									<l>Or those faint beams in which this hill is dressed </l>
									<l>After the sun's remove.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn37">[37]</ref>
									</l>
								</lg>
							</q>
						</p>
						<p n="38">The new delight in chiaroscuro landscape had perhaps sensitised Milton to a nicety of discrimination between nocturnal dimness and nocturnal shadow: the brothers in <title level="m">Comus</title> complain of <q direct="y">double night of darkness, and of shades.</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn38">[38]</ref> Indeed only dunderheads failed to appreciate the inimitable quality of filmy moonlight, and paid out unguardedly the old-style compliments. Here lay the special hilarity of Starveling stumping onstage as Moonshine; and from this derived the impetus behind<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Sweet moon, I thank thee for thy sunny beams; </l>
									<l>I thank thee, Moon, for shining now so bright; </l>
									<l>For by thy gracious, golden, glittering beams,</l>
									<l>I trust to take of truest Thisbe sight. </l>
								</lg>
							</q>
						</p>
						<p n="39">The Elizabethan eye, however, demands a new term: and from Shakespeare onwards we read of the moon's <q direct="y">sheen,</q> a new Elizabethan word, emerging to denote the lustre of a body reflecting light. The seventeenth century imports from the Dutch the compound <q direct="y">night-light</q> to denote the faint light perceptible during the hours of darkness: furnishing thereby an English term for an imported cultural perception.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn39">[39]</ref>
						</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>Mysticism and Melancholy</head>
						<p n="40">Complementary to the novel pleasure in the distinctive visual conditions of the small hours was the mystical revaluation of night's significance. Night had long been <q direct="y">the mother of counsels.</q> Following the biblical and classical traditions we examined of <q direct="y">inspired night,</q> Erasmus' <title level="m">Adagia</title> records <q direct="y">In nocte consilium,</q> Jonson's <title level="m">Timber</title> echoes <q direct="y">Dat nox consilium,</q> and Habington pens an apostrophe to night entitled <q direct="y">Nox nocti indicat scientiam.</q> Chapman's <title level="m">Shadow of the Night</title>, Milton's <title level="m">Il Penseroso</title>, and Vaughan's <title level="a">The Night</title> go further, and revitalise the traditional Christian paradoxes of Dionysus the Areopagite: the <q direct="y">tenebre in bono</q> reflections. Physical darkness opens the intellectual eyes. <q direct="y">There is in God (some say),</q> writes Vaughan <q direct="y">A deep but dazzling darkness</q>: a conceit strikingly close to Milton's line on the Godhead: <q direct="y">Dark with excessive bright thy skirts appear.</q>
						</p>
						<p n="41">Equally important is the new mystical melancholy. Without the Neoplatonic revival of the Saturnian genius, who derives contemplative inspiration from the twilight of groves and nocturnal seclusion, we would not, suggests Lawrence Babb, have had <title level="m">Il Penseroso</title>. And this character's medical humour, <q direct="y">his atrabilious</q> genius, was itself, of course, a conception born with the Renaissance. The Saturnian vogue helped legitimate the sweeter, introspective seventeenth-century melancholy, <q direct="y">a certain tender and pensive sadness</q> as Leishman calls it, which pervades Fletcher's song from <title level="m">The Nice Valour</title>, early in the century:<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Ther's nought in this Life sweet, </l>
									<l>If man were wise to see't, </l>
									<l>But onely Melancholy, </l>
									<l>O sweetest Melancholy. </l>
									<l>Fountaine heads, and pathlesse Groves, </l>
									<l>Places which pale passion loves: </l>
									<l>Moon-light walkes, when all the fowles </l>
									<l>Are warmly hous's, save Bats and Owles.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn40">[40]</ref>
									</l>
								</lg>
							</q>Likewise Margaret Cavendish, who in 1656 declares she is <q direct="y">more inclining to be melancholy than merry, but not crabbed or peevishly melancholy, but soft melting solitary, and contemplating melancholy,</q> enjoys a <q direct="y">sad, and solemne verse . . . As Pensil'd Pictures drawne present the Night, / Whose Darker Shadowes give the Eye delight.</q>
						</p>
						<p n="42">These factors, then -- the evocation of nocturnal earthly scenery, and the new dulcified and mystical melancholy -- clearly mark off the later sixteenth- and seventeenth-century apprehension of night from that of the <title level="m">Pearl</title>-poet, of Chaucer, and of the medieval serenade. And the cardinal point is to be found in Milton's first <title level="m">Prolusion</title>, on whether day or night is better. Orating against the primacy of night (perhaps in satiric revolt against the prevailing vogue), he affirms: <q direct="y">Night is but the passing and the death of Day.</q> Night lacks self-identity: moonlight and starlight are borrowed, he says, from the sun; and sleep is but <q direct="y">the image and semblance of death . . . sleep is not a thing so precious that Night deserves honour for the bestowal of it.</q> Night is merely a void, a privation of the real world of action. Such had been exactly the medieval attitude: hence the traditional theme of <q direct="y">theft-guilty night,</q> which steals hours from the short span of mortals, a theme which still recurs in Browne and Davenant. And hence the botched conceits of <title level="m">A Midsummer Night's Dream</title>'s artisans, once again a reverse index to the new sensibility:<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>O grim-look't night! O night with hue so black! </l>
									<l>O night, which ever art when day is not, </l>
									<l>O night, O night, alack, alack, alack!<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn41">[41]</ref>
									</l>
								</lg>
							</q>The nocturnal revolution lies precisely in the fact that night now does have her own distinctive psyche. The luxuriation in half-light, the nocturnal stroll, and the contemplative melancholy, have objectified night as <emph rend="italics">otium</emph>, beyond the hiatus of sleep. Indeed night now exists practically as a respectable <emph rend="italics">negotium</emph>, with her religious observations and devotions, in sharp contrast to the medieval noctivagants, who were never more than criminals, guilty lovers, or poor travellers led astray (such as we still meet in <title level="m">Comus</title> and Marvell's <q direct="y">Mower to the Glowworms</q>). No longer the conjuror simply of sleep and planets, she offers to the Stuart citizen almost a social programme. </p>
						<p n="43">Night is promoted, in fact, to a fertile condition of ambiguity. <q direct="y">I muse, which shows more love, / The day or night,</q> wonders Herbert's <q direct="y">Even-Song.</q> With the new interpretative elasticity of the Renaissance, nocturnes may ornament a wealth of inspirations -- beauty, purity, peace, secrecy, malice, guilt, frenzy, rapture -- and her poets requisition all ambiguities. Sidney plays off optics against convention to fine ironic effect in sonnet 31, diagnosing in the chaste moon the tell-tale signs of a frustrated lover; only to reintroduce her in a later sonnet (97) as the laughing rallier of the love-sick. <title level="m">A Midsummer Night's Dream</title> similarly exploits the divided influences of Luna for both chastity and fertility (as befits a nuptial drama). </p>
						<p n="44">Night's occult associations may be newly holy, along mystic and cabalist lines, or damned as ever, in witches, ghosts and demons. There are sinister shadows<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn42">[42]</ref> to counterpose the glimmering exquisites in the fairyland of Puck and Titania; and melancholias abound to suit every temperament, ascetic or romantic, prophetic or malcontent. Shakespeare conjures both the criminal and the amorous motifs with equal power: <q direct="y">How silver-sweet sound lovers' tongues by night,</q> thinks Romeo, <q direct="y">Like softest music to attending ears</q> (2.2.15-65); and Lady Macbeth's invocation <q direct="y">Come, thick night, / And pall thee in the dunnest smoke of hell / That my keen knife see not the wound it makes</q> (1.5.50-52) is polarised by Juliet's tender invocation of <q direct="y">love-performing night</q>:<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>
										<q direct="y">Come, civil night,</q>
									</l>
									<l>Thou sober-suited matron, all in black</l>
									<l>And learn me how to lose a winning match </l>
								</lg>
								<l>. . . </l>
								<lg>
									<l>Come, gentle night, come loving, black-browed night,</l>
									<l>Give me my Romeo; and when I shall die</l>
									<l>Take him and cut him out in little stars,</l>
									<l>And he will make the face of heaven so fine</l>
									<l>That all the world will be in love with night,</l>
									<l>And pay no worship to the garish sun. (3.2.5, 10-12, 20-25).</l>
								</lg>
							</q>
						</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>Genre and Politics</head>
						<p n="45">It was within this pluralism of portraitures that night became politicised. Two lines of nocturne developed, I think, one tending to mystical focus, another to fairyland and the amorous; one dominant among cavalier writers, and the other having Puritan affinities. It may even be that the fairy topos popularised by Shakespeare in the <title level="m">Dream</title>, and the melancholic one distinguished by Milton, were not choices in ornament but political shibboleths. </p>
						<p n="46">In the England of Elizabeth, a group of noblemen scientists centred around Raleigh were pursuing <q direct="y">the deepe search of knowledge</q> among the language of the mysteries, when the rising tide of feeling against them prompted Chapman's extraordinary <title level="m">Shadow of the Night</title>. The poem displays <q direct="y">to purest eyes / With ease, the bowells of these misteries.</q> The night was, as we have seen, the time of Orphic and Hermetic holiness, for from <q direct="y">divine darkness</q> had sprung the light of creation, and in divine darkness lay the almighty unmanifested God, inaccessible to mortal apprehension, definable only through negatives. The old day / night antithesis as integrity against covertness is reversed by Chapman into one of triviality against profundity: <q direct="y">Day of deepe students, most contentfull night . . . / Mens' faces glitter, and their hearts are black, / But thou . . . /Art black in face, and glitter'st in thy heart.</q> But this mystical topos of noetic night contained multiplying political ramifications. In Frances Yates' opinion, Chapman's poem itself had been written in response to the mounting reaction against occult researches -- hence the defensive preface against <q direct="y">the viperous head of benumming ignorance</q> and <q direct="y">killing censures</q> -- the reaction represented in England by Marlowe's <title level="m">Faustus</title>. It may be that in Jacobean and Caroline England the <q direct="y">inspired night</q> theme was forced to go underground: Yates, in <title level="m">The Occult Philosophy in the Age of Elizabeth</title> argues that James I classed Agrippa with devils and evil conjurors, disapproved of Dee, and probably saw Inspired Melancholy as damnable.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn43">[43]</ref> Medically, moreover, Saturnians (according to Overbury) were malcontents. Political radicals, too, moved in the current of Hermeticism, Familists and Behmenists especially. The rescidivist Everard translated Hermes. And in the Jacobean climate astrology was <emph rend="italics">ipso facto</emph> suspect. The statutes of the new Savilian Chair in Astronomy at Oxford, endowed in 1619, had explicitly forbidden study of astrology; and the Laudian Code of 1636 ensured the continuance of the medieval pattern of studies at Oxford.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn44">[44]</ref> From 1612, with the death of Prince Henry, the occult was without support at court. Casaubon's critique of the Hermetica as a fake was dedicated in its English translation to James, in 1614.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn45">[45]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="47">In light of all this, one may, I think, perceive in night verse a pattern of polarity, between <q direct="y">high</q> and <q direct="y">low</q> nocturnes. In contrast to the Sacred Night with its web of impolitic connotations, Cavalier poets trivialised it. They invoked the fairy-topos and night revels, or they hymned the jewelled landscapes of day. <title level="m">Luminalia</title>, for instance (written in 1638 to celebrate the confirmation of royal absolutism in the ship-Money case) seems almost an exultant retort to the fervid nonsense of Chapman and his cabalist underworld. It overrules any religious or inspirational properties to night, which signifies only sleep:<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>The studious that consume their brains and sight </l>
									<l>In search where doubtful knowledge lies </l>
									<l>Grow weary of their fruitless use of light, </l>
									<l>And with my shades do ease their eyes. (83-86)</l>
								</lg>
							</q>(Contrast Chapman's <q direct="y">Day of deepe students</q> in the <q direct="y">deepe search of knowledge.</q>) Defending herself against <q direct="y">the old mistaking sages</q> (92) who loathed her, Night in <title level="m">Luminalia</title> argues rather the importance of sleep as essential to success: merchant and mariner, student and statesman, all need sleep to <q direct="y">profit</q> by their <q direct="y">toils</q> (79-98). And here the regal masque furthers its polemical politicisation of night. Sleep-bearing night had been articulated from at least the 1590s in loosely oppositional, egalitarian terms as an anti-courtly motif: <q direct="y">O Night</q> runs Sylvester's translation of Du Bartas, <q direct="y">thou pullest the proud Mask away / . . . No difference night makes between the Peasant and the Prince, / . . . For night's black Mantle covers all alike.</q> Exposing the common humanity of all classes, night, writes Du Bartas, bestows luxurious repose on criminal and bargeman, mower and smith just as on kings. More so indeed, echoed some writers, for the peasant with his quiet conscience <q direct="y">all night / Sleep in Elysium</q>: <q direct="y">Sweet rest enrings / The tired body of the swarty clown</q> and not <q direct="y">the beds of kings.</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn46">[46]</ref>
							<title level="m">Luminalia</title>'s figures retort to Night however that rest is inappropriate at the court, whose people <q direct="y">know their own estate,</q> and are <q direct="y">free from sufferings and decay</q> to dedicate themselves <q direct="y">to raise new joys and keep the old alive</q> (138, 125, 129). In this court <q direct="y">all to triumphs are addressed</q>; their dignity lies, haughtily, in that they both <q direct="y">know</q> and <q direct="y">deserve felicity</q> (120, 141). To demotic Night, bearer of mundane rest, <title level="m">Luminalia</title> thus counterposes courtly celebration of exclusive status: her denizens transcend the rhythms of quotidian labour, freed to revel all night through. <q direct="y">What is the use of silence here? / Thou sees'st, great empress, every eye / Doth watch for measures</q> (130-33) gloat the privileged, poised for night dancing. <title level="m">Comus</title> (122-24, 128) similarly asks <q direct="y">What has night to do with sleep? / Night hath better sweets to prove. / Venus now wakes, and wakens Love / . . . Hail, goddess of nocturnal sport</q>: an invitation pointedly rebuffed by the puritan poet's mystically contemplative Lady. London gallants regularly celebrated their wealth in nocturnal carousal (<q direct="y">Let's laugh now, and the pressed grape drink / Till the drowsy Day-star wink</q> runs Vaughan's apprentice Anacreontic), and indeed nocturnes were sometimes painted across the ceilings of taverns.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn47">[47]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="48">
							<title level="m">Luminalia</title>'s darkness, like Oberon and the earlier <title level="m">Masque of Blackness</title>, luxuriously spills forth <q direct="y">fantastic creatures of the night.</q> Ben Jonson's verse likewise draws on fairyland, for a delicate literary disquiet.<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>The fairy beam upon you, </l>
									<l>The stars to glisten on you: </l>
									<l>A moon of light, </l>
									<l>In the noon of night, </l>
									<l>Till the fire-drake hath o'ergone you.</l>
								</lg>
							</q>Herrick expands this in his <q direct="y">Night-piece,</q> where he awaits love-making with his mistress:<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Her Eyes the Glow-worme lend thee, </l>
									<l>The Shooting Starres attend thee; </l>
									<l>And the Elves also, </l>
									<l>Whose little eyes glow, </l>
									<l>Like the sparks of fire, befriend thee.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn48">[48]</ref>
									</l>
								</lg>
							</q>The contrast with the Puritan George Wither's night, <q direct="y">friend</q> to <q direct="y">Meditation . . . and seriou'st Muses</q> is suggestively sharp. Such nocturnalism is at one level elegantly secular: the mythology of midnight may no longer unseat the urbane scalp. But there may be more here than primitive reflexes transvalued into romancey cultivation. Fairy-nocturne, I think, exerts a discreet polemical allegiance to Royalist values, like the panegyrics of country life alongside which it flows so smoothly.<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>I sing of May-poles, Hock-carts, Wassails, Wakes, </l>
									<l>Of Bridegrooms, Brides, and of their Bridall-cakes. </l>
									<l>I write of Youth, of Love, and have Accesse </l>
									<l>By these, to sing of cleanly-Wantonness . . . </l>
									<l>
										<emph rend="italics">I write of Groves, of Twilights, and I sing</emph>
									</l>
									<l>
										<emph rend="italics">The court of Mab, and of the Fairie-King</emph>.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn49">[49]</ref> [italics mine]</l>
								</lg>
							</q>Protestantism taught that both ghosts and faeries were Catholic fictions deployed to defraud; and such conviction, suggests Keith Thomas, was in the sixteenth century <q direct="y">a shibboleth which distinguished Protestant from Catholic almost as effectively as belief in the Mass or Papal Supremacy.</q> At the same time, fairies were no longer conceived as malevolent but were coming to be seen as benign in character: to the point, amazingly, where tricksters in London were actually able (rather as in Jonson's <title level="m">Alchemist</title>) to cozen money from victims under pretence of investing it with caring faeries. (Faeries, I'd suggest, were perhaps here inheriting the protective <q direct="y">Mariological</q> reflexes of the Middle Ages.) As faeries became for the majority however more a matter of mythology than living beliefs, Shakespeare's <title level="m">Dream</title> introduced into literature one strand of folklore, the tiny, flower-loving and benevolent version with which we are today familiar, and was imitated here by Herrick and Drayton. Given these demystifying developments, Shakespeare's aestheticised fairylore, I would argue, came to function at the increasingly Anglo-Catholic courts of James and Charles as a kind of discourse of nostalgia, political and religious. Fairylore carried clear affinities with an older, more secret, magical and ritualistic world of the past, when supernatural beliefs helped sustain what was at court a keenly regretted conservative society: one so different from the aggressive rationalism of the Reformation with its abolition of Purgatory and scoffing at ghosts, its puritan campaigning against traditional rural sports and its bourgeois dismissal from the traditional calendar of <q direct="y">lucky</q> and <q direct="y">evil</q> days. Fairy religion, writes Herrick, is <q direct="y">part pagan, part papistical</q>; and he fantasises a <q direct="y">Faery Temple</q> replete with <q direct="y">masse-priests,</q>
							<q direct="y">copes</q> and <q direct="y">cloyster-monks.</q> As a kind of <q direct="y">natural</q> arcana, the fairy kingdom and its nocturnal rites shared much with the tonality of a court that grounded its prerogatives in a mystic ideology of sustaining supernatural relations. The tonality seems to overlap with that of court masque, a <q direct="y">theatre of mysteries</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn50">[50]</ref> dealing in wonder and magic; and the intense aestheticism has perhaps affinities with the Laudian <q direct="y">beauty of holiness.</q> Cavalier fairy-nocturne, then, at a level of levity and creative display, offered the reassurance of an enchanted conservatism, Catholic in dignity and wrought with courtly preciosity. It nurtured a longing, among both urban sophisticates and courtly poets, for emotional and religious roots in danger of being lost. </p>
						<p n="49">Like masque, its delights dovetailed into an amorous theme; and Night's erotic associations need little gloss. Darkness has long summoned the post-coital smirk. <q direct="y">The glade nyght ys worth an hevy morowe</q> cried Chaucer. His Wife of Bath had counted it comically naive when her husband accepted that her frequent <q direct="y">walkynge out by nyghte</q> was not for adulterous rendezvous; and the first recorded use of the coinage <q direct="y">noctivagant</q> -- going by night -- expresses a splendidly Puritanical ornithology: <q direct="y">The lustful sparrows, noctivagant adulterers, sit chirping about our houses.</q>
							<q direct="y">Dark night is Cupid's day</q> was an Elizabethan proverb, dated by Tilley to 1595. <q direct="y">Tis a fit night to run away with another man's wife,</q> remarks a character in Fletcher. <q direct="y">Ha,</q> cries Falstaff, <q direct="y">twas a merry night. And is Jane Nightwork still alive?</q> By the 1630s, Cavalier amorous nocturne was so firmly established as both courtly occupation and poetic vogue that the prince of gallants, Sir John Suckling, could mock it from deep within the convention. In his play <title level="m">Aglaura</title>, featuring nocturnal scenes of illicit love, dread deeds and miraculous reversal, and probably borrowing <title level="m">Luminalia</title>'s scenery, a courtier asked for a song cries out: <q direct="y">A vengeance take this love . . . I have got such a cold with rising and walking in my shirt a nights, that a Bittorne whooping in a reed is better musike.</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn51">[51]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="50">Other Jacobean and Caroline night treatments disclose only the orthodox horrors (as in Webster's dramas), or the orthodox awe in the wonder of the constellations (as in Herbert's <q direct="y">Star</q>). The exception, of course, was <title level="m">Il Penseroso</title>: written by Milton as an Hermeticist, and in the very period when his disaffection with Anglicanism grew to the point of definite refusal to <q direct="y">subscribe slave</q> as a minister. Is it then perhaps less than fanciful to see in <title level="m">Comus</title>' attacks on the nocturnal amorousness of literary supernaturals, a poetic reproach of the Cavalier genre of <q direct="y">low</q> nocturnes? </p>
						<p n="51">With the advent of the Commonwealth, its flood of ideas and relaxation of censorship, <q direct="y">Inspired Night</q> became permissible once again. Vaughan's <q direct="y">Night</q> was penned in this period. The sense of night's sanctity during these years is of course also accentuated by the suppression of the Anglican service (giving rise, at the least, to the stanza in Vaughan's <q direct="y">Night</q>), and by the violence of day, which resuscitates the Elizabethan mystic antithesis between mis-spent day and the profound sanctuary of night:<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Dear night! this world's defeat; </l>
									<l>The stop to busy fools; care's check and curb; </l>
									<l>The day of Spirits; my soul's calm retreat </l>
									<l>Which none disturb!<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn52">[52]</ref>
									</l>
								</lg>
							</q>
						</p>
						<p n="52">And with the Restoration, John Norris recapitulates in his <q direct="y">Hymn to Darkness</q> all the major Neoplatonic tributes to night first sung in English by Chapman a full century before: the dazzling darkness paradox; inspirational melancholy; religious awe and fear; darkness as the original <q direct="y">universal wombe</q>; and night as spiritual refuge from the evils of day.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>Milton</head>
						<p n="53">Milton's poetic relations with the varied currents of this new sensibility are characteristic: whilst gathering its full range into his innovative genius, and decisively expanding the form, his aesthetic enthusiasm is from the outset commanded by high political and moral discrimination. </p>
						<p n="54">Night's negative associations teem unbanished: <title level="m">Comus</title>, its protagonists strayed in a midnight rife with occult vitalities, thrills to a five-line catalogue of <q direct="y">evil things that walk by night,</q>
							<q direct="y">blue-meagre hag</q> and <q direct="y">stubborn unlaid ghost,</q> goblins and swart fairy (432-37). In <title level="m">Paradise Lost</title> Satan, gliding in night vapour, is frequently associated with night and three times with midnight: <q direct="y">By night he fled, and at midnight returned.</q> Book five echoes the old Latin Breviary, wherein returning light dispels the evil gathered under fall of dark.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn53">[53]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="55">Yet the aesthetic enthusiasm for night is a conquering enchantment, much as the Lady's pure lyric out-raptures <title level="m">Comus</title>' primitive bawdy. Milton pens one of the earliest colourific sunsets in the language, whose array of clouds <q direct="y">reflected purple and gold</q> (4.596) accords with Edward Norgate's advice to painters in <title level="m">Miniatura</title> (second edition 1649) that <q direct="y">reddish and purple clouds</q> help render sunset.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn54">[54]</ref>Night skies dazzle the Miltonic imagination repeatedly, whether as the light of constellations, that blazing highway to God's house, <q direct="y">whose dust is gold / And pavement stars,</q> wherein the Milky Way <q direct="y">as a circling zone thou seest / Powdered with stars</q>; or as the transfiguring flood of moonlight spilled upon black:<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>there does a sable cloud </l>
									<l>Turn forth her silver lining on the night, </l>
									<l>And casts a gleam over this tufted grove . . . </l>
									<l>Unmuffle ye faint stars, and thou fair moon </l>
									<l>That wont'st to love the traveller's benison </l>
									<l>Stoop thy pale visage through an amber cloud </l>
									<l>And disinherit Chaos, that reigns here </l>
									<l>In double night of darkness and of shades.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn55">[55]</ref>
									</l>
								</lg>
							</q>
							<q direct="y">Swift as the sparkle of a glancing star</q> shoots the masque's Attendant Spirit (80); and Eve, overheard by Satan, lists <q direct="y">walk by moon / Or glittering starlight</q> among the sweetnesses of life in Eden (4.655-56). From Shakespeare he pirates the neologism <q direct="y">sheen,</q> so that his Cupid, starlike, while Adonis slumbers, sits <q direct="y">far above in spangled sheen.</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn56">[56]</ref>
							<title level="m">Il Penseroso</title>, of course, establishes a holy noctivagant aesthetic at the heart of its poetic ideal: elaborating the walk by moon and nightingale into strolling through shadowy oak woods, and pacing quiet ground above a wide tidal shore, before entering the tower to <q direct="y">outwatch the Bear.</q> The <q direct="y">black air,</q> gloom and damps of night, Milton specifies, were absent from Eden, existing today as an unnatural postlapsarian distortion (10.846-50). Adam and Eve pause before bed to <q direct="y">adore</q> the night sky, responding without fear and with peaceful wonder to <q direct="y">This glorious sight</q> (4.721, 657). Eve's <q direct="y">grateful evening mild</q> (647), echoing the ancient motif of bodily respite, deepens this scene's creation of a vespertinal luxury and ease. </p>
						<p n="56">Just as <title level="m">Il Penseroso</title>'s nightingale <q direct="y">shuns the noise of folly</q> to sing her <q direct="y">even-song,</q>
							<q direct="y">most musical</q> (61-64), Milton almost programmatically <q direct="y">takes back the night</q> from profanity of revel for the deeper joy of a sacred harmonics. Night he associates with song: but with a richer melody than troubadour or Cavalier could muster.<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>How sweetly did they float upon the wings </l>
									<l>Of silence, through the empty-vaulted night </l>
									<l>At every fall smoothing the raven down </l>
									<l>Of darkness till it smiled . . . </l>
									<l>. . . Such a sacred, and home-felt delight, </l>
									<l>Such sober certainty of waking bliss </l>
									<l>I never heard till now. (248-51, 261-63)</l>
								</lg>
							</q>
						</p>
						<p n="57">If <title level="m">Comus</title> constitutes <q direct="y">a masque against masking,</q> as John Carey has shrewdly shown,<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn57">[57]</ref>its Lady repudiating masque-like revels along with the Comus who proffers and praises them (738-47), then likewise the Lady's indictment of <q direct="y">wanton dance</q> and <q direct="y">late wassailers</q> (175, 178), together with her counterposed sweeter song, <q direct="y">resounding grace to all heaven's harmonies</q> (242) comprise a reproach, I suggest, not simply to the aristocracy's night revels but to companion Cavalier <q direct="y">low nocturne.</q> For <title level="m">Paradise Lost</title> will reconstruct the same antithesis of courtly nocturne against a truer night music: fulfilment lies not <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>. . . in court amours, </l>
									<l>Mixed dance, or wanton mask, or midnight ball, </l>
									<l>Or serenade, which the starved lover sings </l>
									<l>To his proud fair, best quitted with disdain. </l>
									<l>These lulled by nightingales embracing slept . . . (767-71)</l>
								</lg>
							</q>That Satan sings a traditional Serenade to beckon Eve from Adam's side (at 5.38-43) is again reproach of a profane tradition of nightsong: to which the epic again counterposes a sacred song of night. For Adam reminds Eve how often they have heard <q direct="y">Celestial voices to the midnight air, / Sole, or responsive to each other's note / Singing their great Creator,</q> and remarks to Raphael on his delight when <q direct="y">Cherubic songs by night from neighbouring hills / Aerial music send</q> (4.680-88; 5.547-48). </p>
						<p n="58">It is, I conclude by suggesting, precisely the absence of such religious telos that Milton deplored and contested in the new nocturnal vogue. Night, for all its wheeling stellar grandeur, its ravishing silences and song, is for religious contemplation (as the epic's extended discussions on astronomy make pointed), or more usually, for sleep: as the interval in rhythms of righteous action. The essential contrast between Milton's description of night's onset (<q direct="y">Now came still evening on</q>) and Eve's to Adam (<q direct="y">Sweet the coming on / Of grateful evening mild</q>) in book four,<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn58">[58]</ref> lies in the latter's blankly pleasant landscape as against the Miltonic sense of resistless purposeful activism. Hesperus <q direct="y">rides,</q> leading a vanguard <q direct="y">starry host,</q> until the moon <q direct="y">Rising in clouded majesty, at length / Apparent Queen unveiled her peerless light, / And oe'r the dark her silver mantle threw.</q> The spectacle reminds Adam of the need for sleep that they may buckle to hard graft on the morrow; and the stars he exposits as edifying exemplars of an unflagging work-ethic. <q direct="y">Those have their course to finish, round the earth, / By morrow evening,</q> he enthuses, warming to his theme across twenty lines (4.661-80). It is accordingly the proffering of a contextless beauty, the displacement of active religious perception by an aesthetics of mere mood, that makes Satan's fashionable nocturne satanic. His first temptation to Eve is precisely to walk by night and enjoy its enchantments without contextualising gratitude and awe.<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Why sleep'st thou Eve? Now is the pleasant time, </l>
									<l>The cool, the silent, save where silence yields </l>
									<l>To the night-warbling bird, that now awake </l>
									<l>Tunes sweetest his love-laboured song; now reigns </l>
									<l>Full-orbed the moon, and with more pleasing light </l>
									<l>Shadowy sets off the face of things; in vain, </l>
									<l>If none regard. (5.38-43)</l>
								</lg>
							</q>
						</p>
						<p n="59">Landscape description in this period is in transition, from traditional paysage moralis&eacute; to pictorialism, and verse such as Saint-Amant's <title level="m">La Solitude</title>, for instance, anticipates Romantic <q direct="y">mood-music</q> in the age of the emblem book: a passive, sensuous, deliquescent perception of nature ousting the hieroglyphic imagination.<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn59">[59]</ref> It may be indeed that the evocative luxury of night, its stealing of firm daylight clarities in glimmering suggestion (one remembers Gossaert's dissolving of diurnal substance) explains much of the popularity of the seventeenth century moonlight walk. If Satan, as Howard Schultz<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn60">[60]</ref> has pointed out, is singing an immoral Cavalier serenade, flattering Eve blasphemously, and beckoning her with the conventional <emph rend="italics">venite</emph>, there may be, I suggest, a further possible dimension of the diabolic here, in that profane preference for concealing shades over the clear forms of God's creation. He urges Eve to a state in which natural phenomena dissolve the thoughtful mind, the grateful emblematic rationality, fill up the consciousness with sensuous luxury, and eclipse the Creator who lies beyond them. He tempts her, in Herbert's words, to <q direct="y">rest in Nature, not the God of Nature.</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn61">[61]</ref> Satan, then, is a Romantic, and would write poetry like Thomas Warton, of self-sufficient sensory glut. He offers an impious grandiloquence of the sense as against the truly devotional perception of earth whose hallmark is reason. </p>
						<p n="60">The preference of course, is typical of this <q direct="y">anti-teleological</q> Satan, who denies his creation by God and inhabits a universe he refuses to revere (5.856-66); yet it typifies, too, that merely possessive, competitive relation to beauty exercised by the Cavalier art connoisseur, who collects landscape and moonlight paintings only for ornament and wealth. Despising such values, Milton has only the <emph rend="italics">fallen</emph> Adam conceive Eve in the choice, aesthetic terms of the connoisseur (<q direct="y">I see thou art exact of taste / And elegant</q>), and notes that the Fiend, eyeing from the Tree of Life <q direct="y">Nature's whole wealth,</q> refused regenerative contemplation of the scene <q direct="y">but only used for prospect.</q>
							<ref target="emls3-2fittnoctn62">[62]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="61">In conclusion, we have seen that classical and medieval traditions predominantly identified night with the negative: metaphorically, with the generalities of evil, death and suffering, and concretely, with illicit sexuality, demonology and crime. In contrast, however, and in deep subordination, were the occasional positive motifs: the nocturnal peace of respite, and the visionary religious night whose silence and providential starscapes induce wonder, contemplation, even theophany. Renaissance England's fashionable new cult of the night developed by expanding the religious tradition along <q direct="y">inspired night</q> variations, and by revaluing the old themes of rogue love and baleful supernaturalism within a comfortably adjusted metropolitan topos of jubilant amorous revel and archaic fairy fancy. Disposed, too, toward novel descriptive empiricism, it sought articulation of a delicate nocturnal aesthetic, a <q direct="y">romancey</q> mood-music of deep glooms and mystical glitter. Milton, above all, is enamoured of a night that repudiates amour; and sings of its hours as those of a higher natural or sacred song, deriding the discords of cavalier nocturne. He urges perception of a sacramental starscape, a noetic night of wonder and beneficence, which shames as <q direct="y">satanic</q> a mere spectatorship of sensuous mood and painterly bravura.<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Thus at their shady lodge arrived, both stood, </l>
									<l>Both turned, and under open sky adored </l>
									<l>The God that made both sky, air, earth and heaven. </l>
									<l>Which they beheld, the moon's resplendent globe </l>
									<l>And starry pole: Thou also madest the night, </l>
									<l>Maker omnipotent . . . (<title level="m">Paradise Lost</title> 4.720-25)</l>
								</lg>
							</q>
						</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>Notes</head>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn1">1. <title level="m">2 Henry VI</title> (1.4.16-19); Norris (304).</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn2">2. Fitter (<title level="m">Poetry, Space, Landscape </title>8-9, 14).</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn3">3. Homer (<title level="m">Iliad</title> 1.54, 12.463).</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn4">4. Tartarus: Hesiod (<title level="m">Theogony</title> 728); Horace (<title level="m">Odes</title> 1.4.16-17); twins: Tartarus (<title level="m">Theogony</title> 211, 758); Homer (<title level="m">Iliad</title> 14.231, 16.454, 672); <title level="m">Orphic Hymns</title> (85.8); Renaissance: see the bibliography in Wind's <title level="m">Pagan Mysteries in the Renaissance</title> (165 n.55). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn5">5. Hesiod, <title level="m">Theogony</title> (211-24); Lucan, <title level="m">Pharsalia</title> (6.510 ff); Euripides (<title level="m">Iphigenia in Taurus </title>1027); Horace (<title level="m">Epistles </title>1.16.62); Valerius Flaccus (<title level="m">Argonautica</title> 2.41-42).</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn6">6. Katharine Allen (<title level="m">The Treatment of Nature in Poetry of the Roman Republic</title> 205). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn7">7. Sappho (148); vetus colonus Horace (<title level="m">Odes</title> 3.6.44-48, <title level="m">Tibullus</title> 1.1.43-44); quotation from Alcman (134). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn8">8. Sappho (147); compare number 62 (150); Virgil (<title level="m">Aeneid</title> 4.522-9); Petrarch (<title level="m">Rime</title> 144 [<title level="m">In Vita</title> 164]), Surrey (<q direct="y">Alas, so all things now do hold their peace</q>). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn9">9. For the broad evolution of Greek attitudes to nature see Segal's <q direct="y">Nature and the World of Man in Greek Literature.</q>
						</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn10">10. Walbank (219). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn11">11. Erwin Panofsky (<q direct="y">Et in Arcadia ego</q> 346), referring to Virgil (<title level="m">Eclogues</title> 1.83, 6.846, 10.77).</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn12">12. Moon and marriage: Euripides (<title level="m">Iphigenia in Aulis</title> 717); Hylas and Jason: Apollonius Rhodios (<title level="m">Argonautica</title> 1.1231, 4.165); Virgil (<title level="m">Aeneid</title> 7.10, 8.22-25); Homer (<title level="m">Odyssey</title> 7.84).</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn13">13. Virgil (<title level="m">Aeneid</title> 8.26-33); Theocritus (<title level="m">Idylls</title> 2); Ovid (<title level="m">Metamorphoses</title> 7.184-91).</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn14">14. Theocritus (<title level="m">Idylls</title> 2.118-28); on Dionysus shrunk to Bacchus see Euripides (<title level="m">Bacchae</title> XI-XIII).</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn15">15. Chaucer (<title level="m">Troilus and Criseyde</title> 3.1429-42, 1450-56); Donne (<q direct="y">The Sun Rising</q>). On medieval amorous night-visits, a European rather than English vogue, Baskerville's <q direct="y">English songs on the night visit.</q>
						</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn16">16. Dodds (<title level="m">Pagan and Christian in an Age of Anxiety</title> (37).</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn17">17. Monasticism and moonlight: Leclercq (<title level="m">The Love of Learning and the Desire for God</title> 131); on mighty starscapes in Senecan tragedy, for instance, Herington (185-87); Julian (<title level="m">Orations</title> 5.130 C-D).</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn18">18. On biblical night and religious wisdom or theophany see also <title level="m">2 Chronicles</title> 1.7.7.12; <title level="m">Job</title> 4.13, 33.15; <title level="m">Psalms</title> 17.3, 63.6; <title level="m">Daniel</title> 7.2.</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn19">19. For instance <title level="m">Jeremiah</title> 6.4; <title level="m">Micah </title>3.6. On this theme see Gaster (<title level="m">Myth, Legend and Custom in the Old Testament</title> (section 335, 813-14).</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn20">20. <title level="m">Beowulf</title> (193, 115, 702-03). <q direct="y">Dream of the Rood</q> (68). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn21">21. Homer (<title level="m">Iliad</title> 22.317-19). Aretino (<title level="m">II Terzo Libro delle Lettere</title> 47): ref. Gombrich (117). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn22">22. Stesichorus (154); rosy light of dawn: Ovid (<title level="m">Metamorphoses</title> 2.113), Lucretius (<title level="m">De Rerum Natura</title> 5.461). Douglas (96); Shakespeare (<title level="m">Macbeth </title>3.2.52). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn23">23. Hale (<title level="m">Renaissance Europe 1480-1520</title> 27, 42). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn24">24. Thirteenth-century lyric, printed in Bennett and Smithers (129); <title level="m">The Owl and the Nightingale</title> (185-88); <title level="m">Beowulf</title> (703); <title level="m">I Henry IV </title>(1.2.24-33), <title level="m">Winter's Tale</title> (4.3.16-18): compare <title level="m">The Rape of Lucrece</title> (125-26); <title level="m">Richard III</title> (1.1.72). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn25">25. <title level="m">The Rape of Lucrece</title> (167); night watch: see Thomas (<title level="m">Religion and the Decline of Magic</title> 702); Benandanti, see Ginzburg (<title level="m">The Night Battles: Witchcraft and Agrarian Cults</title>).</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn26">26. Marston and Ascham: see notes to Shakespeare (<title level="m">Macbeth</title>, ed. Muir) for 2.1.49-50 and 3.2.53. Nashe (<title level="m">The Terrors of the Night</title> 249, 2O9). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn27">27. <title level="m">Il Penseroso</title>, it may be objected, is not primarily a nocturne: but if it cannot be wholly conformed to any genre, in its proceedings <title level="m">sui generis</title>
							<q direct="y">Night</q> as opposed to the <q direct="y">Day</q> of <title level="m">L'Allegro</title> is clearly its dominant setting. Elaborating and innovating nocturnal actions and motifs for two-thirds of the poem, it will prove indeed the locus classicus of nocturnal properties and inspiration for two succeeding centuries. </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn28">28. Vaughan (<q direct="y">As time one day by me did pass</q> l. 9; <q direct="y">Hailsum rest</q>: Douglas (<title level="m">Aeneid</title>, prologue to book 13, l. 46); <q direct="y">romancey</q> taste see Leishman (<title level="m">The Art of Marvell's Poetry</title> 263-67); Herrick (<q direct="y">Oberon's Palace</q> 21, 84); Drayton (<q direct="y">Nimphidia</q> 369-432). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn29">29. Chapman (<q direct="y">Hymnus in Noctem</q> [part one of <title level="m">The Shadow of the Night</title>] 269-70); Milton (<title level="m">Il Penseroso</title> 50, 27). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn30">30. Milton (<title level="m">Il Penseroso</title> 83-84, 122). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn31">31. Panofsky (<title level="m">Early Netherlandish Painting </title>236). On nocturnes in seventeenth century Dutch painting see Stechow (<title level="m">Dutch Landscape Painting of the Seventeenth Century</title> 171-82). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn32">32. <q direct="y">Un notte</q>: ref. Clark (<title level="m">Landscape into Art</title> 105); Sidney (<title level="m">Arcadia</title> 172); <q direct="y">ineffable sense</q>: Turner (<title level="m">The Vision of Landscape in Renaissance Italy</title> 115); Tasso (cit. in Turner 115). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn33">33. Ogden and Ogden (<title level="m">English Taste in Landscape</title> 51-2, 139-40), Stechow (177-79); <q direct="y">Luminalia: The Queen's Festival of Light</q> (Orgel and Strong, <title level="m">Inigo Jones: The Theatre of the Stuart Court</title> 2.706, 58-9); Clark (<title level="m">Landscape into Art</title> 105).</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn34">34. <title level="m">A Midsummer Night's Dream</title> (1.1.209-10), <title level="m">The Winter's Tale</title> (4.4.174-76), Spenser (<title level="m">Shepherd's Calendar</title>, <q direct="y">August</q> 89-91); for the putative influence of Spenser, see Shakespeare (<title level="m">A Midsummer Night's Dream</title> [Brooks, ed.] LXII). Goldin (<title level="m">Lyrics of the Troubadours and Trouveres</title> 195). Marlowe (<title level="m">Hero and Leander</title> 188-91).</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn35">35. Drayton (<q direct="y">The First Eclog</q> [<title level="m">Idea: The Shepheards Garland</title>] 79-82); Jonson (<q direct="y">Queen and Huntress</q> 17-18.</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn36">36. Shakespeare (<title level="m">The Merchant of Venice</title> 5.1.54, 1-3); Greville (<title level="m">Caelica</title>, sonnet 6); Spenser (<title level="m">Faerie Queene</title> 2.12.78.8-9); Habington (<q direct="y">Nox nocti scientiam</q> 3-4); Shakespeare (<title level="m">Romeo and Juliet </title>1.5.43-44); Cotton (<q direct="y">Night Quatrains</q> sts. 7, 8); Browne (<title level="m">Britannia's Pastorals</title> book 2, song 1, 792-96): see Ovid (<title level="m">Metamorphoses</title> 7.186-88). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn37">37. <q direct="y">Spangled</q>: Shakespeare (<title level="m">Midsummer Night's Dream</title> 2.1.29); Vaughan (<q direct="y">The Star</q> 1-4), echoing Herbert (<q direct="y">The Star</q> l. 26); Vaughan (<q direct="y">A Rhapsody</q> 10-14); Vaughan (<q direct="y">The Day-Spring</q> 1-2); Shakespeare (<title level="m">Merchant of Venice</title> 5.1.54, 60-65); Vaughan (<q direct="y">They are all gone</q> 1-8). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn38">38. Milton (<title level="m">Comus</title> 334): the <q direct="y">double-darkness</q> conceit recurs in <title level="m">Paradise Regained</title> (1.500) and <title level="m">Samson Agonistes</title> (593) to indicate likewise an absolute density of darkness. Ovid (<title level="m">Metamorphoses</title> 11.50) may have been an influence. </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn39">39. Shakespeare (<title level="m">A Midsummer Night's Dream</title> 5.1.264-67); <title level="m">OED </title>gives as the first recorded use of this meaning (<title level="m">Hamlet </title>3.2.152; <q direct="y">moons with borrowed sheen</q>); but this overlooks <title level="m">Midsummer Night's Dream</title> (2.1.29). Note Milton's delighted echoes in <title level="m">Comus</title> (1002, 892). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn40">40. On the Renaissance Orphic association of Night with the invisible First Cause, see Pico della Mirandola (<q direct="y">Orphic Conclusions</q> 15 [1.107]). Vaughan (<q direct="y">The Night</q> 49-50); Milton (<title level="m">Paradise Lost</title> 3.380); Babb (<q direct="y">The background of <title level="m">Il Penseroso</title>
							</q> 267); Leishman, <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">L'Allegro</title> and <title level="m">Il Penseroso</title> in Their relation to Seventeenth-Century Poetry</q> 67); Fletcher's <q direct="y">Song</q> (<title level="m">The Nice Valour</title> 4-7, 12-15; cit. Leishman <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">L'Allegro</title>
							</q> 60).</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn41">41. Cavendish (<title level="m">Nature's Pictures</title> 388; <title level="m">Poems and Fancies</title> 107); Milton (<title level="m">Prolusions</title> 1 1.231-32); Davenant (<title level="m">Luminalia</title> [Night's first Song] 93-94; Browne (<title level="m">Britannia's Pastorals </title>[book 1, song 1] 810); Shakespeare (<title level="m">Midsummer Night's Dream</title> 5.1.168-70). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn42">42. Shakespeare (<title level="m">Midsummer Night's Dream</title> 3.2.379-88; 5.1.360-76).</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn43">43. Chapman (<title level="m">The Shadow of the Night </title>[parts one and three], <q direct="y">Epistle to Roydon</q> 1-2; <q direct="y">Hymnus in Cynthiam</q> 168-69); Chapman (<q direct="y">Hymnus in Noctem</q> 202, 225-27, 268). Yates (<title level="m">Occult Philosophy</title> 135-46). Chapman (<q direct="y">Epistle to Roydon</q> 9, 14).</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn44">44. Hill (<title level="m">The World Turned Upside Down</title> 185, 289-93, 185). Allen (<q direct="y">Scientific Studies in the English Universities of the Seventeenth Century</q> 225-27, 219). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn45">45. Yates (<title level="m">Giordano Bruno and the Hermetic Tradition</title> 399, 403). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn46">46. Sylvester (<q direct="y">Du Bartas, His First Week</q> 1.24, 565-87). <q direct="y">Elysium,</q> Shakespeare (<title level="m">Henry V</title> 4.1.279-80); <q direct="y">clown,</q> Browne (<title level="m">Britannia's Pastorals</title> [book 2, song 1] 801-06). Contrast the apolitical tributes to luxurious sleep in Sidney's <title level="m">Astrophil and Stella</title> (39 and 98), Spenser's <title level="m">Epithalamium</title> (st. 20), Shakespeare's <title level="m">Macbeth</title> (2.2.34-39). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn47">47. Vaughan (<q direct="y">A Rhapsody</q> 71-72). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn48">48. Jonson (<q direct="y">The Fairy beam upon you</q> 1-5 [<q direct="y">The Gypsies Metamorphosed</q> 325]); Herrick (<q direct="y">The night-piece, to Julia</q> 1-5). I suspect that these two poets are indebted to Shakespeare's Song in <title level="m">Cymbeline</title>, third stanza (4.2.277-82), for mood and imagery here.</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn49">49. Wither (<title level="m">A Collection of Emblemes, Ancient and Moderne</title> Emblem 9); Herrick (<q direct="y">The Argument</q> [to <title level="m">Hesperides</title>] 3-6, 11-12).</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn50">50. On Protestants, ghosts and faeries see Thomas (<title level="m">Religion and the Decline of Magic </title>701-11, 725, 729); fairy-tricksters (Thomas 732-34); on Shakespeare's fairy revolution see Briggs (<title level="m">The Anatomy of Puck</title> 45-47); Herrick (<q direct="y">The Fairy Temple</q> 25, 103, 98, 107); <q direct="y">theatre of mysteries</q> is a phrase of Graham Parry on the masque (<title level="m">The Golden Age Restored</title> 42). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn51">51. Chaucer (<q direct="y">The Complaint of Mars</q> 12); <q direct="y">The Wife of Bath's Prologue and Tale</q> 397-99); Thomas Adams (<q direct="y">The Sinner's Passing-bell</q> [1614; in <title level="m">Works</title> {London: 1861}] 1.347; cit. <title level="m">OED</title>, <q direct="y">noctivagant</q>); Fletcher (<title level="m">The Lover's Progress</title>; cit. Tilley, <title level="m">A Dictionary of the Proverbs in England in the Sixteenth and Sseventeenth Centuries</title> N 169); Shakespeare (<title level="m">2 Henry IV</title> 3.2.193-94); Suckling (<title level="m">Works </title>2.4.2.5-7); on Luminalia connection, see Freehafer (<q direct="y">The Italian Night Piece and Suckling's <title level="m">Aglaura</title>
							</q>). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn52">52. Vaughan (<q direct="y">The Night</q> 25-28). On Vaughan's nature sensibility as formed by war see Fitter (<q direct="y">Henry Vaughan's Landscapes of Military Occupation</q>).</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn53">53. Milton (<title level="m">Paradise Lost </title>9.58, 159, 181; 5.206-08); see Fowler's note to 5.206-08 in his edition (687). Compare the <q direct="y">night-hag</q> (2.662-66).</note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn54">54. <title level="m">Miniatura</title> (cit. Ogden and Ogden 12). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn55">55. <title level="m">Paradise Lost</title> (7.577-78, 580-81); <title level="m">Comus</title> (220-24, 332-34). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn56">56. Shakespeare (<title level="m">Midsummer Night's Dream</title> 2.1.29); Milton (<title level="m">Comus</title> 1002). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn57">57. Carey (<title level="m">Milton</title> 41-54). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn58">58. Milton (<title level="m">Paradise Lost</title> 4.598-609, 646-49, 654-56). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn59">59. See Fitter (<title level="m">Poetry, Space, Landscape</title> ch. 6, esp. 277-92). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn60">60. Schultz (<q direct="y">Satan's Serenade</q>). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn61">61. Herbert (<q direct="y">The Pulley</q> 14). </note>
						<note id="emls3-2fittnoctn62">62. Milton (<title level="m">Paradise Lost</title> 9.1017-18; 4.207, 199-200). </note>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<p>
							<listBibl>
								<head>Works Cited</head>
								<bibl>Alcman. Sleep. 134 in Greek Verse.</bibl>
								<bibl>Allen, Katharine. <title level="m">The Treatment of Nature in Poetry of the Roman Republic</title>. Madison: Wisconsin UP, 1899.</bibl>
								<bibl>Allen, Phyllis. <title level="a">Scientific Studies in the English Universities of the Seventeenth Century</title>. <title level="j">Journal of the History of Ideas</title> 10 (1949): 219-53.</bibl>
								<bibl>Apollonius Rhodios. <title level="m">Argonautica</title>. Trans. E.V. Rieu. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1959.</bibl>
								<bibl>Aretino, Pietro. <title level="m">Il Terzo Libro delle Lettere</title>. Venice: 1546.</bibl>
								<bibl>Babb, Lawrence. <title level="a">The Background of <title level="m">Il Penseroso</title>
									</title>. <title level="j">Studies in Philology</title> 37 (1940): 257-73.</bibl>
								<bibl>Baskerville, C.R. <title level="a">English Songs on the Night Visit</title>. <title level="j">Publications of the Modern Language Association</title> 36 (1921): 565-614.</bibl>
								<bibl>Bennett, J.A.W., and G.V. Smithers. <title level="m">Early Middle English Verse and Prose</title>. 2nd ed. Oxford: Oxford UP, 1974. </bibl>
								<bibl>
									<title level="m">Beowulf</title>. Ed. C.L. Wrenn. 2nd ed. London: Harrap, 1958.</bibl>
								<bibl>Briggs, K.M. <title level="m">The Anatomy of Puck</title>. London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1959.</bibl>
								<bibl>Browne, William. <title level="a">Book two, Song one, Brittannia's Pastorals</title>. 1.217-18 in A.H. Bullen, ed. <title level="m">The Poems of William Browne of Tavistock</title>. 2 vols. London: Lawrence and Bullen, 1894.</bibl>
								<bibl>Carey, John. <title level="m">Milton</title>. London: Evans Brothers, 1969.</bibl>
								<bibl>Cavendish, Margaret. <title level="m">Poems and Fancies</title>. London: 1653.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">Nature's Pictures</title>. London: 1656.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">Poems and Fancies</title>. London: 1653. </bibl>
								<bibl>Chapman, George. <title level="a">Epistle to Roydon</title>, <title level="a">Hymnus in Noctem</title>, <title level="a">Hymnus in Cynthiam</title>. <title level="m">The Shadow of the Night</title>. 20-45 in Phyllis Bartlett, ed. <title level="m">Poems of George Chapman</title>. London: Oxford UP: 1941.</bibl>
								<bibl>Chaucer, Geoffrey. <title level="a">The Wife of Bath's Prologue and Tale</title>. 76-89 in F.N. Robinson, ed. <title level="m">The Canterbury Tales</title>. <title level="m">The Works of Geoffrey Chaucer</title>. 2nd ed. Oxford: Oxford UP, 1974. </bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">The Complaint of Mars</title>. 529-33 in Geoffrey Chaucer. <title level="m">Works</title>.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">Troilus and Criseyde</title>. 385-479 in Geoffrey Chaucer. <title level="m">Works</title>.</bibl>
								<bibl>Clark, Kenneth. <title level="m">Landscape into Art</title>. 2nd ed. London: John Murray, 1979.</bibl>
								<bibl>Cotton, Charles. <title level="a">Night Quatrains</title>. <title level="m">Poems of Charles Cotton</title>. Ed. John Buxton. London: 1958.</bibl>
								<bibl>Davenant, William. <title level="m">Luminalia: the Queen's Festival of Light</title>. Vol. 2. of Steven Orgel and Roy Strong, eds. <title level="m">Inigo Jones: The Theater of the Stuart Court</title>. Berkeley and Los Angeles: U of California P, 1973. </bibl>
								<bibl>Dodds, E.R. <title level="m">Pagan and Christian in an Age of Anxiety</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1968.</bibl>
								<bibl>Donne, John. <title level="a">The Sun Rising</title>. 92-93 in John Carey, ed. <title level="m">John Donne</title>. Oxford: Oxford UP, 1990.</bibl>
								<bibl>Douglas, Gavin. <title level="m">The Aeneid. Selections from Gavin Douglas</title>. Ed. David Coldwell. Oxford: Oxford UP, 1964.</bibl>
								<bibl>Drayton. <title level="a">Nimphidia</title>. 1.177-200 in John Buxton, ed. <title level="m">Poems of Michael Drayton</title>. 2 vols. London: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1953.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="a">The First Eclogue</title> from <title level="m">Idea: The Shepherd's Garland</title>. 1.49 in J.W. Hebel, ed. <title level="m">Complete Works of Michael Drayton</title>. 5 Vols. Oxford: Oxford UP, 1961. </bibl>
								<bibl>
									<title level="a">Dream of the Rood</title>. 159-71 in Richard Hamer, ed. <title level="m">A Choice of Anglo-Saxon Verse</title>. London: Faber, 1970.</bibl>
								<bibl>Euripides. <title level="m">Iphigenia in Taurus</title>. Trans. Philip Vellacott. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1974.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">Bacchae</title>. Ed. E.R. Dodds. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1960.</bibl>
								<bibl>Fitter, Chris. <title level="m">Poetry, Space, Landscape: Toward a New Theory</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1995.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="a">Henry Vaughan's Landscapes and Military Occupation</title>. <title level="j">Essays in Criticism</title> 42 (April 1992): 123-47.</bibl>
								<bibl>Fletcher, John. <title level="m">The Nice Valour</title>. London, 1647. </bibl>
								<bibl>Freehafer, John. <title level="a">The Italian Night Piece and Suckling's <title level="m">Aglaura</title>
									</title>. <title level="j">Journal of English and Germanic Philology</title> 67 (1968): 249-65. </bibl>
								<bibl>Gaster, T.H. <title level="m">Myth, Legend and Custom in the Old Testament</title>. New York: Harper and Row,1969.</bibl>
								<bibl>Ginzburg, Carlo. <title level="m">The Night Battles: Witchcraft and Agrarian Cults</title>. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1983.</bibl>
								<bibl>Goldin, Frederick. <title level="m">Lyrics of the Troubadors and Trouveres</title>. Gloucester, Mass: Peter Smith,1983. </bibl>
								<bibl>Gombrich, E.H. <title level="m">Norm and Form</title>. 3rd ed. Oxford: Phaidon, 1978.</bibl>
								<bibl>Greek Verse. <title level="m">The Penguin Book of Greek Verse</title>. Ed. and trans. Constantine Trypannis. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1971.</bibl>
								<bibl>Greville, Fulke. <title level="a">In Night when colours all to black are cast</title>, <title level="m">Caelica</title>. 591-2 in Richard S. Sylvester, ed. <title level="m">English Sixteenth Century Verse</title>. New York: Norton, 1984.</bibl>
								<bibl>Habington, William. <title level="a">Nox nocti scientiam</title>. 127-28 in Kenneth Allott, ed. <title level="m">The Poems of William Habington</title>. London: Hodder and Stoughton, 1948. </bibl>
								<bibl>Hale, J.R. <title level="m">Renaissance Europe 1480-1520</title>. London: Fontana, 1971</bibl>
								<bibl>Herbert, George. <title level="m">The English Poems of George Herbert</title>. Ed. C.A. Patrides. London: J.M. Dent, 1974. </bibl>
								<bibl>Herington, C.J. <title level="a">Senecan Tragedy</title>. 170-219 in Niall Rudd, ed. <title level="m">Essays in Classical Literature</title>. Cambridge: Heffer, 1972. </bibl>
								<bibl>Herrick, Robert. <title level="m">Poetical Works of Robert Herrick</title>. Ed. L.C. Martin. Oxford: Oxford UP, 1956.</bibl>
								<bibl>Hesiod. <title level="m">Theogony</title>. 23-57 in Dorothea Wender, trans. <title level="m">Hesiod and Theognis</title>. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1973.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">The Works and Days</title>. 59-86 in Dorothea Wender, trans. <title level="m">Hesiod and Theognis</title>. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1973. </bibl>
								<bibl>Hill, Christopher. <title level="m">The World Turned Upside Down</title>. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1975.</bibl>
								<bibl>Homer. <title level="m">The Iliad</title>. Trans. E.V. Rieu. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1950.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">The Odyssey</title>. Trans. E.V.Rieu. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1946.</bibl>
								<bibl>Horace. <title level="m">The Odes of Horace</title>. Trans. James Michie. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1967.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">Epistles</title>. Trans. Niall Rudd. Horace: Satires and Epistles. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1979.</bibl>
								<bibl>Jonson, Benjamin. <title level="m">Complete Poems of Ben Jonson</title>. Ed. George Parfitt. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1988.</bibl>
								<bibl>Julian. <title level="m">Orations</title>. <title level="m">Julian</title>. Ed. and trans. W.C.Wright. 3 vols. Cambridge, Mass: Harvard UP, 1913-23.</bibl>
								<bibl>Leclercq, Jean. <title level="m">The Love of Learning and the Desire for God: A Study of Monastic Culture</title>. New York: Fordham, 1961.</bibl>
								<bibl>Leishman, J.B. <title level="m">The Art of Marvell's Poetry</title>. London: Longman, 1968.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="a">
										<title level="m">L'Allegro</title> and <title level="m">Il Penseroso</title> in their Relation to Seventeenth-century Poetry</title>. 58-93 in Alan Rudrum, ed. <title level="m">Milton: Modern Judgements</title>. London: Macmillan, 1968.</bibl>
								<bibl>Lucan. <title level="m">Pharsalia</title>. Trans. Robert Graves. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1956.</bibl>
								<bibl>Lucretius. <title level="m">De Rerum Natura</title>. Trans. W.H.D. Rouse. Cambridge, Mass: Harvard UP, 1937.</bibl>
								<bibl>Marlowe, Christopher. <title level="m">Hero and Leander</title>. 13-40 in Stephen Orgel, ed. <title level="m">The Complete Poems and Translations</title>. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1971.</bibl>
								<bibl>Milton, John. <title level="m">Comus: A Masque</title>. 168-229 in John Carey and Alastair Fowler, eds. <title level="m">The Poems of John Milton</title>. London: Longman, 1980. </bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">Il Penseroso</title>. 139-146 in John Milton. <title level="m">Poems</title>.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">Paradise Lost</title>. 419-1060 in John Milton. <title level="m">Poems</title>.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">Samson Agonistes</title>. 330-402 in John Milton. <title level="m">Poems</title>.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="a">First Prolusion</title>. 1.211-307. [Trans. Phyllis B. Tillyard.] <title level="m">The Complete Prose works of John Milton</title>. 8 vols. New Haven: Yale UP, 1953.</bibl>
								<bibl>Nashe, Thomas. <title level="m">The Terrors of the Night</title>. In J.B. Steane, ed. <title level="m">The Unfortunate Traveller and Other Works</title>. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1972.</bibl>
								<bibl>Norgate, Edward. <title level="m">Miniatura</title>. 2nd ed. 1649.</bibl>
								<bibl>Norris, John, of Bemerton. <title level="a">Hymn to Darkness</title>. 303-04 in Helen Gardner. <title level="m">The Metaphysical Poets</title>. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1972. </bibl>
								<bibl>Ogden, H.V.S. and M.S. Ogden. <title level="m">English Taste in Landscape in the Seventeenth Century</title>. Ann Arbor: U of Michigan P, 1955.</bibl>
								<bibl>Orgel, Steven and Roy Strong. <title level="m">Inigo Jones: the Theater of the Stuart Court</title>. Berkeley and Los Angeles: U of California P, 1973.</bibl>
								<bibl>
									<title level="m">Orphica</title>. E. Abel, ed. Leipzig, 1885.</bibl>
								<bibl>Ovid. <title level="m">Metamorphoses</title>. Trans. F.J. Miller. Cambridge, Mass: Harvard UP, 1916.</bibl>
								<bibl>
									<title level="m">Owl and the Nightingale, The</title>. 1-27 in Bennett and Smithers. <title level="m">Early Middle English Verse and Prose</title>.</bibl>
								<bibl>Panofsky, Erwin. <title level="a">Et in Arcadia Ego</title>. 340-367 in <title level="m">Meaning in the Visual Arts</title>. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1983.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">Early Netherlandish Painting</title>. 2 vols. Cambridge, Mass: Harvard UP, 1953.</bibl>
								<bibl>Parry, Graham. <title level="m">The Golden Age Restored</title>. Manchester: Manchester UP, 1981.</bibl>
								<bibl>Petrarch, Francesco. <title level="m">Le Rime de Francesco Petrarca</title>. Eds. G. Carducci and S. Ferrari. Firenzi: Sansoni, 1899.</bibl>
								<bibl>Pico della Mirandola. <title level="a">Orphic Conclusions</title>. Vol. 1. <title level="m">Opera Omnia</title>. Basel, 1572.</bibl>
								<bibl>Sappho. <title level="m">Lyric fragments</title>. 144-151 in Greek Verse.</bibl>
								<bibl>Schultz, Howard. <title level="a">Satan's Serenade</title>. <title level="j">Philological Quarterly</title> 27 (1948): 17-26.</bibl>
								<bibl>Segal, C.P. <title level="a">Nature and the World of Man in Greek Literature</title>. <title level="j">Arion</title> 2 (1963): 19-53.</bibl>
								<bibl>Shakespeare, William. <title level="m">A Midsummer Night's Dream</title>. Ed. Harold F. Brooks. London: Methuen, 1979.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">The Second Part of King Henry VI</title>. Ed. Michael Hathaway. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1991.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">Henry V</title>. Ed. J.H. Walter. London: Methuen, 1954.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">Macbeth</title>. Ed. Kenneth Muir. London: Methuen, 1962.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">Merchant of Venice, The</title>. Ed. John Russell Brown. London: Methuen, 1964.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">Rape of Lucrece, The</title>. In F.T. Prince, ed. <title level="m">Shakespeare: The Poems</title>. London: Methuen, 1969.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">Romeo and Juliet</title>. Ed. Brian Gibbons. London: Methuen, 1980.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">Winter's Tale, The</title>. Ed. J.H.P. Pafford. London: Methuen, 1963.</bibl>
								<bibl>Sidney, Philip. <title level="m">The Countess of Pembroke's Arcadia</title>. Vol. 1 of Albert Feuillerat, ed. <title level="m">The Works of Sir Philip Sidney</title>. 4 vols. London: 1912.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">Astrophil and Stella</title>. 153-211 in Katherine Duncan-Jones, ed. Sir Philip Sidney. Oxford: Oxford UP, 1989.</bibl>
								<bibl>Spenser, Edmund. <title level="m">The Faerie Queene</title>. Ed. A.C Hamilton. London: Longman, 1977.</bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">Epithalamium</title>. 579-84 inJ.C. Smith and E. De Selincourt, eds. <title level="m">Spenser: Poetical Works</title>. London: Oxford UP, 1912.</bibl>
								<bibl>Stechow, Wolfgang. <title level="m">Dutch Landscape Painting of the Seventeenth Century</title>. 3rd ed. Oxford: Phaidon, 1966.</bibl>
								<bibl>Stesichorus. <title level="a">The Setting Sun</title>. 154 in Greek Verse.</bibl>
								<bibl>Suckling, John. <title level="m">Aglaura</title>. 2.33-119 in L.A. Beaurline, ed. <title level="m">The Works of Sir John Suckling</title>. Vol. 2. <title level="m">The Plays</title>.Oxford: Oxford UP, 1971.</bibl>
								<bibl>
									<title level="m">Surrey, Henry Howard, Earl of</title>. In Richard S. Sylvester, ed. <title level="m">English Sixteenth-Century Verse</title>. New York: Norton, 1984.</bibl>
								<bibl>Sylvester, Joshua. <title level="m">Du Bartas, His First Week. First Day</title>. 1.23-25 in A.B. Grosart, ed. <title level="m">Complete Works of Joshua Sylvester</title>. New York: AMS P, 1967.</bibl>
								<bibl>Theocritus. <title level="m">Idylls</title>. 5-361 in J.M. Edmonds, trans. <title level="m">The Greek Bucolic Poets</title>. Cambridge, Mass: Harvard UP, 1928.</bibl>
								<bibl>Thomas, Keith. <title level="m">Religion and the Decline of Magic</title>. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1978. </bibl>
								<bibl>Tibullus. <title level="m">The Poems</title>. Trans. Philip Dunlop. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1972.</bibl>
								<bibl>Tilley, M.P. <title level="m">A Dictionary of the Proverbs in England in the Sixteenth and Seventeenth Centuries</title>. Ann Arbor: U of Michigan P, 1950.</bibl>
								<bibl>Turner, A.R. <title level="m">The Vision of Landscape in Renaissance Italy</title>. Princeton: Princeton UP: 1966.</bibl>
								<bibl>Valerius Flaccus. <title level="m">Argonautica</title>. Trans J.H. Mozley. Cambridge, Mass: Harvard UP, 1934.</bibl>
								<bibl>Vaughan, Henry. <title level="m">The Complete Poems</title>. Ed. Alan Rudrum. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1976.</bibl>
								<bibl>Virgil. <title level="m">The Aeneid</title>. Trans. W.F. Jackson Knight. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 1958. </bibl>
								<bibl>Walbank, F.W. <title level="m">The Hellenistic World</title>. London: Fontana, 1981.</bibl>
								<bibl>Wind, Edgar. <title level="m">Pagan Mysteries in the Renaissance</title>. London: Faber, 1968.</bibl>
								<bibl>Wither, George. <title level="m">A Collection of Emblemes, Ancient and Moderne</title>. 1635. Ed. Rosemary Freeman. Columbia, South Carolina: U of South Carolina P, 1975.</bibl>
								<bibl>Yates, Frances. <title level="m">Giordano Bruno and the Hermetic Tradition</title>. Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1978. </bibl>
								<bibl>--- . <title level="m">The Occult Philosophy in the Elizabethan Age</title>. London: Routledge, 1979.</bibl>
							</listBibl>
						</p>
						<p>Responses to this piece intended for the Readers' Forum may be sent to the Editor at <!-- <a href="mailto:emls@ualberta.ca"> -->EMLS@UAlberta.ca<!-- </a> -->.</p>
					</div3>
					<byline>
						<!-- <a href="../emlshome.html" alt="emls home page"> -->
						<!-- <img src="../button.gif" height=47 width=124> -->
						<!-- </a> -->
						<!-- <a href="../emlscopy.html"> -->&copy;<!-- </a> --> 1997-, R.G. Siemens (Editor, <title level="j">EMLS</title>). (CF, KY, RGS, 30 September 1997)</byline>
				</div2>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="issuesection">
				<head>Professional Note</head>
				<div2 id="emls3-2burkperd" n="3" type="professionalnote">
					<head>
						<!-- <a href="http://human.ntu.ac.uk/foh/ems/perdita.html"> -->The Perdita Project<!-- </a> -->: A Database for Early Modern Women's Manuscript Compilations</head>
					<opener>
						<name>Victoria Burke</name> and <name>Elizabeth Clarke</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>Nottingham Trent University</addrLine>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href="mailto:perdita@ntu.ac.uk"> -->perdita@ntu.ac.uk<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
						<!-- <img src="../header2.gif" alt="early modern literary studies" width="283" height="87"> -->
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Burke, Victoria, and Elizabeth Clarke. <title level="a">The Perdita Project: A Database for Early Modern Women's Manuscript Compilations.</title>
						<title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 3.2 (September, 1997): 3.1-5 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/03-2/burkperd.html"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/03-2/burkperd.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;. </p>
					<div3>
						<p>
							<ref target="emls3-2burkperdoverview">Project Overview</ref> | <ref target="emls3-2burkperdmethodology">Methodology</ref> | <ref target="emls3-2burkperdparticipants">Participants</ref>
						</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 id="emls3-2burkperdoverview">
						<head>Project Overview</head>
						<p n="1">Literary and historical scholars have recognized in recent years the importance of the study of manuscripts for a more complete understanding of early modern and seventeenth-century culture. Until now, a major impediment to this research has been that manuscript compilations, particularly by women, are little known and are scattered in collections throughout the world. Nottingham Trent University, in partnership with Oxford University's Centre for Humanities Computing, is funding a three year project which aims to produce a comprehensive guide to over 400 manuscripts compiled by women. This will consist of a database covering compilations of poetry, religious writing, recipes, autobiographical material, and account books. It is intended to be a research tool for scholars of history, literature, cultural studies, and women's studies. The database will not include reproductions of texts, but will provide information on the contents of manuscripts and biographies of the compilers. Using this database, scholars will be able to identify networks of related manuscripts, and men and women who carried on a literary or social correspondence. They should also be able to ascertain whether a trip to the holding library is necessary. It is our intention that the database will help researchers, students, and the general public learn more about early women's writing in all of its forms.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 id="emls3-2burkperdmethodology">
						<head>Methodology</head>
						<p n="2">To enable the widest searching capacity, each manuscript will be described in detail in two different ways: by short articles and lists of information. Two short essays will provide an extended catalogue entry for the manuscript and a biography of the compiler. The catalogue entry will describe the contents of the manuscript, historicize the manuscript, and suggest similar manuscripts which would repay study. It will include a consideration of readership, literary genre and other types of manuscript writing, preliminary dedications, and scribal hands. A second article will provide a biography of the compiler, including her political, religious and class affiliations.</p>
						<p n="3">Information will be presented in a list format for the following areas: the collection in which the manuscript appears; dates; names of people mentioned in the manuscript with any extra information; names of places associated with the manuscript (including counties, European countries, and American colonies); physical characteristics of the manuscript (including size, details of binding, and numbers of folios, blank or otherwise); authors of transcribed material (in printed sources and other manuscript versions); references to printed books; receipts or recipes (medicinal, cookery, and other); accounts (household, real and personal estate, wages of servants, alienation of property, rents and rates); titles of poems, sermons, meditations, prayers; a first- and last-line poetry index; cross references with other manuscripts; references to scholarly articles and editions; and keyword search.</p>
						<p n="4">Much of the groundwork has already been done, but the research will proceed by study visits to libraries, and the use of microfilm copies. In partnership with Oxford University's Centre for Humanities Computing, we will be developing an encoding system following TEI guidelines which conforms to international standards (SGML). The information in the database will be encoded in such a way that complex and wide-ranging searches will be possible, and particular software and hardware will not be required. Publication is intended to be on the Internet, or possibly on CD-ROM. The database will be an important addition to the growing number of projects which merge the humanities with computing technology, such as the Brown Women Writers Project and The Orlando Project: An Integrated History of Women's Writing in the British Isles. A web site will be established where we will provide updated information about the project.</p>
						<p n="5">The project is funded for three years by Nottingham Trent University. Additional funding is being sought from the Humanities Research Board of the British Academy and from the Modern Humanities Research Association. If your department would be interested in using this material we would like to hear of your particular concerns and interests so that we can design the project most efficiently.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 id="emls3-2burkperdparticipants">
						<head>Participants (all at Nottingham Trent University): </head>
						<div4>
							<p>
								<list>
									<item>Elizabeth Clarke, Project Director</item>
									<item>Martyn Bennett, Project Director</item>
									<item>Victoria Burke, Postdoctoral Researcher</item>
									<item>Marie-Louise Coolahan, PhD Student</item>
								</list>
							</p>
						</div4>
						<div4>
							<head>Project Address: </head>
							<p>
								<address>
									<addrLine>The Perdita Project: A Database for Early Modern Women's Manuscript Compilations</addrLine>
									<addrLine>Faculty of Humanities</addrLine>
									<addrLine>Nottingham Trent University</addrLine>
									<addrLine>Clifton Lane</addrLine>
									<addrLine>Nottingham</addrLine>
									<addrLine>NG11 8NS</addrLine>
									<addrLine>England</addrLine>
								</address>
							</p>
							<p>E-Mail: <!-- <a href="mailto:perdita@ntu.ac.uk"> -->perdita@ntu.ac.uk<!-- </a> -->
							</p>
							<p>WWW: <!-- <a href="http://human.ntu.ac.uk/foh/ems/perdita.html"> -->http://human.ntu.ac.uk/foh/ems/perdita.html <!-- </a> -->
							</p>
							<p>Telephone: +44-(0)115-941-8418, ext. 3020.</p>
							<p>Responses to this piece intended for the Readers' Forum may be sent to the Editor at <!-- <a href="mailto:emls@ualberta.ca"> -->EMLS@UAlberta.ca<!-- </a> -->.</p>
						</div4>
					</div3>
					<byline>
						<!-- <a href="../emlshome.html"> -->
						<!-- <img src="../button.gif" width="124" height="47"> -->
						<!-- </a> -->
						<!-- <a href="../emlscopy.html"> -->&copy;<!-- </a> --> 1997-, R.G. Siemens (Editor, <title level="j">EMLS</title>). (VB, SL, RGS, 15 September 1997)</byline>
				</div2>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="issuesection">
				<head>Reviews</head>
				<div2 id="emls3-2revmcr1" n="4" type="review">
					<head>John Rogers. <title level="m">The Matter of Revolution: Science, Poetry, and Politics in the Age of Milton</title>. Ithaca: Cornell UP, 1996. xvi+257pp. ISBN 0 8014 3238 3 Cloth.</head>
					<opener>
						<name>Andrew McRae</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>University of Sydney</addrLine>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href="mailto:%22andrew.mcrae@english.usyd.edu.au%22"> -->Andrew.McRae@english.usyd.edu.au<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
						<!-- <img src="../header2.gif" alt="early"
width="283" height="87" modern literary studies> -->
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">McRae, Andrew. <title level="a">Review of <title level="m">The Matter of Revolution: Science, Poetry, and Politics in the Age of Milton</title>
						</title>. <title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 3.2 (September, 1997): 4.1-6 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/03-2/rev_mcr1.html"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/03-2/rev_mcr1.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;. </p>
					<p n="1">A document in the Public Record Office, dated March 5, 1651, links John Milton to the publication of two very different texts. The note directed to the Council of State firstly recommends the reprint of Milton's <title level="m">Defence of the English People</title>; and secondly records his complaint about the unauthorized publication of a treatise on rickets. This curious conjunction of Milton's political activism and scientific interest has never attracted more than passing reference from biographers. For John Rogers, however, it is one of many signposts to <q direct="y">the cultural intersections between those two events of seventeenth-century history known to us as the English and the Scientific Revolutions</q> (ix). </p>
					<p n="2">Rogers focuses on the philosophy of vitalism, which <q direct="y">holds in its tamest manifestation the inseparability of body and soul and, in its boldest, the infusion of all material substance with the power of reason and self-motion</q> (1). Although vitalism seems always to have carried an air of anachronism, it influenced a range of intellectual activity at the height of the Revolution, and informed the work of several major writers into the Restoration. Crucially, Rogers argues, vitalism drew together political and scientific speculation, each of which was concerned with understanding agents of change. The age's <q direct="y">analogical imperative</q> (9) authorized the search for correspondences between the human body, the natural world, and the nation. </p>
					<p n="3">
						<title level="m">The Matter of Revolution</title> is principally a text-based study, but moves with magisterial ease through discourses of science, religion and politics. It is an example of historicism at its very best: widely informed and immensely informative. At the heart of the book stands William Harvey, best known for his work on the circulation of blood, and fascinating in his uncertainty about the force propelling that motion. Early in his career, the body was a kingdom and the heart was its king; by 1649, however, blood itself was represented as the motivating agent. In the year of Charles I's execution, Harvey thus subjected <q direct="y">the government of the circulatory system</q> to its own <q direct="y">revolution</q> (20). For Rogers, this shift was neither an act of political opportunism, nor a sign of Harvey's own politics. It was, however, a central contribution to the <q direct="y">dangerously antiauthoritarian logic of the Vitalist Moment</q> (27). </p>
					<p n="4">Other chapters of the book focus on better-known authors. A chapter on Gerrard Winstanley and Andrew Marvell identifies a discourse of political agency characterized by a paradoxical passivism and a perception of nature as a revolutionary force. This argument is particularly effective in accounting for the blend of activity and passivity in Marvell's pastoral poetry. Rogers develops the line of analysis further in a chapter exploring the significance Marvell attaches to sexual abstinence. Virginity, especially in <title level="a">Upon Appleton House,</title> represents a certain religious and biological ideal, which forms the basis for a revolutionary conception of the individual and political organization. Sexual politics are raised again later in an analysis of Margaret Cavendish, who is seen to exploit the latent antipatriarchal logic of vitalism. Though Rogers perhaps seeks greater coherence in Cavendish's scientific tracts than they allow, he ably demonstrates their liberalism and opposition to gender-based oppression. </p>
					<p n="5">The impressive central chapters concentrate on Milton, deftly sliding from his political works to an analysis of <title level="m">Paradise Lost</title>. Rogers' account of Milton's science of creation and chaos is particularly impressive, throwing new light on the poem by going where many previous critics have feared to tread. His subsequent discussion of the expulsion pursues a central tension in the text, between an authoritarian conception of the universe and a revolutionary discourse of agency. Hence, while Michael is sent by God to drive Adam and Eve out of Paradise, it is also possible to identify a perception of the perfect natural world purging itself of impurities, leaving the first couple alone at the close under the law of nature.</p>
					<p n="6">Rogers concedes that vitalism's long-term impact was not great. Although it proffered a powerful form of liberalism, this vision was subsumed in the latter seventeenth century by Cartesian mechanism and Hobbesian authoritarianism. The liberalism of the eighteenth century was based therefore on a rejection of vitalism: <q direct="y">the new member of the liberal polity would be the negotiating citizen rather than the divinized saint</q> (226). But Rogers' study demonstrates the influence and the potential of a particular conception of nature and the nation, in all its <q direct="y">logical outlandishness</q> (ix) and imaginative appeal. His book is an achievement of stunning intellectual force and marvelously subtle interpretation. It demands the attention of anyone interested in the major writers and political movements of the seventeenth century.</p>
					<p>Responses to this piece intended for the Readers' Forum may be sent to the Editor at <!-- <a href="mailto:emls@ualberta.ca"> -->EMLS@UAlberta.ca<!-- </a> -->.</p>
					<byline>
						<!-- <a href="../emlshome.html" alt="emls home page"> -->
						<!-- <img src="../button.gif" width="124" height="47"> -->
						<!-- </a> -->
						<!-- <a href="../emlscopy.html"> -->&copy;<!-- </a> --> 1997-, R.G. Siemens (Editor, <title level="j">EMLS</title>). (JD, PB, LH, RGS, 11 September 1997)</byline>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls3-2revwil1" n="5" type="review">
					<head>Warren Chernaik. <title level="m">Sexual Freedom In Restoration Literature</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1995. xii+268 pp. ISBN 0 521 464 978 Cloth.</head>
					<opener>
						<name>Andrew P. Williams</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>North Carolina Central University</addrLine>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href="mailto:%22awilliam@wpo.nccu.edu%22"> -->awilliam@wpo.nccu.edu<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
						<!-- <img src="../header2.gif" alt="early"
width="283" height="87" modern literary studies> -->
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Williams, Andrew P. <title level="a">Review of <title level="m">Sexual Freedom In Restoration Literature</title>.</title>
						<title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 3.2 (September, 1997): 5.1-6 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/03-2/rev_wil1.html"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/03-2/rev_wil1.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;. </p>
					<p n="1">Any frank discussion of Restoration-era sexuality must adequately address the issue of the libertine ethos as a troubling political and cultural posture that privileged gender inequity and stratification all in the name of pleasure. In his <title level="m">Sexual Freedom In Restoration Literature</title>, Warren Chernaik deftly explores the code of the libertine where the pursuit of pleasure and complete sexual freedom regularly manifests itself amidst a literary framework that projects the nature of true libertinism as elusive and often contradictory. Focusing on the works of John Wilmot, Earl of Rochester and Aphra Behn, Chernaik identifies the libertine ethos as one struggling against competing desires for order and the need to rebel. The vacillation between order and rebellion provides a core, discursive framework for <title level="m">Sexual Freedom in Restoration Literature</title> as Chernaik demonstrates the libertine's inability to resolve this conflict within <title level="a">a single predictable pattern</title> (2). </p>
					<p n="2">Chernaik begins by positing libertinism within an historical context firmly rooted in the philosophy of Thomas Hobbes. For the libertine, Hobbesian doctrine became a <q direct="y">way of interpreting human conduct</q> (24). However, this interpretive strategy led to the appropriation of Hobbes as libertines such as Rochester routinely modified or ignored Hobbesian thought to suit their purposes. As a result, the literary expression of libertinism during the Restoration often revealed a lack of unifying philosophical principles, and instead, redirected the center of the libertine pursuit of total freedom into a narrowly defined absorption of the individual self. </p>
					<p n="3">Central to Chernaik's analysis of the libertine ethos is the presence of a fundamental paradox in its advocacy of certain incompatible principles. Namely, the libertine's aggressive pursuit of total freedom, especially in regards to the instinctual attainment of bodily pleasures, can never be obtained, due in part to the restlessness of the human condition which makes impossible the perfect compatibility of human desire and the fruition of that desire (32). Restoration literature, as Chernaik points out, identifies the locus of this unobtainable desire primarily within a Hobbesian psychology of the marketplace. Eschewing the Epicurean tranquillity of mind, <q direct="y">Hobbes' emphasis on the perpetual conflict between desire and fruition serves to commodify sexual freedom and fulfillment</q>
						<!--kah: added missing second quotation mark per rgs' suggestion--> within a market suffering from <q direct="y">permanent conditions of scarcity</q> (34). As a result, the libertine ethos expressed in such works as Etherege's <title level="m">The Man of Mode</title> and Congreve's <title level="m">The Way of the World</title> reveals a world in which the <q direct="y">desire for possession is infinite, but the rewards limited</q> (35). </p>
					<p n="4">The primary value of <title level="m">Sexual Freedom in Restoration Literature</title> to the student and scholar of the Restoration is Chernaik's discussion of numerous examples of Restoration Literature, especially the works of Rochester and Behn, which clearly demonstrate the frustration and ennui implicit within the libertine ethos. The libertine's pursuit of true sexual freedom routinely manifests itself in an uncomfortably sterile and nonpleasurable preoccupation with the physical self where <q direct="y">lust becomes indistinguishable from rage</q> (71). Chernaik's analysis, especially in regards to Rochester, presents the libertine male as trapped within an ethos of impenetrable contradictions, specifically, the libertine's simultaneous assertion and denial of complete human freedom (81). </p>
					<p n="5">Whereas Rochester's works such as <title level="a">I Rise at Eleven</title> and <title level="a">A Ramble in St. James's Park</title> posit the contradictory nature of the libertine ethos within the scope of the physical self and its contesting desire for and loathing of a wholly amoral and nonproductive sexuality, the expression of the libertine ethos in female writers of the Restoration, especially Aphra Behn, remains intently affixed to larger issues of competitive political and domestic manipulation. Though insisting that an equal degree of sexual desire exists between the sexes, Behn's work routinely critiques the inherent inequality of the libertine ethos where the sexual freedom of the man is usually purchased by the sexual enslavement of the female. Behn's poetry often calls into question certain core assumptions of the libertine ethos, especially the <q direct="y">traditional boundaries of gender</q>
						<!--kah: added missing first quotation mark per rgs' suggestion--> which <q direct="y">privilege one sex over another</q> (183). In poems such as <title level="a">An Ode to Love</title> and <title level="a">To Lysander at the Musick-Meeting,</title> Behn retains the libertine spirit of sexual freedom but inverts the traditional objectification of the female body, and instead, offers an erotic yet <q direct="y">androgynous ideal of beauty</q> which asserts the ability and right of the female poet <q direct="y">to revivify tradition</q> (174). Behn's response to the challenge of the male libertine to female sexual freedom was not confined to the construction of a desirable, yet nondescript sexual ideal; Behn's dramatic works consistently questioned the commodification of female sexuality, especially in the confines of marriage, where sexual consummation becomes a <q direct="y">means of asserting ownership</q> (190). Behn's female heroines routinely become active agents for their own sexual freedom, as in <title level="m">The Widow Ranter</title> where <q direct="y">the breeches role</q> not only disguises the title character, but is also reflective of her libertine <q direct="y">inward nature</q> (195). Chernaik ably demonstrates Behn's strategic response to the libertine ethos as a condemnation, not of libertinism itself, but of the social double standard which subjugates female sexual liberty. By making the <q direct="y">pursuit of sexual pleasure by women</q> a central issue in her work, Behn embraces the libertine's desire for complete sexual freedom, but she does so without condoning the aggressive and often violent expression of sexual power and control which often accompanied the libertine ethos (202). </p>
					<p n="6">
						<title level="m">Sexual Freedom in Restoration Literature</title> is an informative and succinct examination of the contesting ideologies of the libertine ethos and its place in Restoration Literature. Chernaik not only defines the historical and philosophical antecedents of Restoration libertinism, he situates it within a social context which considers the private, psychological and public, political ramifications of this ethos. <title level="m">Sexual Freedom in Restoration Literature</title> is a well researched and engaging text which exposes the ultimate contradiction of the libertine ethos; the advocacy of complete sexual freedom is advocacy of an illusion. Unfortunately, as Chernaik points out, the pursuit of an illusion can result in exploitation, corruption, and violence.</p>
					<p>Responses to this piece intended for the Readers' Forum may be sent to the Editor at <!-- <a href="mailto:emls@ualberta.ca"> -->EMLS@UAlberta.ca<!-- </a> -->. </p>
					<byline>
						<!-- <a href="../emlshome.html" alt="emls home page"> -->
						<!-- <img src="../button.gif" width="124" height="47"> -->
						<!-- </a> -->
						<!-- <a href="../emlscopy.html"> -->&copy;<!-- </a> --> 1997-, R.G. Siemens (Editor, <title level="j">EMLS</title>). (PB, LH, RGS, 15 September 1997) </byline>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls3-2revdaw2" n="6" type="review">
					<head>Stephen Orgel.<title level="m"> Impersonations: The Performance of Gender in Shakespeare's England</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1997. xv+179 pp. ISBN 0 521 56056X Cloth; 0 521 568 420 Paper. </head>
					<opener>
						<name>Anthony Dawson</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>University of British Columbia</addrLine>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href="mailto:%22dawson@unixg.ubc.ca%22"> -->dawson@unixg.ubc.ca<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
						<!-- <img src="../header2.gif" alt="early" width="283" height="87" modern literary studies> -->
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Dawson, Anthony. <title level="a">Review of <title level="m">Impersonations: The Performance of Gender in Shakespeare's England</title>.</title>
						<title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 3.2 (September, 1997): 6.1-6 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/03-2/rev_daw2.html"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/03-2/rev_daw2.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;. </p>
					<p n="">This is a short book with more interesting ideas and more cleverly marshalled information than most long ones. Written with magisterial ease, it ranges over the many questions that have been raised in the last decade or so concerning the boy actors, cross-dressing, homoeroticism, anti-theatricalism and the social position of women within <q direct="y">patriarchy,</q> offering fresh readings of familiar problems. Stephen Orgel excels at asking basic questions. One of the book's most engaging features is its refusal to accept automatically what has become the standard line in most recent accounts of these issues. Is it really true, for example, that women did not appear on the English stage during the period? The answer is no. Not only that, women's work was much more varied than is commonly acknowledged: citing material from social historians, Orgel shows that women were active members of guilds and worked in a wide variety of trades; nor were they as restricted in either their manners or their behavior as standard historicist accounts, inflected by feminist insistences, would have us believe. </p>
					<p n="">Such issues are raised as part of a general argument that ideology and social practice need to be kept distinct, that actual behaviour was multiple, complex and variegated and hence not subject to generalizations about such matters as the position of women <q direct="y">within patriarchy.</q> In some respects, Orgel makes clear, women may have been the <q direct="y">Other,</q> but in many cases <q direct="y">it is not at all clear . . . who are 'us' and who are 'them'.</q> There are <q direct="y">Others of many kinds in this theatre</q> (12). Indeed, the distinction between fathers and children (of either sex) was in many circumstances more important than that between men and women. Gender, in other words, has to be understood in relation to other distributions of power, whether of generation, class, nationality or whatever. As Orgel insists more than once in the book, in such matters context is everything (<q direct="y">everyone in this culture was in some respects a woman, feminized in relation to someone</q> [124]). Even on details this same interrogative approach persists and pays off: we are reminded that, contrary to the claims of most recent critics, Marlowe's Edward is NOT killed by a vicious anal rape, but is crushed to death under a table. Orgel is also, to my knowledge, the first person to ask why Viola takes on the name <q direct="y">Cesario</q> (he provides a provocative answer as well) and his exploration of why Rosalind's boy-name carries an <q direct="y">inescapable allusion</q> to the catamite <q direct="y">for whom Jove himself abandons his marriage bed</q> (57) goes beyond any previous one. </p>
					<p n="">Just because of the careful scrutiny Orgel gives to accepted ideas, it is disappointing when he himself slips into dogmatism. For example, his claim that Antonio and Sebastian in <title level="m">Twelfth Night</title> are an <q direct="y">overtly homosexual couple</q> (51) is oversimplified -- the word <q direct="y">overtly</q> cutting against the careful scepticism on display in most of the book. Since a large part of Orgel's overall point is that male eroticism is free-flowing and metamorphic (i.e. attaches itself to both boys and women), and since the text provides no clear evidence of sexual relations between Sebastian and Antonio, such a statement seems gratuitous. Similarly, a number of blanket claims he makes about marriage in Shakespeare (17-18) need to be qualified. The statement that <q direct="y">marriage is a dangerous condition in Shakespeare</q> is just the kind of remark that he is in other places so good at deconstructing -- and counter-illustrations to a number of his listed examples can easily be adduced. In general, his specific interpretations of Shakespeare are often tendentious, and seem less convincing than the rest of the book. Take, for instance, the claim that the epilogue of <title level="m">As You Like It</title> reveals that <q direct="y">the drama has not represented an erotic and heterosexual reality at all</q> (50). Again, in place of the shifting, elusive eroticism he traces elsewhere in the book, he here makes a dogmatic claim that seems untenable -- if heterosexual feeling has not been <q direct="y">represented</q> in the play, what are we to make of Rosalind's response to the wrestling match, of Silvius's mooning over Phoebe, of Orlando's love sonnets, Touchstone's pragmatic lust, or Oliver and Celia's quiet contentment? This raises a larger question of representation itself (the same issue comes up around his interpretation of the ending of <title level="m">Merchant</title> later on [77]). One of the book's aims is to complicate the relation between representation and reality, but this is subverted by claims that <q direct="y">the play (<title level="m">As You Like It</title>) insists that the wife is really a boy</q> (63). Of course the play doesn't do this at all; it encourages us to acknowledge that the actor playing the part of the wife at the beginning of the epilogue (<q direct="y">It is not the fashion to see the lady the epilogue . . . </q>) is <q direct="y">really</q> a boy after all, and indeed one who withdraws from the possibility of kissing men to make a curtsy (a gesture associated predominantly but not exclusively with women) before all the spectators. Shakespeare keeps the relations more fluid than criticism, even excellent criticism, is prone to do. And he does so by foregrounding the issue on which the theatre is founded -- that of <q direct="y">impersonation.</q>
					</p>
					<p n="">Though the title of Orgel's book focuses on representation, performance and impersonation, he doesn't really examine this issue within the institutional arrangements and constraints of the theatre itself (the way, say, Michael Shapiro's recent book on theatrical cross-dressing does). This leaves something of a gap, since the specific question of how audiences responded to representations, to constructed <q direct="y">persons</q>, is sometimes blurred (as I have suggested elsewhere, the oft-cited passage from Mary Wroth's <title level="m">Urania</title> is an unreliable guide to audience reception of cross-dressed actors). Hence the kinds of confusion about who Rosalind <q direct="y">really</q> is. It seems important to remember that within the fiction created by stage representation, the normative response is a kind of <q direct="y">dual consciousness</q> wherein belief in the fictive reality of the personage sits side by side with a latent awareness of the performer. Orgel's eagerness to undermine the kinds of distinctions made by historical critics can be misleading when it extends to trying to erase the distinction between performer and personage. </p>
					<p n="">But at the same time, his pursuit of the conflicting and interweaving strands of cultural impersonation is so provocative and his development so elusive that one follows along fascinated. There is even a teasing quality to the strategy he adopts. He starts with the question that preoccupied him in an earlier essay, <q direct="y">Nobody's Perfect, or why did the English stage take boys for women?</q> The answers, as he now sees, are multiple and contradictory, a fact which gives him license to follow the strands in essayistic style. The result is a series of seductively deferred promises -- he keeps approaching and then pulling back from a definitive answer. The strategy works even while he tells us at the beginning that he seeks not <q direct="y">to answer a question, but to raise one; to address an exfoliating cultural issue of which we can give many kinds of accounts, but none sufficient to settle the matter.</q> Thinking about gender in Shakespeare's culture, Orgel reminds us, inevitably involves thinking about the same question in our own, and hence formulating questions about early modern constructions involves us in our own conundrums. He illustrates this through a prefaced anecdote in which he deftly places his own theatrical cross-dressing as a student in the 1940s in a context that reveals the shifting nature of gender categories. We are then ready to be led through a round of investigations aimed at uncovering a mass of contradictory but illuminating evidence. </p>
					<p n="">The drift in the first part of the book is towards an understanding of <q direct="y">the anxieties attendant upon the institutionalization of masculinity . . . and to the sanctioned homoeroticism that played so large a role in the relationships between men</q> (30). Later, it is women, and especially the challenge they pose to the categorization to which they were subject, who take centre stage. The overall result is an enriched awareness of the fluidity of gender categories and roles, as illustrated, for example, by the metamorphic slippage in sexual desire from boys to women and back again -- this is <q direct="y">the other side of the [widespread cultural] fear that love effeminates</q> (42). So too the transvestite actor is a polyvalent sign: on the one hand, he is a conductor of cultural anxiety about powerful, desiring women; but he also represents and enables the potential masculinity of women, thereby helping to empower them by showing the value of <q direct="y">acting like a man</q> (106, 153). Indeed, femininity itself becomes associated, in a fruitful paradox, with man-like behaviour. Such major themes are buttressed by a number of exemplary and thoughtful sketches of such matters as contradictions in anatomical theory happily accommodated by unfazed theorists (Thomas Browne for one); the history of the castrati; the legal status of, and cultural tolerance for, pederasty (<q direct="y">the love of men for men in this culture appears less threatening that the love of men for women</q> [49]); the apprentice system within the theatre companies and the society generally (the relations between masters and servants cutting across potentially erotic relations); women voters; the fashion among the highest ladies of the land for masculine attire and the parallel fascination for dressing heroes as women; and finally a triptych of biographical portraits of extraordinary women who knew how to work the system for their advantage (presented to counter the common view among historical critics that women were excluded from the public world). While much of the material here has been gathered from secondary sources, there is no doubt about the brilliant selectiveness of Orgel's scholarship and the inventive uses to which he puts it. It is, in the end, a pleasure not to be offered a single explanation of the enigma of gender; the book's interrogative style, thematic complexity, and engaging deployment of historical material give us a richer picture than any totalized account. </p>
					<p>Responses to this piece intended for the Readers' Forum may be sent to the Editor at <!-- <a href="mailto:emls@ualberta.ca"> -->EMLS@UAlberta.ca<!-- </a> -->. </p>
					<byline>
						<!-- <a href="../emlshome.html" alt="emls home page"> -->
						<!-- <img src="../button.gif" width="124" height="47"> -->
						<!-- </a> -->
						<!-- <a href="../emlscopy.html"> -->&copy;<!-- </a> --> 1997-, R.G. Siemens (Editor, <title level="j">EMLS</title>). (JD, PB, LH, RGS, 11 September 1997) </byline>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls3-2revbud1" n="7" type="review">
					<head>Louis Montrose.<title level="m"> The Purpose of Playing: Shakespeare and the Cultural Politics of the Elizabethan Theatre</title>. Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1996. xiii+227pp. ISBN 0 226 53482 0 Cloth.</head>
					<opener>
						<name>Paul Budra</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>Simon Fraser University</addrLine>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href="mailto:%22budra@sfu.ca%22"> -->budra@sfu.ca<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
						<!-- <img src="../header2.gif" alt="early" width="283" height="87" modern literary studies> -->
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Budra, Paul. <title level="a">Review of <title level="m">The Purpose of Playing: Shakespeare and the Cultural Politics of the Elizabethan Theatre</title>
						</title>. <title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 3.2 (September, 1997): 7.1-5 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/03-2/rev_bud1.html"> --> http://purl.oclc.org/emls/03-2/rev_bud1.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;.</p>
					<p n="1">This book is divided into two parts. In the first, Montrose, who has long been the most eloquent theoretician of New Historicism, considers some of the <q direct="y">socioeconomic, political, and religious forces and institutions that shaped the Elizabethan subject's conditions of existence and the Elizabethan theatre's conditions of production</q> (xi). This is a very broad mandate for a very short book; indeed, it is a formidable mandate for a book that has to go on to a part two: the application of the <q direct="y">themes</q> of part one to Shakespeare's <title level="m">A Midsummer Night's Dream</title> with special attention paid to questions of gender and domestic economy. And, if that were not enough, the book begins with a metacritical prologue on the so-called <q direct="y">culture wars</q> and ends with a short epilogue on the <q direct="y">historical conditions of possibility of Shakespeare's genius</q> (206). </p>
					<p n="2">What emerges most clearly out of this ambitious project is Montrose's distrust of the popular Foucauldian subversion/containment model of power relations. For Montrose this binary opposition is <q direct="y">hopelessly inadequate</q> (11) for cultural analysis, and the book pursues this point by focussing on two central problems: the existence in the Elizabethan period of two theoretically distinct modes of cultural production, one hierarchical and deferential, the other based on market relations; and the complex and shifting relations between playing, Crown, and civic oligarchy. Drawing on plays, anti-theatrical literature, homily, and Elizabethan histories, Montrose mounts a series of arguments around these subjects, all of which end with some recognition of the multivalent layers of ambiguity, filiation, and mediation inherent in the power relations of the specific cultural moment or practice. </p>
					<p n="3">The conclusions that Montrose draws are sensible and a welcome antidote to much recent polemical Renaissance criticism. For example, Montrose goes over the now familiar arguments regarding the late sixteenth-century suppression of guild and religious drama, but he distances himself from those critics who view the pre-consolidation of Protestant authority as a communal Eden, seeing rather the subordination of local to national interests as part of a complex cultural shift, not simply the flexing of hegemonic muscle. On the other hand, the desire to avoid binary polarities of political/cultural category can lead Montrose to qualify until there is not much left to say. So, for example, in his analysis of the Lord Chamberlain's Men's performance of <title level="m">Richard II</title>, staged at the behest of Essex just before the launching of his ill-fated rebellion, Montrose concludes that <q direct="y">the motivations of the players do not seem to have been <emph rend="italics">political</emph> -- if we construe that term narrowly, to mean actively promoting the agenda of a particular faction. The players' motives were, nevertheless, shaped by consideration of a distinctly <emph rend="italics">ideological</emph> character</q> (75). What motives, we might ask, would <emph rend="italics">not</emph> be considered ideological in today's critical climate? Montrose continues to explain that the immediate motives of the players were <q direct="y">social deference and commercial gain.</q> This is news? </p>
					<p n="4">The strongest statements in the first part of the book come when Montrose is addressing fellow critics who offer less qualified visions of the Elizabethan theatre's relation to political culture. And so he has harsh words for Richard Helgerson's interpretation of Shakespeare's representation of absolutist power. More tellingly, Montrose goes on at disproportionate length to attack Paul Yachnin's thesis that Elizabethan-Jacobean theatre was not only irrelevant to issues of political power, but celebrated, or at least acknowledged, that irrelevance. Yachnin's subtle argument is simplified and dismissed by Montrose and for obvious reasons: Montrose is committed to a political/ideological model of playing and culture that, however qualified, cannot admit what Yachnin acutely intimates -- maybe it really <emph rend="italics">was</emph> all fun and games. </p>
					<p n="5">The second part of the book, in which Montrose focusses on <title level="m">A Midsummer Night's Dream</title>, is more satisfying. Pulling in Elizabethan marriage manuals, mythological subtexts, Aristotelian and Galenic models of human reproduction, royal processions, and guild drama, Montrose problematizes an already critically saturated play with new levels of cultural resonance and, yes, wonder. When covering such topics as menstruation, the political import of Bottom's dream, or the economic implications of Puck's epilogue, Montrose is consistently illuminating and inventive, easily accomplishing the more narrow and practical critical project he details in his summary, that of <q direct="y">attempting to locate [the play] more precisely in the ideological matrix of its own production</q> by recognizing the <q direct="y">foregrounding of theatricality as a mode of human cognition and human agency</q> (205).</p>
					<p>Responses to this piece intended for the Readers' Forum may be sent to the Editor at <!-- <a href="mailto:emls@ualberta.ca"> -->EMLS@UAlberta.ca<!-- </a> -->.</p>
					<byline>
						<!-- <a href="../emlshome.html" alt="emls home page"> -->
						<!-- <img src="../button.gif" width="124" height="47"> -->
						<!-- </a> -->
						<!-- <a href="../emlscopy.html"> -->&copy;<!-- </a> --> 1997-, R.G. Siemens (Editor, <title level="j">EMLS</title>). (RGS, JD, PB, LH, 3 September 1997) </byline>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls3-2revgoo4" n="8" type="review">
					<head>Joan Ozark Holmer. <title level="m">The Merchant of Venice: Choice, Hazard and Consequence</title>. New York: St. Martin's P, 1995. xxii+369pp. ISBN 0 312 12411 2 Cloth.</head>
					<opener>
						<name>Bryan N.S. Gooch</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>University of Victoria</addrLine>
						</address>
						<!-- <img src="../header2.gif" alt="early" width="283" height="87" modern literary studies> -->
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Gooch, Bryan N.S. <title level="a">Review of <title level="m">The Merchant of Venice: Choice, Hazard and Consequence</title>.</title>
						<title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 3.2 (September, 1997): 8.1-5 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/03-2/rev_goo4.html"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/03-2/rev_goo4.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;. </p>
					<p n="1">Joan Ozark Holmer in <title level="m">The Merchant of Venice: Choice, Hazard and Consequence</title> offers a number of useful lessons about a play which has suffered overmuch from misinterpretation or misreading as a result of the application of current sensibilities regarding racial issues. Indeed, careless -- or deliberate -- application of a set of values, however virtuous, to an artwork of another period, conceived with a different set of precepts laudable and comprehensible in that day, may be instructive in one way (as we point with pride to our apparently unassailable modern mores), but tends to lead to a series of dangers, not the least of which is the exclusion of the work in question from our list of comfortably acceptable cultural ornaments. Such seems the present fate of Shakespeare's <title level="m">Merchant</title> in some quarters, and Holmer's book is a welcome response to the problem: she argues convincingly that the issues concerning Shylock have to do with religion and character, not race (here she is at one with John Russell Brown, Kenneth Myrick, et al.) and that the play, far from offering a double focus (split between Venice and Belmont, strife and love, materialism and idealism), demonstrates a striking artistic and thematic unity which is supported in terms of characters, action, image, and language (Holmer notes particularly, for instance, the verbal congruity of the trial scene). </p>
					<p n="2">The overall arrangement of the volume appears to be straightforward. Following the front matter are six chapters concentrating on 1) the historical background, 2) <q direct="y">structure and language,</q> 3) <q direct="y">friends and lovers,</q> 4) Antonio and Shylock, 5) the trial, and 6) <q direct="y">union and reunion.</q> Extensive and helpful notes to each chapter are grouped together after the text and are followed by a bibliography and an index. However, the very real coherence of the play produces a potential problem for a critic who attempts to discuss it in detail and who brings to bear such a well-grounded, thoughtful approach as Holmer demonstrates: it is not merely difficult, but demonstrably impossible, to separate the historical issues (e.g., politics, theology and law -- including usury, here seen as involving gain without risk, given a bond of security), thematic concerns, characters, and so on into more or less tight compartments, or to avoid, in a discussion of even more significant scenes, the necessity of throwing out lines of connection to other scenes. The result is that there is more than one discussion of usury, of Shylock (and also his relationship to Antonio), and of the necessity of choosing correctly and risk-taking (<q direct="y">hazard</q>), for instance. The reader may well have, at times, a certain sense of <emph rend="italics">d&eacute;j&agrave; vu</emph>, and even a cursory glance at the index will demonstrate the problem. Ironically, though, the repetition which surfaces as one works through this superbly detailed text goes to support Holmer's contention of the play's unity and offers a nice rebuttal to those who would contend that Shakespeare only came into his own in this respect in the magisterial tragedies of the 1600s. A less considered treatment of, say, background material, and a more superficial discussion of major scenes (not that every one is treated with relatively equal detail here), would also have been fraught with difficulty -- without providing much substance. What supports Holmer's arguments, and sustains a reader's patience, is her level of scholarship (including criticism), her extensive knowledge, for instance, of biblical names, genealogy, and allusions, her explanation of iconographical elements, her sense of the play's theological, social, and political context, and her willingness to run her own organisational risks. This is clearly a book by someone who has not only marshalled a great deal of relevant detail but who has thought about it with care and concern, and particular rewards are to be gained by readers willing to go back, after a first reading, to reconsider individual sections -- to ponder the arguments about the casket or trial scenes, for example -- or to use the index in order to link the discussions of usury. It is a book not to be read and put down but to be worked with -- a companion, in the best sense, to one's own ruminations about the play. It will also be useful to actors and directors as well as scholars of drama and theatre history. To <q direct="y">hiss the mystery lesson,</q> if one might think of Lewis Carroll, is to miss the point. And, to fail to understand how Shakespeare's age would have seen the play and its issues is, ultimately, to lose sight of the work. As Holmer argues, the casket scene with its emphasis on risks, on correct choice, is central to the play and criticism also needs to get beyond appearances. Holmer's work does just that. </p>
					<p n="3">
						<title level="m">Merchant</title> emerges, if this book is given due attention, as a far less troubling and far more exciting dramatic/literary tapestry than some modern approaches might allow. Venice and Belmont are clearly linked, both in terms of theme (parent/child relationships, vows, choices, risks, money, gifts, exchanges, bonds, and friendship) and character (Bassanio, Lorenzo, Jessica, and Gratiano, for instance); Shylock is as present in the mind when he is off-stage as when he is in front of the audience; the struggle between Antonio (who is not perfectly virtuous and not, according to Holmer, anti-Jewish) and Shylock is a central threat (and both characters are punished in the end, with half a fortune and half the argosies). And if the play ends in Belmont (with Lorenzo and Jessica, with stars above and the sound of music, and with the spirited, jesting, forgiving inquisition about the rings-gifts/bonds), the beginning of the end occurs in Venice, with an emphasis on right judgment and redemption. (Requiring Shylock because he broke Venetian law to become a Christian, Holmer asserts, was, for the Elizabethans, to save his soul, not to impose a cruel, apparently racist penalty.) In the end, as so often, Shakespeare argues for balance, and even at the mid-point of his career he was prepared, at the close of a comedy, to present the notion of redemption which he would take up again so markedly in the romances, especially in <title level="m">The Tempest</title> and <title level="m">A Winter's Tale</title>. As Prospero remarks: <q direct="y">Though with their high wrongs I am strook to th' quick, / Yet, with my nobler reason, 'gainst my fury / Do I take part. The rarer action is / In virtue than in vengeance</q>(V.i.25-28). And, to draw attention to dislocation in the play because of all the contrasts which reverberate through its scenes (again, Venice and Belmont, revenge and mercy, hate and love, etc.) is to miss the point as well, for as Geoffrey Tillotson has observed (in discussing Pope's couplets), linkage is inherent in contrast. And when did Shakespeare ever miss an instructive opportunity in that regard, or an opportunity to argue for a perceptiveness which would distinguish between the appearance and the reality, between the outer and the inner (here, in his pursuit of vengeance, Shylock fails), between the flesh and the blood/spirit? Holmer clearly puts Shylock between the Barabas of Marlowe and the Gerontus of Wilson (191) and so further defines the problem of coming to terms with his character: extremes are always easier to describe and to categorize. Clearly, one of the play's features is its emphasis, certainly in terms of the central figures, on humanity, and that is true for Shylock as for the others: he is not without sympathetic attraction. </p>
					<p n="4">If the organisational dilemma which this book confronts and demonstrates is without a neat solution, another difficulty remains -- at least for this reader. That is Holmer's adherence to Q2's inclusion of Salerino with Solanio and Salerio. John Dover Wilson long ago suggested, as John Russell Brown and others also point out, that the name Salerino was the result of scribal or compositorial error and that given textual evidence, Salerino and Salerio are one and the same -- a view rather upheld in recent years. To be blunt, the revivification of Salerino (perhaps a good name for an aberrant member of the flute family of instruments) seems as unusual as it is unhelpful. </p>
					<p n="5">That said, this is still a fine book, written by a thoughtful scholar who appears to enjoy and value the play. As noted, this is a volume for study and reflection, and Holmer's insistence that we will mistake or mishandle <title level="m">Merchant</title> if we do not thoroughly understand its context is one that critics and audiences would do well to remember when coming to terms with other works in the canon as well. </p>
					<p>Responses to this piece intended for the Readers' Forum may be sent to the Editor at <!-- <a href="mailto:emls@ualberta.ca"> -->EMLS@UAlberta.ca<!-- </a> -->.</p>
					<byline>
						<!-- <a href="../emlshome.html" alt="emls home page"> -->
						<!-- <img src="../button.gif" width="124" height="47"> -->
						<!-- </a> -->
						<!-- <a href="../emlscopy.html"> -->&copy;<!-- </a> --> 1997-, R.G. Siemens (Editor, <title level="j">EMLS</title>). (JD, PB, LH, RGS, 15 September 1997) </byline>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls3-2revhin2" n="9" type="review">
					<head>Elizabeth Cary. <title level="m">The Tragedy of Mariam</title>. Ed. Stephanie J. Wright. Staffordshire: Keele UP, 1996. 128pp. ISBN 1 85331 181 1 Cloth; 1 85331 104 9 Paper. </head>
					<opener>
						<name>Carrie Hintz</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>University of Toronto</addrLine>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href="mailto:%22chintz@chass.utoronto.ca%22"> -->chintz@chass.utoronto.ca<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
						<!-- <img src="../header2.gif" alt="early" width="283" height="87" modern literary studies> -->
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Hintz, Carrie. <title level="a">Review of <title level="m">The Tragedy of Mariam</title>.</title>
						<title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 3.2 (September, 1997): 9.1-6 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/03-2/rev_hin2.html"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/03-2/rev_hin2.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;. </p>
					<p n="1">Elizabeth Cary's <title level="m">The Tragedy of Mariam</title> has become one of the early modern period's most studied texts by a woman writer, with good reason. Based on Josephus's <title level="m">Jewish Antiquities</title>, the play explores the troubled relationship of King Herod and his consort Mariam in 35 B.C. At the beginning of the play, Herod is missing and presumed dead. He returns, but not before Mariam discovers that he has decreed she should be killed after his death, as a result of his possessive passion for her. Mariam expresses keen anger, finally confronting Herod himself. Later, Herod is led by his sister Salome to believe that Mariam has been unfaithful, and arranges for her death. To his horror, he learns that he has been deceived, but too late to save the innocent Mariam. The stirring events of this play, with its seething passions and brute political force, show the intersection of tyranny and patriarchy in the early modern period. As Stephanie J. Wright, the editor of this Keele University Press edition, notes, <title level="m">Mariam</title> reflects <q direct="y">the politics of a society in which the married man is not only his wife's husband, but also her lord</q> (17).</p>
					<p n="2">Before the 1990s, it was difficult to find an edition suitable for use in the classroom. Now there are three versions in addition to Wright's in print, two in collections of Renaissance drama by women (Cerasano and Wynne-Davies, 1996 and Purkiss, 1994) and Barry Weller and Margaret W. Ferguson's 1994 scholarly California Press edition. It is finally possible to read this important text in many possible versions, but it has become necessary to ask what yet another edition can add to our understanding of the play. Wright's edition is a solid contribution to the editorial history of the play, although it does not render the previous editions less important. Wright does refine the editorial work of previous editions; she saw two copies of the play Weller and Ferguson did not, and looked at handwritten emendations no other editor had considered. Wright offers fresh notes, and, helpfully, explains points of difference with previous editors. Having several versions of the notes is undeniably helpful for the researcher, and further proof of the play's aesthetic density.  </p>
					<p n="3">In general, the edition is pleasant to read. Wright's notes are credible and thorough, and allow the reader to navigate through the text easily. Biography and history are dealt with well, albeit somewhat briefly, and Wright makes intriguing links back to <title level="m">Mariam</title>'s dramatic precursors, particularly court masques which explored the nature of patriarchal and political authority. Wright deftly gestures to current work on <title level="m">Mariam</title>, offering her own opinions on key critical questions raised by the drama.  </p>
					<p n="4">What could differentiate this edition from any other is that it takes into account the inaugural performance of the drama, that took place on October 19-22, 1994 at the Bradford Alhambra Studio, and that was directed by Wright herself. Given the importance of this performance for the study of early-modern women writers, and for seventeenth-century drama more generally, it is unfortunate that Wright does not give us more information about the rehearsal and staging process; she offers only the vague remark that the theatre company discovered that the play was <q direct="y">peopled by ambiguous and complicated characters</q> (23). Even a photograph of a rehearsal or performance of the play would have been valuable, capturing something of what the play was like when brought to life on the stage.  </p>
					<p n="5">Instead of offering the titbits of stagecraft craved by lovers of this play, Wright spends her energy arguing that Elizabeth Cary wished her play to be staged rather than read as a closet drama. This may be true, but it is probably unprovable. Wright may be confusing our sense that the play works wonderfully on stage (which I am fully prepared to believe) with Cary's expectations. She cites the complexity of the characters and the presence of showy physical action (such as sword fights) as evidence that the play should be staged rather than merely read. Both these arguments are specious; it is possible, as in a novel or dramatic poem, to thrill to the action of a sword fight, whether read out loud or silently. Wright's assertion that <title level="m">Mariam</title> made a <q direct="y">significant contribution to the development of public drama in the early seventeenth century</q> (23) overstates the case, since it was not performed at the time. However, the play is undeniably one of the most accomplished and rivetting Senecan closet dramas of the period, and relates well to other public dramas of the period.  </p>
					<p n="6">This edition is worth having, despite my sense that Wright stresses the wrong elements in her introduction. This play will continue to inspire critical excitement and lively discussion in the classroom. If we have gone from having too few versions to having more than enough to choose from, it is a pleasing testimony to the interest of the work itself, and to the energy of scholars who wish to explore it. </p>
					<listBibl>
						<head>Works Cited</head>
						<bibl>Cerasano, S.P. and Marion Wynne-Davies, eds. <title level="m">Renaissance Drama by Women</title>. London: Routledge, 1996.</bibl>
						<bibl>Purkiss, Diane, ed. <title level="m">Renaissance Women: the plays of Elizabeth Cary: the poems of Aemilia Lanyer</title>. London: Pickering &amp; Chatto, 1994.</bibl>
						<bibl>Weller, Barry and Margaret W. Ferguson, eds. <title level="m">The Tragedy of Mariam with The Lady Falkland: Her Life</title>. Berkeley: U of California P, 1994.</bibl>
					</listBibl>
					<p>Responses to this piece intended for the Readers' Forum may be sent to the Editor at <!-- <a href="mailto:emls@ualberta.ca"> -->EMLS@UAlberta.ca<!-- </a> -->.</p>
					<byline>
						<!-- <a href="../emlshome.html" alt="emls home page"> -->
						<!-- <img src="../button.gif" width="124" height="47"> -->
						<!-- </a> -->
						<!-- <a href="../emlscopy.html"> -->&copy;<!-- </a> --> 1997-, R.G. Siemens (Editor, <title level="j">EMLS</title>). (JD, PB, LH, RGS, 11 September 1997) </byline>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls3-2revlet1" n="10" type="review">
					<head>Charles Ross.<title level="m">The Custom of the Castle: From Malory to Macbeth</title>. Berkeley: U of California P, 1997. xvii+205pp. ISBN 0 520 20430 1 Cloth.</head>
					<opener>
						<name>J.B. Lethbridge</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>University of Tuebingen</addrLine>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href="mailto:lethbridge@uni-tuebingen.de"> -->lethbridge@uni-tuebingen.de<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
						<!-- <img src="../header2.gif" alt="early"
width="283" height="87" modern literary studies> -->
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Lethbridge, J. B. <title level="a">Review of <title level="m">The Custom of the Castle: From Malory to Macbeth</title>.</title>
						<title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 3.2 (September, 1997): 10.1-9 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/03-2/rev_let1.html"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/03-2/rev_let1.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;. </p>
					<p n="1">A <q direct="y">custom of the castle</q> is <q direct="y">the moment when a knight comes upon a castle and confronts a ritual or tradition or institutional control presided over by some villain</q> (11); this topos <q direct="y">may be read as a meditation on the weight of custom or local practice in resolving problems of moral knowledge</q> (11). A custom is justified by an account of its origins; in this narrative structure, <q direct="y">clashing standards of behaviour open a gap between moral knowledge and moral action</q> (84), an epistemological dilemma which requires a narrative solution (14). Ross traces the custom of the castle topos from Chr&eacute;tien to Spenser and Shakespeare with reference to changing conceptions of the law in France, Italy and England. </p>
					<p n="2">In the French model, represented by Malory, customs <q direct="y">function as a form of natural law</q> (7); but such an identification is unstable because while customs change over time, natural law remains the same for ever (10). Thus Malory's Tristram needs to <q direct="y">fordo</q> the foul custom of the Weeping Castle (16), where <q direct="y">fordo</q> suggests both maintaining and overcoming the custom (16). </p>
					<p n="3">The Italians, represented by Boiardo and Ariosto, try, on the other hand, to outwit the social system when something is wrong with it (16). Boiardo treats the custom of the castle as an allegory of the Other. The question for Ross is whether Ranaldo's violence in overcoming the custom is justified (40). <q direct="y">The issue then becomes what history meant to Boiardo</q> (55), and the answer is that Boiardo <q direct="y">uses the past . . . to give value to the moral imagination</q> (55). Ariosto's Bradamante outwits the custom of the Tower of Tristam, which insists that only the most beautiful woman may shelter there, by successfully arguing that since she herself gained entrance as a warrior and not as a woman, then Ullania should be allowed to stay despite having lost the beauty contest against Bradamante. </p>
					<p n="4">Spenser, conscious that competing customs do not present criteria for choosing among them, and that any specific advice on how to be courteous will be defeated by competing customs, defines courtesy as <q direct="y">some sort of universal ideal</q> which resides in the mind (85), rather than as a specific set of instructions. <title level="m">Hamlet</title> also <q direct="y">questions whether civility can ever be defined in a particular way</q> (116). The customs of the castle operate in <title level="m">Hamlet</title> through the fear of offending one's ancestors, most obviously the ghost of Hamlet's father. In <title level="m">Macbeth</title>, furthermore, <q direct="y">doubt and uncertainty attend the realization that customs may be created, that people alter the institutions they pass to the future.</q> The castles of Macbeth <q direct="y">illustrate the distant future orientation of English customary law . . . Macbeth offers an oxymoronic vision of the future as the times of good custom</q> (116). This view of Macbeth depends upon seeing the end of the play as a moment when <q direct="y">banished good returns, evil is purged, savage customs are tamed. Macbeth's foul ways and his castles yield to the new dominion promised by Malcolm: domestic order, civility, proper burial, true succession</q> (128). </p>
					<p n="5">These are excellent classifications, but some of Ross's readings are problematic. I shall provide two examples. </p>
					<p n="6">An important step of the argument in the chapter on Malory is the suggestion that Tristram upholds the custom of the Weeping Castle until Galahalt arrives to provide a <q direct="y">unique means to eliminate the local custom</q> (30). But does Malory's text lead to this conclusion? In slaying Breunor and his wife under the terms of the foul custom, Tristram is upholding, not that custom but another custom of knight errantry, that of freeing a society from the foul custom of its lord. Galahalt does not, therefore, release Tristram as Ross asserts (31). Galahalt must (following another custom) avenge his father's death, which is why he arrives at the Weeping Castle, even though he firmly disapproves of his father's foul custom there. He tricks Tristram into surrendering, and once this trick is accomplished then another chivalric custom comes into play -- the custom in which the yielded life is treated as sacred -- and Tristram is granted mercy. Galahalt commands Tristram to find Lancelot, and Tristram is bound by the chivalric code to carry out that command; it is difficult to see that if Tristram does not do this Galahalt will enforce the old foul custom. The text's treatment of custom is more complex than Ross acknowledges. </p>
					<p n="7">Ross mistreats the text, apparently because he finds it a <q direct="y">shock</q> and <q direct="y">no small surprise</q> (27) that Tristram cuts off Sir Breunor's head after defeating him (27). There is, however, no suggestion in the text that the narrator or the other actors are shocked or surprised. To Ross <q direct="y">it would seem that a chivalrous knight's task would be to defeat Sir Breunor and reform his castle, while sparing him and his lady. Sir Tristram should eliminate the custom of judicial murder that obtains at the Weeping Castle, not necessarily kill the keepers of it.</q> (27) It is not clear that the standards implied by <q direct="y">it would seem</q> and <q direct="y">should</q> are those of Malory's text. Similarly, the reading of Boiardo relies on the question whether Ranaldo's violence is justified (40); yet it is not clear that either the question or the criteria by which it is answered arise from the text. </p>
					<p n="8">Secondly, to make the point that customs challenge each other and have no justification outside themselves, Ross must suggest that all customs are seen to be equally valid. He attributes this idea to Spenser, arguing that Spenser's anxiety in the face of competing customs controls his presentation of courtesy. The scene between Calidore and Briana in the first canto of Book VI of <title level="m">The Faerie Queene</title>, <q direct="y">gives prominence not just to the difficulty but to the uneasiness that accompanies the establishment of civility</q> (87). Spenser does at times register such unease. To establish the point in this instance, however, Ross exaggerates Calidore's action when he enters Briana's castle. He writes that when Briana challenges him, Calidore <q direct="y">is putting the castle to the sword</q> (86). Spenser writes that the castle inhabitants <q direct="y">About him flockt, and hard at him did lay; / But he them all from him full lightly swept, / As doth a Steare, in heat of sommers day, / With his long taile the bryzes brush away</q> (6.1.24), which is not the same thing as <q direct="y">putting the castle to the sword.</q> Ross states that <q direct="y">chagrin takes hold of Calidore</q> (87). Calidore is <q direct="y">abashed</q> (6.1.26, quoted at p. 87) at Briana's accusation that he is unknightly, but if <q direct="y">chagrin</q> is to mean <q direct="y">ashamed</q> or <q direct="y">regretful</q> of what he has done, it seems far from Calidore's confident assertion in the same stanza that Briana and the foul custom are at fault and not himself. Calidore unabashedly asserts the wrongfulness of Briana's foul custom and implies, as Ross says, <q direct="y">that good customs, which characterize civility, preexist the evil efforts of Briana and her people to negate them</q> (87). But if one qualifies these readings at all, there is little of the <q direct="y">nervous anxiety</q> which Ross finds raised by the <q direct="y">question of customary behaviour</q> (87). Spenser presents the custom as foul. </p>
					<p n="9">Yet, despite these concerns, the book broaches an excellent subject and raises important ideas both generally and in the reading of individual episodes. <title level="m">The Custom of the Castle</title> is good starting point for more detailed work.</p>
					<p>Responses to this piece intended for the Readers' Forum may be sent to the Editor at <!-- <a href="mailto:emls@ualberta.ca"> -->EMLS@UAlberta.ca<!-- </a> -->.</p>
					<byline>
						<!-- <a href="../emlshome.html" alt="emls home page"> -->
						<!-- <img src="../button.gif" width="124" height="47"> -->
						<!-- </a> -->
						<!-- <a href="../emlscopy.html"> -->&copy;<!-- </a> --> 1997-, R.G. Siemens (Editor, <title level="j">EMLS</title>). (PB, LH, RGS, 15 September 1997)</byline>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls3-2revbook" type="reviewinfo">
					<head>
						<!-- <img src="../header2.gif" alt="early" modern literary studies height=87 width=283> -->Reviewing Information, Books Received for Review, and Forthcoming Reviews</head>
					<div3>
						<p rend="centre"> - <ref target="emls3-2revbookinformation">Reviewing Information</ref> | <ref target="emls3-2revbookreceived">Books Received for Review</ref> | <ref target="emls3-2revbookforthcoming">Forthcoming Reviews</ref> -</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 id="emls3-2revbookinformation">
						<div4>
							<head>Reviewing Information</head>
							<p>
								<title level="m">EMLS</title> invites reviews of recent scholarly works -- critical editions, commentaries, and theoretical, historical, literary, or interdisciplinary criticism which centres on sixteenth- or seventeenth-century English or related literary culture. We also encourage reports of all resources which are relevant to literary studies of the period, including those available exclusively in the electronic medium.</p>
							<p>Our aim is to publish reviews of a consistently high standard, which are both engaging and critically fair, written by a broad range of people at different stages of their academic careers with varied disciplinary backgrounds.</p>
						</div4>
						<div4>
							<head>Requests to Review</head>
							<p>Requests to review books listed below, or proposals for reviews of other new titles, together with a brief description of reviewers' academic qualifications, publications or research interests should be sent to Lisa Hopkins, the Associate Editor (Reviews), at <!-- <a href="mailto:l.m.hopkins@shu.ac.uk"> -->L.M.Hopkins@shu.ac.uk<!-- </a> --> or by regular mail to the School of Cultural Studies, Sheffield Hallam University, Collegiate Crescent Campus, Sheffield, UK, S10 2BP.</p>
						</div4>
						<div4>
							<head>Submission of Materials for Review</head>
							<p>Materials for review may be sent to Lisa Hopkins, the Associate Editor (Reviews), at the above address. Please note that all unsolicited materials sent to <title level="m">EMLS</title> for the purposes of review must be plainly marked with the word &quot;Donation&quot; on the front of the mailing cover.</p>
						</div4>
					</div3>
					<div3 id="emls3-2revbookreceived">
						<head>Books Received for Review as of September 1997:</head>
						<p>
							<list>
								<item>Albanese, Denise. <title level="m">New Science, New World</title>. Durham: Duke UP, 1996.</item>
								<item>Bath, Michael. <title level="m">Speaking Pictures: Emblem Books and Renaissance Culture</title>. London: Longman, 1993.</item>
								<item>Benedict, Barbara M. <title level="m">Making the Modern Reader: Cultural Mediation in Early Modern Literary Anthologies</title>. Princeton: Princeton UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Biester, James. <title level="m">Lyric Wonder: Rhetoric and Wit in Renaissance English Poetry</title>. Ithaca: Cornell UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Bishop, T.G. <title level="m">Shakespeare and the Theatre of Wonder</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1996.</item>
								<item>Blank, Paula. <title level="m">Broken English: Dialects and the Politics of Language in Renaissance Writings</title>. New York: Routledge, 1996.</item>
								<item>Breight, Curtis C. <title level="m">Surveillance, Militarism and Drama in the Elizabethan Era</title>. New York: St Martin's P, 1995.</item>
								<item>Bulman, James. <title level="m">Shakespeare, Theory and Performance</title>. London: Routledge, 1995.</item>
								<item>Cable, Lana. <title level="m">Carnal Rhetoric: Milton's Iconoclasm and the Poetics of Desire</title>. Durham: Duke UP, 1995.</item>
								<item>Cereta, Laura. <title level="m">Collected Letters of a Renaissance Feminist</title>. Ed. Diana Robin. Trans. Diana Robin. Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1997.</item>
								<item>Comensoli, Viviana. <title level="m">Household Business: Domestic Plays of Early Modern England</title>. Toronto: U of Toronto P, 1996.</item>
								<item>Cox, John D., and David Scott Kastan, eds. <title level="m">A New History of Early English Drama</title>. New York: Columbia UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Cressy, David. <title level="m">Birth, Marriage and Death: Ritual, Religion, and the Life-Cycle in Tudor and Stuart England</title>. Oxford: Oxford UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>De Grazia, Margeta, Maureen Quilligan, and Peter Stallybrass, eds. <title level="m">Subject and Object in Renaissance Culture</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1996.</item>
								<item>Diehl, Huston. <title level="m">Staging Reform, Reforming the Stage</title>. Ithaca: Cornell UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Doerksen, Daniel W. <title level="m">Conforming to the Word: Herbert, Donne and the English Church before Laud</title>. Cranbury, NJ: Bucknell UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Edwards, Philip. <title level="m">Sea-Mark: The Metaphorical Voyage from Spenser to Milton</title>. Liverpool: Liverpool UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Erickson, Wayne. <title level="m">Mapping </title>The Faerie Queene<title level="m">: Quest Structures and the World of the Poem</title>. New York: Garland, 1996.</item>
								<item>Fanshawe, Richard. <title level="m">The Poems and Translations of Sir Richard Fanshawe</title>. Vol. 1. Ed. Peter Davidson. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1997.</item>
								<item>Fonte, Moderata (Modesta Pozzo). <title level="m">The Worth of Women</title>. Ed. Virginia Cox. Trans. Virginia Cox. Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1997.</item>
								<item>Garin, Eugenio, ed. <title level="m">Renaissance Characters</title>. Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1997.</item>
								<item>Halpern, Richard. <title level="m">Shakespeare Among the Moderns</title>. Ithaca: Cornell UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Harvey, P.D.A. <title level="m">Mappa Mundi: The Hereford World Map</title>. Toronto: U of Toronto P, 1996.</item>
								<item>James, Tracy. <title level="m">Erasmus of the Low Countries</title>. Berkely: U of California P, 1996. </item>
								<item>Jardine, Lisa. <title level="m">Reading Shakespeare Historically</title>. New York: Routledge, 1996. </item>
								<item>Jehlan, Myra and Michael Warner, eds. <title level="m">The English Literatures of America</title>. New York: Routledge, 1996. </item>
								<item>Keyishian, Harry. <title level="m">The Shape of Revenge: Victimization, and Vengeance, and Vindictiveness in Shakespeare</title>. Atlantic Highlands, NJ: Humanities P, 1995. </item>
								<item>Maquerlot, Jean-Pierre. <title level="m">Shakespeare and the Mannerist Tradition: A Reading of Five Problem Plays</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1995. </item>
								<item>Meagher, John C. <title level="m">Shakespeare's Shakespeare: How the Plays were Made</title>. New York: Continuum Books, 1997. </item>
								<item>Owens, W.R. and Lizbeth Goodman, eds. <title level="m">Shakespeare, Aphra Bhen and the Canon</title>. New York: Routledge, 1996. </item>
								<item>Parker, Douglas, ed. <title level="m">A Proper Dyaloge betwene a Gentillman and an Husbandman</title>. Toronto: U of Toronto P, 1996. </item>
								<item>Pask, Kevin. <title level="m">The Emergence of the English Author: Scripting the Life of the Poet in Early Modern England</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1996. </item>
								<item>Platt, Peter G. <title level="m">Reason Diminished: Shakespeare and the Marvelous</title>. Lincoln: U of Nebraska P, 1997. </item>
								<item>Purkiss, Diane. <title level="m">The Witch in History</title>. New York: Routledge, 1996. </item>
								<item>Raymond, Joad. <title level="m">The Invention of the Newspaper: English Newsbooks 1641-1649</title>. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1996. </item>
								<item>Shuger, Debora Kuller. <title level="m">Habits of Thought in the English Renaissance</title>. Toronto: U of Toronto P, 1997. </item>
								<item>Stewart, Alan. <title level="m">Close Readers: Humanism and Sodomy in Early Modern England</title>. Princeton: Princeton UP, 1997. </item>
								<item>Traub, Valerie, M. Lindsay Kaplan, and Dympna Callaghan, eds. <title level="m">Feminist Readings of Early Modern Culture: Emerging Subjects</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1996. </item>
								<item>Wilcox, Helen, ed. <title level="m">Women and Literature in Britian: 1500-1700</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1996. </item>
								<item>Yachnin, Paul. <title level="m">Stage-Wrights: Shakespeare, Jonson, Middleton, and the Making of Theatrical Value</title>. Philadelphia: U of Pennsylvania P, 1997.</item>
							</list>
						</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 id="emls3-2revbookforthcoming">
						<head>Forthcoming Reviews:</head>
						<p>
							<list>
								<item>Alexander, Robert J., ed. <title level="m">Somerset</title>. Records of Early English Drama. Toronto: U of Toronto P, 1996.</item>
								<item>Burns, Edward, ed. <title level="m">Reading Rochester</title>. Liverpool: Liverpool UP, 1996.</item>
								<item>Donne, John. <title level="m">Variorum Edition of the Poetry of John Donne</title>. Vol 8. Bloomington: Indiana UP, 1995.</item>
								<item>Erickson, Wayne. <title level="m">Mapping the Fairie Queene: Quest Structures and the World of the Poem</title>. New York: Garland, 1996.</item>
								<item>Farago, Claire, ed. <title level="m">Reframing the Renaissance: Visual Culture in Europe and Latin America. 1450-1650</title>. Yale: Yale UP, 1996.</item>
								<item>Green, Ian. <title level="m">The Christian's ABC</title>. Oxford: Oxford UP 1996.</item>
								<item>Gregerson, Linda. <title level="m">The Reformation of the Subject: Spenser, Milton, and the English Protestant Epic</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1995.</item>
								<item>Grell, Ole Peter and Andrew Cunningham, eds. <title level="m">Religio Medici: Medicine and Religion in Seventeenth-Century England</title>. Brookfield, VT: Scolar, 1996.</item>
								<item>Hamilton, Donna B. and Richard Strier, eds. <title level="m">Religion, Literature and Politics in Post Reformation England</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1996.</item>
								<item>Joughin, John, ed. <title level="m">Shakespeare and National Culture</title>. Manchester: Manchester UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Maquerlot, Jean-Pierre and Michelle Willems, eds. <title level="m">Travel &amp; Drama in Shakespeare's Time</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1995.</item>
								<item>Marotti, Arthur. <title level="m">Manuscript, Print and the English Renaissance Lyric</title>. Ithaca: Cornell UP, 1995.</item>
								<item>McEachern, Claire. <title level="m">The Poetics of English Nationhood: 1590-1612</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1996.</item>
								<item>McRae, Andrew. <title level="m">God Speed the Plough: The Representation of Agrarian England 1500-1660</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP 1996.</item>
								<item>Peacock, John. <title level="m">Stage Designs of Inigo Jones</title>. Cambridge: Cambridge UP 1996.</item>
								<item>Pugliatti, Paula. <title level="m">Shakespeare the Historian</title>. New York: St. Martin's P,1995.</item>
								<item>Thompson, Ann and Sasha Roberts, eds. <title level="m">Women Reading Shakespeare, 1600-1900: An Anthology of Criticism</title>. Manchester: Manchester UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Todd, Margo, ed. <title level="m">Reformation to Revolution: Politics and Religion in Early Modern England</title>. London: Routledge, 1994.</item>
								<item>Woudhuysen, Henry. <title level="m">Sir Philip Sidney and the Circulation of Manuscripts 1558-1640</title>. Oxford: Oxford UP, 1996.</item>
							</list>
						</p>
						<p>
							<!-- <a href="../emlshome.html" alt="emls home page"> -->
							<!-- <img src="../button.gif" height=47 width=124> -->
							<!-- </a> -->
							<!-- <a href="../emlscopy.html"> -->&copy;<!-- </a> --> 1997-, R.G. Siemens (Editor, <title level="j">EMLS</title>). (PB, LH, RGS, 17 September 1997)</p>
					</div3>
				</div2>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="issuesection">
				<head>Readers' Forum</head>
				<div2 type="forum">
					<p>Responses to articles, reviews, and notes appearing in this issue that are intended for the Readers' Forum may be sent to the Editor at EMLS@UAlberta.ca.</p>
				</div2>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
