<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 SYSTEM "teixlite.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xsl/teihtml.xsl"?>
<TEI.2>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Early Modern Literary Studies</title>
				<editor>Ray Siemens</editor>
				<funder>Conversion from HTML to TEI.2 conformant markup funded by the Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council of Canada, Aid to Research and Transfer Journals Program, Special Initiatives Grant # 647-98-0040.</funder>
				<sponsor>Sheffield Hallam University and the University of Toronto Electronic Publishing Centre</sponsor>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Conversion from HTML to TEI.2 conformant markup:</resp>
					<name>Kathryn Harvey</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<extent>approx. 275k</extent>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>University of Toronto Electronic Publishing Centre and Sheffield Hallam University</publisher>
				<availability status="restricted">
					<p>Copyright 2000.</p>
				</availability>
				<pubPlace>Sheffield, UK, and Toronto, Canada</pubPlace>
				<idno>ISSN 1201-2459</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl>
					<title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title>, Volume 4, Issue 1 (May 1998)</bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<projectDesc>
				<p>Early Modern Literary Studies (ISSN 1201-2459) is a refereed journal serving as a formal arena for scholarly discussion and as an academic resource for researchers in the area. Articles in EMLS examine English literature, literary culture, and language during the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries; responses to published papers are also published as part of a Readers' Forum. Reviews evaluate recent work as well as academic tools of interest to scholars in the field. EMLS is committed to gathering and to maintaining links to the most useful and comprehensive internet resources for Renaissance scholars, including archives, electronic texts, discussion groups, and beyond.</p>
			</projectDesc>
			<samplingDecl>
				<p>The entire contents of EMLS issues have been converted from HTML with the exception of the Table of Contents page.</p>
			</samplingDecl>
			<editorialDecl>
				<p>Quotations: All quotation marks have been converted to "q," "title," or other tags and have not been retained as data.  Some attempt has been made to provide finer distinctions among quoted and mentioned passages.</p>
				<p>Corrections: The conversion from HTML has been manually performed and every attempt has been made not to introduce errors into the text.</p>
			</editorialDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<p>The id attributes contain canonical references in the following form: JournalAbbrevVol-IssueAuthorTitleAbbrevExtension, where the journal abbreviation is "EMLS," followed by the volume and issue number.  The author and title abbreviations take the form of the first four letters of the author's last name and first three or four letters of a word identifying the content of the article (usually taken from a word in the title, or in the case of a review "rev" is often used).  The extension refers to the type of reference.  For example, the id for the first annotation of the article "King Lear in its Own Time: The Difference that Death Makes" by Ben Ross Schneider Jr. would be "EMLS1-1schnlearn1," where the "n1" indicates note 1.</p>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>26 February 2000</date>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>SGML edited by</resp>
					<name>Kathryn Harvey</name>
				</respStmt>
				<item>began conversion</item>
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>27 February 2000</date>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>SGML edited by</resp>
					<name>Kathryn Harvey</name>
				</respStmt>
				<item>conversion continued </item>
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>4 March 2000</date>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>SGML edited by</resp>
					<name>Kathryn Harvey</name>
				</respStmt>
				<item>conversion continued </item>
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>25 June 2000</date>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>SGML edited by</resp>
					<name>Kathryn Harvey</name>
				</respStmt>
				<item>tag clean-up</item>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div1 type="issuesection">
				<head>
					<title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 4.1 (May, 1998)</head>
				<head>Articles</head>
				<div2 id="emls4-104-1abs" type="articleabstracts">
					<!-- <img src="../header2.gif" alt="early" modern literary studies width="283" height="87"> -->
					<head>Article Abstracts / R&eacute;sum&eacute;s des Articles</head>
					<p rend="centre">(Translations from English courtesy of Luc Borot, Centre d'Etudes et de Recherches sur la Renaissance Anglaise, Universit&eacute; Paul-Valery, Montpellier, France.)</p>
					<div3 type="text">
						<p>
							<ref target="emls4-1evanjons">Jonson's Stoic Politics: Lipsius, the Greeks, and the <q direct="y">Speach According to Horace.</q>
							</ref> Robert C. Evans, Auburn University Montgomery.</p>
						<p>[<ref target="emls4-104-1absevanjons-e">English</ref> | <ref target="emls4-104-1absevanjons-f">French</ref>]</p>
						<p>
							<ref target="emls4-1heanshak">Petruchio's Horse: Equine and Household Management in <title level="m">The Taming of the Shrew</title>
							</ref>.Peter F. Heaney, Staffordshire University.</p>
						<p>[<ref target="emls4-104-1absheanshak-e">English</ref> | <ref target="emls4-104-1absheanshak-f">French</ref>]</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<div4 id="emls4-104-1absevanjons-e" type="text">
							<head>
								<ref target="emls4-1evanjons">Jonson's Stoic Politics: Lipsius, the Greeks, and the <q direct="y">Speach According to Horace.</q>
								</ref> Robert C. Evans, Auburn University Montgomery.</head>
							<p>Markings made by Ben Jonson in his personal copy of Justus Lipsius' Latin <title level="m">Politica</title> (i.e., <title level="m">Politics</title>), published in 1623, suggest that both men equated good politics with moral goodness. Jonson seems to have been one of many readers who prized Lipsius for showing how the insights of the ancient Greeks and Romans could be harmonized not only with Christian ethics but also with a practical concern for real political conduct. This article particularly reports Lipsius' quotations (and Jonson's markings) of passages from Greek authors. Jonson's reading of Lipsius was also a way of re-reading the ancient Greeks, and to speak of the <q direct="y">Lipsian</q> influence on Jonson's politics during the reign of Charles I is to speak, indirectly, of a Greek influence as well. Various allusions in Jonson's works show how Jonson used Lipsius to access the Greeks, while the long poem entitled <q direct="y">A Speach According to Horace</q> illustrates the parallels between the political ideas and ideals of Lipsius and Jonson.</p>
						</div4>
						<div4 id="emls4-104-1absevanjons-f">
							<head>
								<ref target="emls4-1evanjons">La politique sto&iuml;cienne de Ben Jonson: Juste Lipse, les Grecs et le <q direct="y">Discours d'apr&egrave;s Horace</q>.</ref> Robert C. Evans, Auburn University Montgomery.</head>
							<p>Les annotations de Ben Jonson sur son exemplaire personnel de la <title level="m">Politica</title> latine de Juste Lipse publi&eacute;e en 1623, sugg&egrave;rent que les deux hommes &eacute;tablissaient une &eacute;quivalence entre la bonne politique et la bont&eacute; morale. Jonson semble avoir fait partie des nombreux lecteurs qui estimaient Juste Lipse pour avoir montr&eacute; &agrave; quel point les intuitions des anciens Grecs et Romains pouvaient &ecirc;tre mis en harmonie non seulement avec la morale chr&eacute;tienne, mais aussi avec un souci pratique pour la conduite politique r&eacute;elle. Cet article &eacute;tudie particuli&egrave;rement les citations de passages tir&eacute;s des auteurs grecs par Juste Lipse (et les annotations de Jonson). Pour Jonson, lire Juste Lipse &eacute;tait une autre fa&ccedil;on de re-lire les Grecs, et parler de l'influence de Juste Lipse sur les id&eacute;es politiques de Jonson sous le r&egrave;gne de Charles Ier revient tout autant &agrave; parler indirectement d'une influence grecque. Dans les oeuvres de Jonson, diverses allusions montrent comment il a utilis&eacute; Juste Lipse pour avoir acc&egrave;s aux auteurs grecs, alors que le long po&egrave;me intitul&eacute; <q direct="y">Discours d'apr&egrave;s Horace</q> illustre les parall&egrave;lismes entre les id&eacute;es politiques et les id&eacute;aux de Juste Lipse et de Jonson. </p>
						</div4>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<div4 id="emls4-104-1absheanshak-e">
							<head>
								<ref target="emls4-1heanshak">Petruchio's Horse: Equine and Household Management in <title level="m">The Taming of the Shrew</title>.</ref> Peter F. Heaney, Staffordshire University.</head>
							<p>Few of the hundreds of horses mentioned in Shakespeare's plays are given any significance but, where horses are singled out and given prominence, the reader should take notice. A notable example is Petruchio's horse, in <title level="m">The Taming of the Shrew</title>, which is riddled with diseases, all of them described in lavish detail, and most of them causing swelling of the mouth or the head. This essay begins with the suggestion that the unfortunate horse should be seen as a sign, a symptom (if not a metaphor), for the condition of its master, Petruchio, who exhibits what could be described as disorders of the mouth and the ego. Petruchio's behaviour, even before his self-declared suit for the hand of Katherine, is egocentric and violent; more significantly, the horse also depicts Petruchio's <q direct="y">policy</q> of misrule, disorder and mismanagement. The essay also points to the growing interest, in sixteenth-century England, in the writings on domestic conduct and household management of the Greek philosopher, Xenophon, and more recent Renaissance humanists. Petruchio's treatment of his horse, and subsequent <q direct="y">taming,</q> of Katherine, the supposed shrew, are shown to be a means by which Shakespeare's text problematises patriarchal authority. <title level="m">The Shrew</title>, it is argued, is an example of a text which offers resistance to the dominant discourse.</p>
						</div4>
						<div4 id="emls4-104-1absheanshak-f">
							<head>
								<ref target="emls4-1heanshak">Le cheval de P&eacute;truchio: gestion &eacute;questre et domestique dans <title level="m">La m&eacute;g&egrave;re apprivois&eacute;e.</title>
								</ref> Peter F. Heaney, Staffordshire University.</head>
							<p>Des centaines de chevaux mentionn&eacute;s dans les pi&egrave;ces de Shakespeare, peu nombreux sont ceux qui re&ccedil;oivent une quelconque importance, mais lorsque les chevaux sont mis en avant et re&ccedil;oivent une certaine &eacute;minence, le lecteur se doit de le remarquer. Un exemple notable est le cheval de P&eacute;truchio dans <title level="m">La m&eacute;g&egrave;re apprivois&eacute;e</title>. Il est en effet perclus de maladies qui sont toutes d&eacute;crites avec un luxe de d&eacute;tails, or la plupart provoquent une enflure de la bouche ou de la t&ecirc;te. Le pr&eacute;sent essai commence par sugg&eacute;rer que le malheureux cheval doit &ecirc;tre per&ccedil;u comme un signe, un sympt&ocirc;me (sinon une m&eacute;taphore), de la condition de son ma&icirc;tre, P&eacute;truchio, qui manifeste ce qu'on pourrait d&eacute;crire comme des troubles de la bouche et de l'&eacute;go. Le comportement de P&eacute;truchio, m&ecirc;me avant qu'il ne se d&eacute;clare en qu&ecirc;te de la main de Catherine, est &eacute;gocentrique et violent; de fa&ccedil;on plus significative, le cheval d&eacute;crit &eacute;galement la <q direct="y">politique</q> de mauvais gouvernement de soi, de d&eacute;sordre et de mauvaise gestion mat&eacute;rielle qui est celle de P&eacute;truchio. Le pr&eacute;sent essai met aussi l'accent sur l'int&eacute;r&ecirc;t manifest&eacute; dans l'Angleterre du XVIe si&egrave;cle pour les &eacute;crits sur la conduite et l'&eacute;conomie domestiques du philosophe grec X&eacute;nophon, et d'humanistes de la Renaissance plus r&eacute;cents. On montre comment le traitement du cheval par P&eacute;truchio, et le <q direct="y">domptage</q> subs&eacute;quent de Catherine, la m&eacute;g&egrave;re suppos&eacute;e, sont un moyen, pour le texte de Shakespeare, de probl&eacute;matiser l'autorit&eacute; patriarcale. On soutiendra que <title level="m">La m&eacute;g&egrave;re apprivois&eacute;e</title> est un exemple de texte r&eacute;sistant au discours dominant.</p>
							<p>
								<!-- <a href="../emlshome.html"> -->
								<!-- <img src="../button.gif" width="124" height="47"> -->
								<!-- </a> -->
								<!-- <a href="../emlscopy.html"> -->&copy;<!-- </a> --> 1998-, R.G. Siemens (Editor, <title level="j">EMLS</title>).</p>
						</div4>
					</div3>
					<byline>(LB, RGS, 15 June 1998)</byline>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls4-1evanjons" n="1" type="article">
					<!-- <img src="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/header2.gif" alt="early" modern literary studies width="283" height="87"> -->
					<head>Jonson's Stoic Politics: Lipsius, the Greeks, and the <q direct="y">Speach According to Horace</q>
					</head>
					<opener>
						<name>Robert C. Evans</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>Auburn University Montgomery</addrLine>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href="mailto:bobevans@strudel.aum.edu"> -->bobevans@strudel.aum.edu<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Evans, Robert C. <title level="a">Jonson's Stoic Politics: Lipsius, the Greeks, and the 'Speach According to Horace'</title>. <title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 4.1 (May, 1998): 1.1-44 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/evanjons.html"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/evanjons.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;.</p>
					<div3 type="text">
						<head>I.</head>
						<p n="1">The question of Ben Jonson's politics, always important, assumes an added significance during the Caroline period. Since we know (as Jonson did not) the disastrous outcome of Charles' reign, and since that reign, in retrospect, seems infinitely fascinating and controversial, the political attitudes of the most significant Caroline man of letters assume added interest. This is especially true because evaluations of Jonson's later works (particularly the poetry, masques, and entertainments) so often reflect reactions to his presumed political stance. It seems easy to read the late works, especially those written for the king, court, or courtiers, as puff-pieces or whiffs of flattery, all the more embarrassing in light of later events. The Caroline period is often treated as a sorry final chapter in the life and art of a great man and writer. It is often seen as a time when his works declined into <q direct="y">dotages</q> and when his politics, like his body, lapsed from an earlier sturdiness. Jonson the Caroline writer can sometimes be read as an apologist for a reign that needed apologies but did not deserve them.<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn1">1</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="2">It thus seems all the more important to try to determine the political principles that may have motivated Jonson the Caroline poet. What ideals, exactly, may have influenced his political ideas and their poetic expression? What standards may have dictated his political pronouncements? What larger goals and deeper beliefs may have inspired him to write? </p>
						<p n="3">Answers are suggested by the numerous markings Jonson made in his personal copy of the <title level="m">Politicorum, sive Civilis Doctrinae Libri Sex</title> (<title level="m">Six Books of Politics or Civil Doctrine</title>) by the Flemish neostoic intellectual, Justus Lipsius. Lipsius' importance for Jonson has recently been discussed at length, but his importance for Jonson the Caroline writer seems all the greater when we recall that the poet could not have read or marked his copy of the <title level="m">Politics</title> earlier than 1623 (its date of publication, not long before Charles' accession in 1625). Lipsius' importance is also enhanced when we remember that Jonson cited the <title level="m">Politics</title> and alluded to it throughout Charles' reign. Although Jonson marked only the first two and part of the fourth books of the <title level="m">Politics</title>, his vigorous markings testify that he read at least those portions of the work with exceptional attention.<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn2">2</ref> The sheer energy with which he so profusely marked so much of Lipsius' treatise demonstrates his keen interest, and his quotations or allusions suggest his general sympathy with Lipsius' thinking. Of course, to speak of <q direct="y">Lipsius' thinking</q> in the <title level="m">Politics</title> is somewhat misleading, since the book is primarily a huge digest of quotations from the Greek and Roman classics. These are assembled, however, to support Lipsius' assertions on basic issues of politics, religion, governance, warfare, and especially ethics. Ethics, indeed, is the key to understanding not only the <title level="m">Politics</title> of Lipsius but also the politics of Jonson. Both men seem to have equated good politics with moral goodness: the just ruler, the worthy citizen, and the ideal commonwealth should all be rooted in virtue. </p>
						<p n="4">Lipsius' conception of virtue, like Jonson's, owed much to the great thinkers of ancient Rome, especially the Stoics.<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn3">3</ref> As perhaps the foremost <q direct="y">neostoic</q> of the Renaissance, Lipsius sought to reconcile the wisdom of such sages as Seneca, the shrewdness of such political historians as Tacitus, and the basic moral emphasis of Renaissance Christianity. It hardly seems surprising that Jonson found this mix appealing; he was only one of many European intellectuals who prized Lipsius' book for showing how the insights of the ancient Romans could be harmonized not only with a basic Christian ethic but also with a practical concern for real political conduct.<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn4">4</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="5">Yet it was not only from the Romans that Lipsius drew inspiration and citations. He also frequently quoted the Greeks, especially Aristotle, and particularly (if not surprisingly) Aristotle's own <title level="m">Ethics</title> and <title level="m">Politics</title>. And, typically, where Lipsius led, Jonson followed, marking the Greek quotations with a soft pencil and his customary vigor. Jonson also marked quotations from such other major Greek sources as Plato, Plutarch, Thucydides, and Xenophon, and the list of minor Greek sources he marked includes the following: the Adagia Graecorum (Greek adages), Aeschylus, Archilochus, Aristophanes, Athenaeus, Bias, Brasidas, Callimachus, Cleon, <q direct="y">Comicus vetus</q> (the old comedy), Crates, Dio Cassius, Diogenes Laertius, Diodorus Siculus, Epicurus, Euphemus, Euripides, Herodotus, Hesiod, Homer, Iamblichus, Lucian, Menander, Mercurius (Hermes) Trismegistus, Origines, Pericles, Philo Judaeus, Plutarch, Polybius, Serenus, Solon, Sophocles, and Stobaeus. Jonson's reading of Lipsius was therefore also a way of re-reading the ancient Greeks, and to speak of the <q direct="y">Lipsian</q> influence on Jonson's Caroline politics is to speak, indirectly, of a Greek influence as well. </p>
						<p n="6">Studying Jonson's familiarity with the Greeks, via Lipsius, seems important for several reasons. In the first place, separate copies of many of the Greek authors Jonson marked in Lipsius either do not survive from his personal library, or are not very fully marked by him, or are not marked by him at all. For instance, the standard catalogue of Jonson's library lists only one copy of Aristotle's complete works known to have been owned by the poet, but most of the markings in that volume do not seem to have been made by Jonson.<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn5">5</ref> Moreover, although Jonson is reported to have owned copies of Aristotle's <title level="m">Poetics</title> and <title level="m">Rhetoric</title>, their modern locations were unknown when the standard catalogue of his library was published (in 1974), nor have those locations been since reported. Furthermore, although the standard edition of Jonson's writings does cite a few references or allusions to Aristotle, it reports none to Aristotle's <title level="m">Politics</title>.<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn6">6</ref> Yet this is the Arisotelian work that Lipsius quotes most often, and Lipsius' quotations from it are routinely marked by Jonson. Similarly, although one allusion to Aristotle's <title level="m">Ethics</title> is reported in the standard edition, Lipsius cites that work repeatedly, and Jonson routinely marks such citations. Examining Jonson's markings of Greek quotations in Lipsius, then, may provide new insights into his political and ethical thinking. (It goes without saying that sometimes a <emph rend="italics">failure</emph> to mark, especially when much surrounding matter <emph rend="italics">is</emph> marked, can also possibly be significant.) In any case, examination of Jonson's responses to Lipsius' text can certainly offer new information about his familiarity with Greek thought.<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn7">7</ref> Moreover, discussing Jonson's familiarity with the Greeks whom Lipsius cites can help us search for unnoted allusions to them in Jonson's own writings of the Caroline period. </p>
						<p n="7">One such allusion involves Homer. In <title level="m">The King's Entertainment at Welbeck</title>, performed for Charles in May 1633, the king is described as a man <q direct="y">Whose single watch, defendeth all your sleepes! / Whose labours, are your rests! whose thoughts and cares, / Breed you<emph rend="italics">r</emph> delights! whose bus'nesse, all your leasures!</q> (H&amp;S 7: 801). As it happens, these words are borrowed almost verbatim from Seneca, quoted by Lipsius and distinctively marked by Jonson. The supposition that Jonson borrowed from Seneca by way of Lipsius seems clinched by the fact that the immediately preceding line from the <title level="m">Entertainment</title> borrows a phrase from Homer also quoted by Lipsius in the same chapter (and only a few lines before) his quotation from Seneca. In the <title level="m">Entertainment</title>, Jonson calls Charles the <q direct="y">Pastor</q> of his people, apparently echoing a phrase from Homer's <title level="m">Iliad</title> cited by Lipsius and translated by him as <q direct="y">pastor populorum</q> (43).<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn8">8</ref> Typically, in his copy of the <title level="m">Politics</title> Jonson underlines the original Greek (but not the translation), and the phrase is also encompassed by a long line drawn in the margin (43). Neither the allusion to Seneca nor the echo of Homer is noted in the standard edition of Jonson's works, although both seem clearly to have been inspired by his reading (and marking) of Lipsius.<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn9">9</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="8">Reviewing the marked Greek passages in Jonson's copy of Lipsius seems important, then, for several reasons. Doing so gives us a chance, if nothing else, to supplement the index of the standard edition, demonstrating Jonson's familiarity with a far wider range of Greek thought than that index indicates. Moreover, such a review can perhaps assist us in tracing previously unnoted allusions and, more broadly, in appreciating more fully the extent of Jonson's interest in (and familiarity with) Greek culture. He was, after all, the poet who noted Shakespeare's knowledge of <q direct="y">small <emph rend="italics">Latine</emph>, and lesse <emph rend="italics">Greeke</emph>
							</q> (H&amp;S 8:391), and Jonson seems to have been justly proud of his own ability in Greek. We take his knowledge of the Romans for granted, but his awareness of Greek thought and writing has perhaps been less fully stressed. Finally, examining that awareness, as it was derived from his reading of Lipsius, may also help provide a fuller understanding of the underlying political principles that helped shape Jonson's thinking and writing during the reign of Charles I.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>II.</head>
						<p n="9">Jonson's markings of Greek authors whose names begin the Roman alphabet are spotty until one arrives at Aristotle.<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn10">10</ref> He does underline and flower one quote from an unidentified play by AESCHYLUS; this asserts that a wise man knows, not many things, but things which are most useful (36). ANAXIMENES, probable author of the <title level="m">Rhetorica ad Alexandrum</title>, also provided several quotes that Jonson marked, but since the <title level="m">Rhetorica</title> was usually attributed to Aristotle (and is so attributed by Lipsius), those quotes will be discussed later. A phrase from ARCHILOCHUS is underlined; it refers to greedy officials who fleece the public (117).<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn11">11</ref> Similarly, <title level="m">The Acharnians</title>, by ARISTOPHANES, includes a passage that Jonson marks. It suggests that those who lack religion and fidelity are not to be trusted (54). Finally, ATHENAEUS (117) is cited as the source of a quotation from Sophocles (to be discussed later). </p>
						<p n="10">ARISTOTLE, of course, was the Greek writer who most interested Lipsius, and in the sections of the <title level="m">Politics</title> Jonson read, he marks nearly all the Aristotelian citations. He flowers, for instance, an underlined Aristotelian assertion (source unspecified) that the understanding is the soul's eye (31). Although he fails to mark a quote from Aristotle's <title level="m">Ethics</title> linking honesty and prudence (31), he does mark an extended definition of prudence (31) -- a trait Lipsius considered essential in any good ruler. Later he marks a passage from the <title level="m">Ethics</title> in which Aristotle stresses a ruler's need for experience (33), while another marked citation from the same work links prudence with experience (76). Also marked is the claim that we give most credence to that which is least subject to change (77), although Lipsius cautions that prudence can never be reduced to unchanging rules. Interestingly, Jonson fails to pick out in any special way a final quote from the <title level="m">Ethics</title>, in which Aristotle notes the hedonism and dissolute living of the multitude (124). </p>
						<p n="11">Aristotle's <title level="m">Politics</title> provides the main source of Lipsius' quotations from the Greek philosopher, and Jonson marks them profusely. He underscores, for instance, the claims that ruling and being ruled are both necessary and profitable (37) and that monarchy is the most ancient and godlike form of government (38). He marks, too, the claim that males are more naturally fit to rule than women (39), as well as the assertion that while a tyrant seeks his own good, a king seeks the profit and good of his subjects (43).<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn12">12</ref> Jonson also notes the claim that elected kings are often chosen for their preeminent virtue (44), and he notes, too, Aristotle's advice that a good king should protect his people, both aristocracy and commonality (49).<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn13">13</ref> Interestingly, a horizontal line is drawn next to the underscored passage in which Aristotle wonders whether there is any difference between a woman ruling and a prince being ruled by a woman (59). (The extra marking makes one wonder whether Jonson saw any relevance to Charles' relations with Henrietta Maria.) Also specially marked (with a flower and horizontal line) is Aristotle's later declaration that a prince ought to take a chief interest in religion (78).<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn14">14</ref> Later, Jonson underscores Aristotle's argument that a prince is only the keeper and distributor, not the owner, of the commonwealth's goods (118), although he fails to underline the philosopher's report that tax assessments were often made in either three- or five-year cycles (120). Jonson does underline the recommendation that no citizen should have too much power (122), and he triply marks the final quotation from Aristotle's <title level="m">Politics</title> with a pointing hand, a flower, and underlining. This is the observation that political instability and tyranny can result from prodigality (123).<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn15">15</ref> Here as elsewhere, Jonson seems to have been especially interested in Lipsius' tendency to emphasize the public or political consequences of personal or private behavior. </p>
						<p n="12">Lipsius cites Aristotle's <title level="m">Rhetoric</title> less frequently than the <title level="m">Politics</title>, but Jonson shows his usual interest. He marks, for instance, the claim that remembering the past is profitable when making present decisions (34), and he also marks the claim that laws safeguard a city (49). Finally, when Lipsius cautions against excessive taxes, Jonson marks Aristotle's proverbial warning against draining the dead (116). He also marks a passage Lipisus attributes to Aristotle (from the <q direct="y">Rhetor. ad. Theod.</q>) which contends that allowing contracts to be violated or infringed will greatly damage commerce (54). Similarly, Jonson marks as well several passages from the <title level="m">Rhetorica ad Alexandrum</title>, once attributed to Aristotle but now assigned to ANAXIMENES. One passage advises that integrity can be expected from those who fear either divine punishment or infamy on earth (55), while another urges a prince to adorn the mind, not the body (56). Jonson not only underlines the Greek version of this passage but also draws a trident-shaped mark next to its Latin translation (57). He also marks a passage from the <title level="m">Rhetorica</title> asserting that God most favors those who worship him with the greatest affection (78), and also one suggesting that all nations account it a capital crime to violate received customs (79).<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn16">16</ref> These last three passages probably originated with Anaximenes, but a long line of writers, including Jonson and Lipsius, associated them with Aristotle. </p>
						<p n="13">Jonson does mark a passage from ATHENAEUS quoting Sophocles (117; see below). Similarly, words from BIAS are marked, but only as cited by Stobaeus (29; see below), just as BRASIDAS is cited as quoted by Thucydides (54; see below). CALLIMACHUS is, alphabetically, the Greek whom Lipsius next cites and whom Jonson marks: Hymn I is quoted to affirm that kings come from God (38).<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn17">17</ref> A source identified only as CLEON is cited as quoted by Thucydides (53; see below), while a passage from <q direct="y">COMICUS VETUS</q> (old comedy) is underlined to show that money is the soul and blood of mortal men (114). A source identified only as CRATES provides two quotes taken from Stobaeus (119; see below) while various marked quotations list DIO CASSIUS as their source. That historian, for instance, is cited for reporting Maecenas' advice (to the emperor Augustus) that the ruler should always and in all ways revere God, observe his country's laws, and encourage others to do likewise (79). Interestingly, Jonson does not underline an immediately ensuing quotation from Dio Cassius advising strong punishment for those who innovate in religion, although a long curved and then vertical marginal line does encompass it (79).<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn18">18</ref> Although Jonson underscores a later quote noting that the common people diligently examine a prince's profits and revenues but overlook his expenses (114), he does not underline another quote from Dio Cassius suggesting that the poor should be taxed little by little (118). Yet he emphatically marks (with a marginal flower, a curved line, a horizontal line, and underscoring) a passage from Dio Cassius contending that the people will not begrudge taxes if they see that the prince lives soberly and moderately, without wasting anything vainly (118). Finally, Maecenas is the source of two unmarked quotes from Dio Cassius (119; 121). </p>
						<p n="14">
							<q direct="y">DIOGENES STOIC.</q> is the cited source of a vigorously marked quote. This Diogenes seems to have been the Stoic philosopher sometimes linked with Babylonia or Seleucia (<title level="m">Webster's</title> 421). Lipsius cites Stobaeus, the Greek anthologist, as his source for this lengthy quote, which is marked with underlining, a flower, a vertical line in the margin, and a horizontal line. In it, Diogenes argues that the worthiest person (the prince) should most revere the worthiest matter (religion), since both he and it are preeminent (78). Meanwhile, two marked quotes are attributed to the <title level="m">Bibliotheca</title> of DIODORUS SICULUS. The first praises history for preserving the virtue of worthy persons, for recording the wretched acts of the wicked, and for benefitting all mankind (34). The second, specially highlighted with a flower, is used by Lipsius to condemn Egyptian kings who sought to solidify their rule by imposing a diverse and confused religion on their subjects, thus preventing conspiracies (78). </p>
						<p n="15">EPICURUS, as cited in Latin by Seneca, is then cited by Lipsius in a passage Jonson marks. To stress the power of conscience, Epicurus is paraphrased as arguing that a wicked man may hide himself but will still be full of doubt (29). Similarly, EUPHEMUS, as cited by Thucydides, is marked by Jonson (48; see below). Meanwhile, EURIPIDES is the source of three quotes. One argues that great persons should obey the law (48).<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn19">19</ref> The second (apparently from <title level="m">Iphigeneia in Taurus</title>) praises fidelity (54), and the third is used to condemn cynical, hypocritical piety that can disguise violations of equity and justice (54). Finally, <q direct="y">Moyses the AEgyptian,</q> as cited by EUSEBIUS (and as translated by the Latin writer Rufinus of Aquileia), is quoted to suggest that in judging a man's faith, seeing (rather than hearing) is believing (25). In other words, acts are more credible than declarations. </p>
						<p n="16">A source listed only as <q direct="y">GRAECOR. ADAG.</q> (Greek adages?) provides a marked quote arguing that god sells riches for labor (27), while the <title level="m">Histories</title> of HERODOTUS provide a flowered passage declaring that a man cannot avoid what is fated, nor will he accept admonishment rooted in probability (27). The <title level="m">Theogony</title> of HESIOD, meanwhile, is quoted to argue that the earliest kings were created only to speak what was right and to punish offences (49), while HOMER is cited on six separate occasions. One unspecified Homeric source, for instance, claims that kings are nourished and brought up with God (39), and the <title level="m">Iliad</title> is quoted to support the ideal of one lord and prince (39).<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn20">20</ref> The <title level="m">Iliad</title> is also the source of a passage comparing the king to a shepherd (43), while a flowered passage from the same source stresses the dishonor involved when a prince devours his people (i.e., through taxation; 114). Two passages from the <title level="m">Odyssey</title> stress the value of experience in knowing good and evil (33) and emphasize the ideal similarities between a prince and a father (51). </p>
						<p n="17">IAMBLICHUS is quoted twice by Lipsius in passages that Jonson marks. He and Aristotle are both cited to suggest that the understanding is the eye of the soul (an idea flowered by Jonson; 31), while Iamblichus alone is credited with the claim that what is honored increases, that what is condemned diminishes, and that such patterns are signs of a well ordered kingdom (125). LUCIAN, meanwhile, provides the figurative language which allows Lipsius to accuse greedy officials of being more ravenous than cats (a comparison Jonson not only underlines but highlights with one of his distinctive cross-shaped marks). MENANDER is quoted to argue that all things obey prudence (32), while the <title level="m">Poemandres</title> of MERCURIUS (HERMES) TRISMEGISTUS is cited to assert that all mortals are subject to destiny by birth and mutability (26). ORIGENES is quoted to prove that conscience is the correctress of our affections and the schoolmistress of our soul (28), and PERICLES is quoted by Thucydides, who in turn is quoted by Lipsius (28; see below). Meanwhile, PHILO JUDAEUS, in his <title level="m">Embassy to Gaius</title>, provides the observation that people base religious beliefs on personal emotions rather than reason. However, Jonson does not underline this quote (although it is encompassed by one of his long marginal lines). </p>
						<p n="18">PLATO provides a number of quotations that Jonson underscored, although he is cited less than half as often as Aristotle in the parts of Lipsius' <title level="m">Politics</title> that Jonson marked. Jonson notes, for instance, words from the <title level="m">Theaetetus</title> emphasizing that virtue and justice are divine qualities (23), but he fails to mark words from the <title level="m">Republic</title> alluding to the difficulty of discussing religious topics (25). The <title level="m">Meno</title> provides the idea that prudence precedes and leads to proper behavior (31), while <title level="m">Alcibiades II</title> provides an unmarked definition of discretion (32). Plato's <title level="m">Politicus</title> is the source for an underlined assertion comparing a king to a god among men (38), and from the <title level="m">Politicus</title>, too, comes a marked quotation arguing that a lawless state will seem irksome and attract no willing allegiance (47). Jonson shows great interest in a passage from <title level="m">Alcibiades I</title> (marking it in various ways, including with a flower, and underlining both the original Greek and the Latin translation). Here Plato is quoted as urging that to govern well, a ruler must communicate his virtue to the citizens (45). Finally, Jonson flowers a passage from Plato's <title level="m">Laws</title> urging assessments of individual wealth (120). </p>
						<p n="19">PLUTARCH is another Greek who apparently fascinated both Lipsius and Jonson. His <title level="m">Parallel Lives</title> provided Lipsius with a number of quotes that Jonson marked. The life of <title level="m">Timolean</title>, for instance, commends history for providing patterns of virtue to emulate (34), while the life of <title level="m">Cato</title> seems the source of a quote from Cato suggesting that law courts should be set with traps for lawyers (50). From the life of <title level="m">Alexander</title> Lipsius seems to have borrowed that leader's criticism of gardeners who cut herbs to the root (115) -- criticism that Lipsius uses to indict excessive taxation. However, on the same page of Lipsius' <title level="m">Politics</title>, Jonson fails to mark a comment on persuasion and force from Plutarch's life of <title level="m">Themistocles</title> (115), nor does he mark another comment (from the same source) on poverty and weakness (116). He does, though, mark a quote from Plutarch taken from a work identified only as <q direct="y">Politic.</q> This passage observes that people are generally full of malice and complaint toward those who govern (126). Finally, Plutarch (in a work identified only as <q direct="y">Apophth.</q>) is also the source of the underscored idea that princes are accustomed to being criticized for doing good (126). </p>
						<p n="20">POLYBIUS, another historian, provided two Lipsian passages marked by Jonson. The first commends histories for providing the best guide to managing civil affairs (34), while the second (in Latin) commends stable commonwealths in which people live virtuous private lives while publicly embracing clemency and justice (45). Meanwhile, a Greek cited only as <q direct="y">SERINUS</q> (or <q direct="y">SERENUS</q>) is quoted to defend monarchy, comparing the effects of divided power to the probable dangers of having two suns (38). From an unspecified source, SOLON is quoted as linking advancing wisdom with advancing age (34), and three quotations are attributed to SOPHOCLES. The first, on prudence as a source of happiness (32), comes from <title level="m">Antigone</title>, while a second, from an unspecified work, illustrates Jonson's occasionally selective annotation. The entire passage is encompassed by a vertical line, but only the last phrase is underscored. The section not underlined lists the chaos resulting from lack of government, while the underscored portion emphasizes the benefits of obedience (37).<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn21">21</ref> Finally, an unspecified Sophoclean passage (borrowed from Athenaeus) is not underlined but is marginally marked. It suggests that people often overlook evil when pursuing gain (117). In contrast, the <title level="m">Florilegium</title> of STOBAEUS is cited for (in turn) citing Bias, who linked a clear conscience with lack of fear (29), just as Stobaeus' <title level="m">Sermones</title> are quoted for citing an unspecified <q direct="y">Crates</q> who compared princely wealth and riches to fig trees on mountaintops, accessible only to birds of prey (119). Jonson flowers this, and the same source is cited to identify such birds with strumpets and flatterers (119). Like other marked passages in Greek, these two memorably demonstrate Jonson's often mediated access to the classics: Crates is cited by Stobaeus, Stobaeus is cited by Lipsius, and Lipsius' citation is read and marked by Jonson. </p>
						<p n="21">THUCYDIDES provides another example of such indirect access. Thus from an oration quoted by the Greek historian, Jonson marks Pericles' words that we must endure what the gods decree and must confront enemies with fortitude (28), just as he also marks Lipsius quoting Thucydides quoting the Athenian ambassador Euphemus. Euphemus is reported to have justified expedient rulers, but Lipsius strongly condemns his words, and Jonson not only underlines the quotation but also marks it with an asterisk (48). Jonson also marks a passage from Thucydides suggesting that men and states naturally err and that no laws can completely restrain them (52). When Thucydides quotes Cleon as having said that commiseration, gracious speech, and lenity hurt a government (53), Jonson underlines and flowers the quotation, but he also underlines Lipsius' assessment that Cleon foully erred in having said this. However, Lipsius explicitly commends Brasidas, as cited by Thucydides, for having said that it is more disgraceful for powerful persons to triumph by deceit than by open force (54). Jonson not only underscores this notion but marks it with an asterisk, and these words constitute simply another of the various passages he marked in which Lipsius quotes Thucydides quoting someone else. </p>
						<p n="22">XENOPHON brings us not only near the close of the alphabet but also to the end of the Greek sources Jonson marked. From the <title level="m">Memorabilia Socratis</title>, for instance, he underlined a passage arguing that a king is not chosen in order to pamper himself but in order to promote the happiness of those who have so honored him (43). Similarly, from the <title level="m">Cyropaedeia</title> he marked Cyrus' opinion that no person was fit to rule unless he was more excellent than his subjects (44), and he similarly marked Cyrus' reasoning (from the same source) that if persons feared God, they would be less likely to attack either each other or the ruler (78). From Xenophon's <title level="m">Anabasis</title> Lipsius borrowed, and Jonson marked, the assertion that no riches can adorn a person, especially a prince, more than virtue and justice (48). And, finally, from the <title level="m">Hieron</title> comes a marked passage associating Venus and the graces with the prince (57). Lipsius uses this quote to advise against over-elaborate clothing, and Jonson marks the words not only with underlining but also with an emphatic asterisk.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>III.</head>
						<p n="23">The relevance of Jonson's reading of Lipsius to an understanding of the poet's Caroline politics can easily be glimpsed if we turn to one of his earliest Caroline poems -- <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">A speach according to</title> Horace</q> (<title level="m">Under-wood</title> 44; H&amp;S 8.213-16). Its date has usually been assumed to be early in the new reign, but Martin Butler has recently offered convincing reasons for dating it fairly precisely, arguing that it was probably written sometime <q direct="y">between late March and mid-April 1626</q> (287). This means that the poem was probably composed not much more than a year after Charles succeeded to the throne, and only a few years after Jonson could have acquired his 1623 copy of Lipsius' <title level="m">Politics</title>. There is, of course, no way to know for sure whether the poet had acquired his copy of Lipsius <emph rend="italics">before</emph> writing the <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">Speach</title>,</q> yet this uncertainty hardly matters. My point, after all, is not to argue that reading Lipsius influenced the poem's composition; rather, my point is to suggest that the politics the poem reveals are congruent with the <title level="m">Politics</title> of Justus Lipsius. Whether Jonson read the <title level="m">Politics</title> before or after writing the poem, the <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">Speach</title>
							</q> implies many parallels with the thoughts of the Flemish theorist. If the <title level="m">Politics</title> influenced the poet, it is easy to see why; if the author of the <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">Speach</title>
							</q> read Lipsius with interest, that is also easy to understand. </p>
						<p n="24">George Parfitt, one of Jonson's best critics, has called the <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">Speach</title>
							</q>
							<q direct="y">puzzling and fascinating</q> and <q direct="y">an example of a great public poet trying to cope with a difficult social and historical situation</q> (86). Parfitt rightly points out that the poem <q direct="y">belongs to a period of national and international uncertainty, a period which forced men to examine their allegiances and beliefs with care</q> (87), and he argues that the <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">Speach</title>
							</q> is fascinating <q direct="y">partly because it is not only a deeply disturbed poem but also because it is one in which the disturbance is not fully resolved</q> (87). In the poem, Jonson excoriates the aristocracy and gentry for neglecting their traditional duties as military leaders, and, with a mixture of admiration, condescension, and apparently genuine perplexity, he describes how trained bands of armed commoners have stepped in to fill the gap. According to Parfitt, <q direct="y">Jonson found the situation puzzling,</q> since the <q direct="y">vacuum [had been] filled by men whom Jonson could not believe were capable of fulfilling the roles they were playing</q> (91). Parfitt considers Jonson's puzzlement <q direct="y">honest, intelligent, and revealing</q> (91), and he contends that the <q direct="y">quality and integrity of Jonson's response in this poem are such that its inability to provide solutions testifies to the difficulties of the situation</q> (92). In Parfitt's words, <q type="block"> Preserving the tensions of a major creative writer as his society moved towards changes of immense importance, the poem thus reveals something of the complexity of choice-with-integrity at this time, and it provides a moving sense of how deeply a man may care for a culture and society which were destined, as history posthumously says, to change . . . . (92)</q>
						</p>
						<p n="25">Parfitt's reading makes the <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">Speach</title>
							</q> seem all the more fascinating, both as a poem and as a human and historical document. One can easily see why a man capable of writing this work might eagerly have welcomed the social, ethical, and political advice Lipsius could offer. And, in fact, Lipsius' ideas seem especially relevant to a fuller understanding of the mentality that produced the poem's final half. That section (largely unexamined by Parfitt) vibrates with resonances also heard in Lipsius, and noting such parallels can perhaps provide us with new insights -- not simply into Jonson's <q direct="y">stoic politics</q> but also into the complexities of a particularly intriguing work of art. Here as elsewhere, knowing something about Jonson's politics can perhaps help to make us more sensitive readers of his poems. </p>
						<p n="26">The concluding portion of the <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">Speach</title>
							</q> attacks the superficial training of various <q direct="y">Lordings</q> (l. 62) and <q direct="y">Grandlings</q> (l. 64), who bristle at any attempt to <q direct="y">tutor</q> them in their responsibilities (l. 66), especially when that attempt is made by <q direct="y">Booke-wormes</q> (l. 67).<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn22">22</ref> Rejecting their traditional military duties, they take pride instead in their birth, breeding, and alliances (l. 66), and Jonson makes them contemptuously ask, <q direct="y">Why are we rich, or great, except to show / All licence in our lives?</q> (ll. 69-70). The only subjects they profess to care about are sports, whoring, dancing, making money, attending plays, and wearing elaborate costumes. As for their social obligations, Jonson imagines them variously crying, <q direct="y">let Clownes, and Tradesmen breed / Their Sonnes to studie Arts, the Lawes, the Creed</q> (ll. 73-74), and <q direct="y">Let poore Nobilitie be vertuous</q> (l. 79), and <q direct="y">Let them care, / That in the Cradle of their Gentrie are; / To serve the State by Councels, and by Armes</q> (ll. 83-85). The poem's final lines condemn such pseudo-aristocrats as <q direct="y">Carkasses of honour; Taylors blocks, / Cover'd with Tissue, whose prosperitie mocks / The fate of things</q> (ll. 99-101). They are, in the poem's grim final words, nothing but hollow or <q direct="y">emptie moulds</q> (l. 102). Their personal irresponsibility, Jonson suggests, is not only individually degenerate but also dangerous to the larger body politic. </p>
						<p n="27">As it happens, the final pages that Jonson marked in his copy of Lipsius' <title level="m">Politics</title> are obviously relevant to the general tone and specific details of the <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">Speach</title>.</q> Those pages idealize the old Roman role of censor, a role concerned with supervising and correcting manners. Jonson seems to have sometimes seen himself as a kind of censor, and certainly the title of his poem suggests that he was self-consciously thinking of Roman examples. In any case, his markings in this section of Lipsius provide many points of comparison with the indictment he issues in the <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">Speach</title>.</q> For instance, there is an obvious parallel between the tone of the poem and Lipsius' claim that when license is tolerated, it can eventually <q direct="y">wholly subvert an estate</q> (121). To combat such license, the censor should serve <q direct="y">as the corrector of manners, and master of the ancient discipline</q> (121) -- certainly a role Jonson seems to relish playing in this poem.<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn23">23</ref> In particular, the censor should be concerned (as is Jonson in the <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">Speach</title>
							</q>) <q direct="y">to cut off from youth ill practises, and unlawfull desires</q> (121), and he should encourage all citizens to pursue <q direct="y">goodnesse and paines taking, not sumptuousnesse, nor riches</q> (121).<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn24">24</ref> Without such correction, excess would <q direct="y">grow infinit in euerie thing, where monie might be prodigallie consumed</q> (122), particularly in <q direct="y">Monie, Buildings, Banquets, and Apparel</q> (122).<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn25">25</ref> According to Lipsius, <q direct="y">Effeminate riches haue poisoned al ages with dishonest superfluitie</q> (122), and an excessive concern with money (as demonstrated by the <q direct="y">Grandlings</q> in <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">A Speach</title>
							</q>) is <q direct="y">a most dangerous plague</q> (122). Typically, Lipsius piles quotation on quotation to reiterate his point, borrowing words from Aristotle, among many others (122). </p>
						<p n="28">Lipsius' condemnation of <q direct="y">usurie</q> that benefits <q direct="y">the welthier sort</q> (121; a recurrent theme) seems particularly relevant to Jonson's similar condemnation of the idle rich, whose chief interest is in <q direct="y">so much land a yeare, or such a Banke, / That turnes us so much moneys, at which rate / Our Ancestors impos'd on Prince and State</q> (ll. 76-78). Similarly relevant to Jonson's poem is Lipsius' attack on <q direct="y">Superfluitie in banquets and apparell,</q> which is the token of <q direct="y">a diseased citie</q> (123). Such tastes <q direct="y">do stirre vp youth, after they have spent their owne substance, to do wicked acts</q> (123), and indeed Aristotle himself is quoted as having warned that <q direct="y">alteration [i.e., subversion or revolution] is made in an estate, when men consume all in living prodigallie, for these fellowes bend their studies to innouat matters, and either they themselues are very neere tyrannie, or else they call others thereto</q> (123). Jonson may have taken a particular interest in this warning, since it is preceded by the admonition that unchecked license <q direct="y">will breed a seminarie of the race of Catiline</q> (123). </p>
						<p n="29">To combat the kinds of excesses he attacks, Lipsius commends the role of censor -- a role quite similar to that of the Jonsonian satirist. The censor ideally functions by attempting to shame transgressors (124), much as Jonson does in the <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">Speach</title>.</q> If shame should fail, then corporal punishment may be necessary (124), but in any case the prince must be vigilant to <q direct="y">Cause Faith to return backe, correct voluptuousnesse, and bind together, by seuere lawes, those things which are decaied</q> (124).<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn26">26</ref> The ruler should <q direct="y">rather . . . labour for the safetie of all men, then for their pleasure</q> (124). When supervising his people, he should not <q direct="y">winke at that which is euill, dissemble their faults, and with their present pleasure, giue consent to their future mischiefe</q> (124). Instead, he must live an exemplary life and thus shame others into doing the same.<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn27">27</ref>
							<q direct="y">Shame will worke the best alteration in some, in others necessitie, and euen a loathing of it in others</q> (125). Iamblichus is quoted as extolling the effectiveness of princely reward and punishment: <q direct="y">What so is in honour is augmented and increaseth, &amp; that which is in contempt, declineth, and diminisheth: and that is a most manifest sign of a kingdome well established</q> (125). One could hardly ask for a better explanation of the rationale and objectives of Jonson's <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">Speach</title>,</q> a poem in which Jonson adopts the role of censor, becoming a kind of unofficial magistrate of manners. </p>
						<p n="30">Whether Jonson read Lipsius' discussion of the censor before, during, or after writing his poem, it is easy to see why that reading caught his interest and how it is relevant both to this specific poem and to his Caroline politics in general. Fundamentally, both the theorist and the poet share an essentially moralistic approach to political problems: most political and social ills can be traced to the kind of <q direct="y">private</q> immorality the <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">Speach</title>
							</q> attacks. In fact, of course, for both Jonson and Lipsius no immorality is ever truly private; all selfish or unethical conduct inevitably has harmful social consequences. If Jonson seems obsessed by such apparently trivial matters as aristocratic addictions to <q direct="y">gate, / Carriage, and dressing</q> (ll. 87-88) and if he fulminates against those whose chief desire is to <q direct="y">make legs</q> and <q direct="y">smell most sweet</q> (l. 90), it is not because he is a busybody who cannot leave other people alone. It is because he, like Lipsius, cannot finally separate <q direct="y">private</q> behavior from its social and political ramifications. No wonder he read Lipsius with such eagerness; no wonder he marked him with such zest. </p>
						<p n="31">However, pointing out the general parallels between Lipsian ideas and the ideas Jonson expresses in <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">A Speach</title>
							</q> calls attention to only one of the poem's dimensions. Like any significant work of art, the <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">Speach</title>
							</q> is interesting less for what it says than for the artistry with which its points are made. We value Jonson first and foremost as a poet, not as a political thinker, and the true test of his worth as a political poet resides in the way he manages to make his politics contribute to the richness and density of his art. George Parfitt has already demonstrated how the political ambivalence of the <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">Speach</title>
							</q> heightens its artistic complexity and its lasting interest, but, as before, Parfitt's remarks focus mainly on the poem's first half. Here, I will conclude by examining more closely the final section, a section that is both politically intriguing and artistically sophisticated.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>IV.</head>
						<p n="32">Obviously one technique that Jonson most fully exploits in the <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">Speach</title>
							</q> is the one Lipsius associates with the Roman censor: the technique of shame. The poem can be read as one long effort to embarrass and humiliate the irresponsible aristocrats who neglect their duties to the commonwealth. Although Jonson suggests that his hope is to <q direct="y">perswade</q> (l. 61) or appeal to reason, he immediately concedes that this goal is unrealistic: his targets are likened to irrational, inhuman forces of nature (the <q direct="y">billow, wind, and storme</q> of <q direct="y">Tempestuous Grandlings</q>; ll. 63-64). This hopelessness, of course, helps authorize Jonson's blatantly satirical tone, even while the satire itself is meant to persuade the uncorrupted (including, presumably, the King) that social reformation is urgently needed.<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn28">28</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="33">Jonson suggests that the obstacles to reform include not only personal egotism but also family pride and class snobbery -- all forces which subvert the ideal and reality of a commonwealth. Jonson imagines the <q direct="y">Grandlings</q> asking, <q direct="y">Who'll informe / Us, in our bearing, that are thus, and thus, / Borne, bred, allied?</q> (ll. 64-66). These lines demonstrate his artistry, especially in the heavily accented <q direct="y">Us,</q> the ensuing assonance of <q direct="y">us</q> sounds, the forceful alliteration of <q direct="y">b's,</q> and the strong stress on the three significant final verbs. The smug tone perfectly fits the imagined speakers, but, as usual, Jonson also squeezes maximum meaning out of a few words. The phrase <q direct="y">Borne, bred, allied,</q> for instance, encapsulates the major stages of a grandling's life, especially the word <q direct="y">allied,</q> which implies not only involvement in political factions (themselves dangerous to the commonwealth) but also the formation of family alliances. Marriage is imagined here as primarily political; the family is conceived not as rooted in love, loyalty, and virtue, but simply as another self-seeking interest group. </p>
						<p n="34">When Jonson imagines the grandlings objecting to being <q direct="y">tutor[ed]</q> by <q direct="y">Booke-wormes</q> (l. 67), he may have recalled his own real-life roles as tutor and reader, although he obviously also looks back to the reference in l. 35 to <q direct="y">
								<emph rend="italics">Aelian</emph>'<emph rend="italics">s</emph> tactickes,</q> a book which the city bands apparently consulted. Jonson himself owned, read, and marked a copy of this famous work (in the original Latin, of course [McPherson 13, 23]), and his reading of both Aelian and Lipsius shows that his interests, though bookish, were never impractical. This makes all the more ironic the grandlings' accusation that bookish tutors <q direct="y">dare doe nothing free</q> (l. 68). Jonson, of course, prided himself on his daring and valor,<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn29">29</ref> but the accusation is also ironic, because the freedom the grandlings prize is actually enslaving. Theirs is an egotistical <q direct="y">licence</q> (l. 70) which, by abdicating responsibility, actually promotes oppression, tyranny, and even foreign attack. By voicing the usually unspoken asumptions that motivate the grandlings' conduct, Jonson exposes their foolishness.<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn30">30</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="35">By demanding the right to <q direct="y">All</q> licence (l. 70), the grandlings violate the cardinal Lipsian tenets of reason and moderation.<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn31">31</ref> Seeking mere pleasure, they miss their full human potential -- a fact nicely emphasized when Jonson links them with animals such as dogs, horses, and hawks (ll. 71-72). The grandlings reject such distinguishingly human (and humane) values as learning, loyalty, virtue, honor, and responsibility, and indeed they make a sorry contrast even with the animals they prize, since these beasts display such qualities as obedience, discipline, and focused pursuit. Their masters, in contrast, merely <emph rend="italics">assume</emph> their superiority to <q direct="y">Citizens,</q>
							<q direct="y">Clownes,</q> and <q direct="y">Tradesmen</q> (l. 73), and Jonson seems to mock, not share, their condescension. Here as elsewhere, he seems to value worth, not wealth or birth. For him as for Lipsius, virtue is the chief criterion of social merit.<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn32">32</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="36">In dismissing so quickly and cavalierly the importance of learning <q direct="y">Arts</q> and <q direct="y">Lawes</q> and <q direct="y">Creed</q> (l. 74), the grandlings dismiss three central emphases of Lipsius' <title level="m">Politics</title>, and it seems nicely ironic that the stressed verb-phrase <q direct="y">will beleeve</q> (l. 75) refers not to any transcendent commitment but simply to a willful devotion to wealth.<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn33">33</ref> Here again Jonson takes full advantage of an apparently simple word, since <q direct="y">will</q> implies not only stubbornness but also inevitability and an indefinite, continuing perversity. At the same time, he looks back to the past while refusing to romanticize it, instead conceding that the self-serving aristocrats merely follow the false lead of greedy <q direct="y">Ancestors</q> (l. 78). Yet even as he criticizes aristocratic snobbery (as in the reference to <q direct="y">men of our owne Ranke</q>; l. 75), Jonson does not criticize the ideal of aristocracy itself. Indeed, it is the grandlings who betray that ideal by expecting only the <q direct="y">poore Nobilitie</q> to <q direct="y">be vertuous</q> (l. 79). Jonson even makes the <q direct="y">Prince and State</q> seem victims of aristocratic avarice (l. 78). Caroline England is criticized, but Charles himself escapes direct blame. Both he and the commonwealth are abused by nobles who, instead of priding themselves on a heritage of service, benefit from a heritage of self-serving exploitation. </p>
						<p n="37">The egotism of such persons is, as usual, not only stated but also poetically and ironically underscored. Thus Jonson nicely stresses <q direct="y">Wee</q> (l. 79), while the adjective <q direct="y">poore</q> boomerangs in ways the wealthy but unworthy grandlings do not anticipate (l. 79). The grandlings have <q direct="y">Descended</q> in more ways than one, and the <q direct="y">rope of Titles</q> they value refers not only to interwoven strands of family connections, and not only to appelations of social rank, but also to binding, legalistic contracts or deeds of land. In these, ultimately, their power is rooted, although it is also shored up by the kind of bookworms (heralds) they earlier disdained (ll. 67; 82). Just as they concede military power to the trained bands, so they concede another sort of power to the heralds; their earlier lack of interest in learning extends even to their own family histories.<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn34">34</ref> And, through their irresponsibility, they permit fabricated titles to take up the slack. As long as heralds can justify aristocratic wealth, the grandlings are content; their <q direct="y">blood is now become / Past any need of vertue</q> (ll. 82-83). Here Jonson seems to suggest not only the literal, material blood through which titles were inherited, but also temperament and mettle, just as he also implies that virtue is partly a response to the challenges posed by necessity. An aristocracy faced with no pressures from necessity inevitably becomes both physically and ethically weak. </p>
						<p n="38">This weakness makes the reiterated <q direct="y">let . . . Let . . . Let</q> clauses of ll. 73-86 seem especially ironic. The repeated verbs suggest condescending permission or supercilious allowance (<q direct="y">Let poore Nobilitie be vertuous . . . Let them care</q>). Yet the clauses also convey weakness, fatigue, and dissipation disguised as indifference -- an abdication of responsibility and authority. The grandlings grant the right to duties (but also powers) they no longer care to discharge. By surrendering their traditional roles and rights to persons they consider to be <q direct="y">in the Cradle of their Gentrie</q> (l. 84), the grandlings actually prove their own immaturity, their own lack of accountability. Indeed, by calling them <q direct="y">grandlings</q> (a term he seems to have coined; see <title level="m">OED</title>), Jonson even hints that they are little more than <q direct="y">groundlings</q> -- commoners in the least attractive sense, despite their land and titles. They refuse to serve <q direct="y">the State,</q> either <q direct="y">by Councels</q> or <q direct="y">by Armes</q> (l. 85). The phrasing here, as often, is quietly equivocal: <q direct="y">Councels</q> can be understood both as modern-day <q direct="y">councils</q> and as <q direct="y">counsels</q> (suggesting both public and private advice), while the linking of <q direct="y">Councels</q> and <q direct="y">Armes</q> suggests the ideal union of mind and body, intent and deed, always prized by Jonson. Moreover, when the grandlings confess that they <q direct="y">neither love the Troubles, nor the harmes</q> (l. 86), the linked nouns suggest an aversion both to mental or emotional anxiety and to physical or material risk. </p>
						<p n="39">This emphasis on avoiding pain, however, is at once replaced by a desire not simply for pleasure but for <emph rend="italics">illicit</emph> pleasure. The first <q direct="y">love</q> the grandlings mention is a <q direct="y">whore</q> -- a noun that immediately renders the word <q direct="y">love</q> ironic (l. 87). In the same way, the verb <q direct="y">study</q> is paradoxical, since the <q direct="y">study</q> mentioned makes mind serve body (ll. 86-87). Moreover, the subjects of such study are completely superficial; they lack even the dignity of being necessary. The grandlings make their bodies act and appear in unnatural, unspontaneous ways, and although such <q direct="y">study</q> is motivated partly by egotism, it is also driven by a fear of of being momentarily unfashionable. Ironically, the grandlings neglect their larger responsibilities to the commonwealth not in pursuit of genuine independence (which Jonson might respect), but rather in pursuit of a debased and slavish obedience. Here as throughout, egotism equals servitude. The grandlings' concern with <q direct="y">gate, / Carriage, and dressing</q> makes them seem almost feminine (ll. 87-88), if femininity is identified (as it often was in Jonson's culture) with weakness and vanity.<ref target="emls4-1evanjonsn35">35</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="40">Jonson's reference to such superficial <q direct="y">study</q> nicely sets up his ensuing ironic mention of the <q direct="y">Academie, where the Gallants meet</q> to <q direct="y">make legs</q> and <q direct="y">to smell most sweet</q> (ll. 89-90). By selecting <q direct="y">Academie,</q> of course, he chooses a noun with enormous resonance -- a word linked with some of the greatest traditions of classical philosophy. In the present context the word seems almost parodic, and this group of self-absorbed <q direct="y">Gallants</q> also contrasts strongly not only with truly disciplined scholars but even with the well-intentioned (if somewhat ridiculous) trained bands of citizen-soldiers whom Jonson stresses so strongly in the poem's first half. The very word <q direct="y">Gallant</q> -- from a French term meaning to <q direct="y">make merry</q> -- suggests the superficiality of those it describes, while the gallants' concern to <q direct="y">make legs</q> implies not genuine deference or real respect but simply another kind of self-assertion, competition, and public display. The act of making legs may involve bowing and apparent humility, but in this case it actually symbolizes pride. Like so much the grandlings do, it is done for show. </p>
						<p n="41">This is why it seems so appropriate that they attend <q direct="y">Playes,</q> where they are less concerned to witness performances than to perform. Just as they neglect their responsibilities as members of the commonwealth, so they also neglect their responsibilities as attentive members of the audience. They attend theaters not to learn but to usurp attention, a fact which makes the reference to how diligently they <q direct="y">learne and studie</q> at the <q direct="y">Academie</q> all the more ironic (l. 92). By describing how the grandlings primp (fixing their <q direct="y">eye-browes,</q> attempting their <q direct="y">Beautie to repaire</q> [ll. 97, 96]), Jonson once again feminizes them, but he also implies how much their neglect of the endangered body politic springs from a preoccupation with their own decaying bodies. How appropriate, then, that he should call them <q direct="y">Carkasses of honour</q> (l. 99). This apparently simple phrase is typically rich, suggesting not only that the grandlings embody the death of honor, and not only that they are carkasses who happen (by accident of birth) to be conventionally honored, but also that the body is inevitably nothing more than a carcass, especially if its role as the temporary home of spirit and virtues is neglected. </p>
						<p n="42">However, Jonson disgustedly refuses <q direct="y">to stay</q> any <q direct="y">longer on these pictures</q> (l. 98). He refuses, that is, to pay them the attention they crave, just as he also refuses to pay them the attendance they expect. They may make legs to others, but he refuses to make any obeisance to them. For him they are simply <q direct="y">pictures</q> -- insubstantial images, the mere likenesses of real persons. Their <q direct="y">prosperitie mocks / The fate of things</q> in several typically complicated senses (ll. 100-01). First, they proudly, falsely assume that their material prosperity protects them against fate, which of course it cannot do. Their own mockery can and will be mocked -- as, indeed, it is in this poem. Moreover, while the word <q direct="y">things</q> might at first seem too vague or abstract to be exact, it is in fact precisely the right word to suggest the ultimately undistinguished, undifferentiated condition of mere matter. Despite all their pride and temporary triumph, the grandlings are things little different from the <q direct="y">things</q> they buy and wear. </p>
						<p n="43">Yet their triumph, though temporary, is a fact Jonson cannot and does not deny. (Denying it, of course, would make his poem unnecessary.) Instead, he ends with the haunting image of <q direct="y">totter'd vertue,</q> who <q direct="y">holds / Her broken Armes up, to their [the grandlings'] emptie moulds</q> (ll. 101-02). The reference to <q direct="y">broken Armes</q> is not only a powerful symbol of powerlessness but is also particularly appropriate to this poem, with its emphasis on military decadence. Just as he had earlier imagined humans as mere pictures, so here Jonson seems to imagine a concept or ideal (Virtue) as if it were a living, injured being. The final gesture of <q direct="y">vertue</q> -- holding up her broken arms -- can be interpreted variously as defiance, supplication, fear, or courage. Here as so often elsewhere, Jonson's famous <q direct="y">plain style</q> is anything but. Although the poem gives its literal last words to the grandlings, those words (<q direct="y">emptie moulds</q>) suggest lack of substance and eventual defeat. </p>
						<p n="44">Unfortunately, there seems no way of knowing whether Jonson, by the time he finished his poem, had also finished or even started his reading of Lipsius. What do seem clear, however, are the many ways in which the stoic politics championed by Lipsius meshed with Jonson's own political instincts. The passages Jonson marked in his copy of the <title level="m">Politics</title> suggest the same mentality responsible for a poem like the <q direct="y">
								<emph rend="italics">Speach according to</emph> Horace.</q> Lipsius provides an elaborate, explicit rationale for the attitudes the <q direct="y">
								<title level="m">Speach</title>
							</q> implies, and the same seems true of much of Jonson's writing from the Caroline period. Those attitudes seem to have been broadly moralistic rather than narrowly ideological: true ethical reformation (rather than mere constitutional tinkering) seem to have been at the heart of many of Jonson's political ideals. Appreciating Jonson's apparent sympathy with Lipsian political thinking can therefore also, perhaps, help us comprehend the principles that underlay Jonson's response to Charles, his opponents, and his reign. And comprehending these principles may, in turn, help us to a fuller appreciation of Jonson's Caroline art. </p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<p>
							<list>
								<head>>Notes</head>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn1">1. For fuller discussion of this matter see, for instance, Evans, <title level="m">Jonson, Lipsius, and the Politics of Renaissance Stoicism</title>, 35-36 and especially the works cited in note 8. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn2">2. For a full discussion of these matters, see Evans, <title level="m">Jonson, Lipsius, and the Politics of Renaissance Stoicism</title>. See also the articles by Evans in the anthology edited by James Hirsh; the article by Lynn Bryan and Evans; and the note by Probst and Evans. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn3">3. For discussions of Jonson and stoicism see, for instance, Hilberry, Maus, and McCanles (to name only a few possible sources). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn4">4. For a good recent survey of neostoic influence, see Salmon. See also the works cited in Evans, <title level="m">Jonson, Lipsius, and the Politics of Renaissance Neostoicism</title> (esp. at 1-27 and 339-49) and, also, the major new study by Andrea McCrea. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn5">5. See McPherson, esp. 26-27. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn6">6. See <title level="m">Ben Jonson</title>, ed. C. H. Herford and Percy and Evelyn Simpson, 11 vols. (Oxford: Clarendon Press, 1925-52), 11: 616. Hereafter this edition will be abbreviated as <q direct="y">H&amp;S.</q>
								</item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn7">7. On the issue of whether Jonson could read Greek, see McPherson, 17-18. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn8">8. Parenthetical page numbers, here and throughout, refer to the pages in Lipsius' <title level="m">Politics</title> on which specific passages appear. These pages are photographically reproduced in Evans, <title level="m">Jonson, Lipsius, and the Politics of Renaissance Stoicism</title> (275-338). William Jones' 1594 English translation is printed on pages 156-274 of the same book. Jones' translation has been reformatted to correspond exactly to the pagination of Jonson's Lipsius, so that page 23 of the <title level="m">Politics</title>, for instance, is also page 23 of the translation. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn9">9. For a much fuller discussion of this example, see the article by Probst and Evans. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn10">10. For the reader's convenience, I have capitalized the names of the Greek authors Jonson marked. <emph rend="italics">All</emph> the marked passages are underlined by him unless otherwise indicated. When Jonson's additional marking is particularly heavy or interesting, I have tried to indicate that in my comments within the body of this paper. For discussion and reproduction of Jonson's characteristic markings, see Evans, <title level="m">Jonson, Lipsius, and the Politics of Renaissance Stoicism</title>, 153-55 and 275-38. My parenthetical numbers refer to pages in Lipsius; for a fuller explanation, see endnote 8 above. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn11">11. Charles I, in one of his first significant proclamations, promised <q direct="y">the reformation &amp; redresse of any abuses in misgovernment, upon due knowledge &amp; examination thereof</q> (Larkin 2: 5). From time to time I will cite relevant passages from the proclamations Charles issued during the first year or so of his reign, since I will later discuss a poem written by Jonson near the end of that first regnal year. My purpose is to suggest a few of the potential points of contact between the thinking of Lipsius, Charles, and Jonson. For fuller discussion of this matter, see Evans, <title level="m">Jonson, Lipsius, and the Politics of Renaissance Stoicism</title>, 111-24 and 126-30. Hereafter I will refer to Charles' proclamations by citing <q direct="y">Larkin,</q> with appropriate volume and page numbers. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn12">12. In a proclamation dated 28 March 1625, Charles promised to <q direct="y">shew himselfe a most gracious and benigne Soveraigne Lord to all his good Subjects, in all their just and lawfull suites and causes</q> (Larkin 2: 3). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn13">13. In his first two proclamations, Charles repeatedly stressed the rights and duties of <q direct="y">all</q> his subjects (Larkin, 2: 3-5, <emph rend="italics">passim</emph>). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn14">14. In a proclamation dated 14 August 1625, Charles declared his <q direct="y">readinesse and constant resolution to maintaine the same true Religion professed, and by Law established within this Realme, and upon all occasions to suppresse the contrary</q> (Larkin 2: 53). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn15">15. In a proclamation dated 4 September 1625, Charles rebuked the <q direct="y">dissoluteness, and neglect of warlike discipline</q> in certain of his troops, arguing that <q direct="y">great danger to the service and imployment wherein they are placed, is manifestly threatned therby</q> (Larkin 2: 58-59). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn16">16. In a proclamation dated 14 August 1625, Charles praised the <q direct="y">true and hearty zeale and affection to Gods true Religion</q> of most of his subjects, and he commanded English Catholic seminarians living abroad to <q direct="y">submit themselves to his Majesties Lawes, and conforme themselves to live in such dutie and obedience as becommeth good Subjects</q> (Larkin 2: 53). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn17">17. The proclamation declaring Charles' accession (dated 27 March 1625) beseeched <q direct="y">God, by whom Kings doe Reigne</q> (Larkin 2: 2). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn18">18. In a proclamation dated 14 June 1626, Charles declared <q direct="y">His full and constant resolution, that neither in matter of Doctrine, or Discipline of the Church, nor in the government of the State, he will admit of the least innovation . . .</q> (Larkin 2: 91). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn19">19. In a proclamation dated 28 March 1625, Charles commanded <q direct="y">all persons of all estates, degrees and conditions, to see his peace duely kept, and to be obedient to his Lawes . . .</q> (Larkin 2: 3). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn20">20. In a proclamation dated 13 May 1625, Charles declared his intent that <q direct="y">there may be one uniforme course of Government, in, and through all Our whole Monarchie . . . </q> (Larkin 2: 28). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn21">21. In a proclamation dated 28 March 1625, Charles declared his expectation that his people would <q direct="y">in all cases shew themselves unto his Majestie, their naturall liege Lord, most loving, faithfull, and obedient Subjects, according to their most bounden duties and allegiances, whereby they shall please Almighty God, and doe that which shall tend to their owne preservations and safeties . . .</q> (Larkin 2: 3). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn22">22. I quote from the text printed in H&amp;S (8: 213-16). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn23">23. In a proclamation dated 26 May 1625, Charles, referring to his father's court, attacks the <q direct="y">disorder in and about his houshold, by reason of the many idle persons, and other unnecessary attendants following the same; Which evill, We, finding to bring much dishonour to Our House, have resolved the reformation thereof . . .</q> (Larkin 2: 37). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn24">24. In a proclamation dated 14 May 1625, Charles rebuked merchants whose <q direct="y">greedy desire of vnlawfull gaine, would never bee kept within any bounds of equall and reasonable Prices . . .</q> (Larkin 2: 30). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn25">25. In a proclamation dated 2 May 1625, Charles sought to restrain disorderly building in London; see Larkin 2: 21. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn26">26. In a proclamation dated 11 January 1626, Charles declared his resolution that the laws <q direct="y">concerning the confining of Popish Recusants, bee from hencefoorth duely observed, and that the offenders against the same shall incurre and receive those penalties and punishments which their high contempts deserve, and which by Our Lawes ought to be inflicted upon them</q>; see Larkin 2: 76. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn27">27. A proclamation dated 22 January 1626 emphasized that <q direct="y">his Majestiy himselfe in His owne Person did give a memorable example [of true repentence and humility] to all his people,</q> and that, thanks to such communal devotion, God had seen fit to lift the plague; see Larkin 2: 85. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn28">28. In a proclamation dated 14 May 1625, Charles had declared that his officials, <q direct="y">when, and as often as any complaint shall bee made unto them by any partie or parties, justly grieved or wronged</q> should <q direct="y">foorthwith . . . endeavour themselves to see speedy reformation thereof and due punishment of the person or persons that shall offend therein, according to the severest Justice of Our Lawes in that behalfe</q>; see Larkin 2: 31. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn29">29. See, for example, ll. 39-42 of the 1623 <q direct="y">
										<emph rend="italics">Tribe of</emph> BEN</q> epistle (H&amp;S 8: 218-20. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn30">30. On the immediate context of Jonson's poem in domestic politics and international relations, see Butler, esp. 287-91. See also, for instance, Gardiner, esp. 6: 8, 31-33, 36-37, 48-49, 56-57, 70-71, 86-89, 90-91, 96-97, and 114-15. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn31">31. In a proclamation dated 16 February 1627 (almost a year after the composition of Jonson's poem), Charles declared his desire <q direct="y">in all things to cary Our Selfe towards all Our Subjects with that Justice and moderation, as is fit for a just and a good King . . .</q> (Larkin 2: 129). Many of the proclamations issued <emph rend="italics">after</emph> the writing of Jonson's poem also suggest points of contact between the thinking of Lipsius, the king, and the poet. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn32">32. This point has recently been reiterated at length by McCanles. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn33">33. For another example of Charles' condemnations of greed, see his proclamation against embezzlement of war supplies, dated 25 December 1625 (Larkin 2: 69-70). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn34">34. Michael McCanles, in analyzing this poem, emphasizes how Jonson uses the work to distinguish himself both from corrupt nobles and from other middle-class aspirants and to advertise his own qualifications. McCanles sees the poem as implicitly endorsing <q direct="y">a true nobility defined by intellectual achievement. And Jonson knew just the man who could fill the bill</q> (129). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1evanjonsn35">35. See, for example, the following comment from Jonson's <title level="m">Discoveries</title>: <q direct="y">Looke upon an effeminate person: his very gate confesseth him. . . . The excesse of Feasts, and apparell, are the notes of a sick State; and the wantonesse of language, of a sick mind</q> (H&amp;S 8: 592-93). See also Huebert.</item>
							</list>
						</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>Works Cited</head>
						<p>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl>Bryan, Lynn, and Robert C. Evans. <title level="a">Ben Jonson, Neostoicism, and the <title level="m">Monita</title> of Justus Lipsius</title>. <title level="j">Ben Jonson Journal</title> 1 (1994): 105-24.</bibl>
								<bibl>Butler, Martin. <title level="a">The Dates of Three Poems by Ben Jonson</title>. <title level="j">Huntington Library Quarterly</title> 55 (1992): 279-93.</bibl>
								<bibl>Evans, Robert C. <title level="m">Jonson and the Contexts of His Time</title>. Lewisburg, PA: Bucknell UP, 1994.</bibl>
								<bibl>Gardiner, Samuel R. <title level="j">History of England from the Accession of James I to the Outbreak of Civil War, 1603-1642</title>. 10 vols. London: Longmans, Green, 1883-84.</bibl>
								<bibl>Hilberry, Clarence Beverly. <title level="m">Ben Jonson's Ethics in Relation to Stoic and Humanistic Ethical Thought</title>. Norwood, PA: Folcroft Library Editions, 1973.</bibl>
								<bibl>Hirsh, James, ed. <title level="m">New Perspectives on Ben Jonson</title>. Madison, NJ: Fairleigh Dickinson UP, 1997. </bibl>
								<bibl>Huebert, Ronald. <title level="a">A Shrew Yet Honest: Manliness in Jonson</title>. <title level="j">Renaissance Drama</title> 15 (1984): 31-68.</bibl>
								<bibl>---. <title level="a">Jonson, Lipsius, and the Latin Classics</title>. In <title level="m">New Perspectives on Ben Jonson</title>, ed. James Hirsh. Madison, NJ: Fairleigh Dickinson UP, 1997. 55-76.</bibl>
								<bibl>---. <title level="m">Jonson, Lipsius, and the Politics of Renaissance Stoicism</title>. 2d ed. Durango, CO: Longwood Academic, 1992.</bibl>
								<bibl>Jonson, Ben. <title level="m">Ben Jonson</title>. Ed. C.H. Herford and Percy and Evelyn Simpson. 11 vols. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1925-52.</bibl>
								<bibl>Larkin, James F., ed. <title level="m">Stuart Royal Proclamations, Volume II: Royal Proclamations of King Charles I, 1625-1646</title>. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1983.</bibl>
								<bibl>Maus, Katherine Eisaman. <title level="m">Ben Jonson and the Roman Frame of Mind</title>. Princeton: Princeton UP, 1984.</bibl>
								<bibl>McCanles, Michael. <title level="m">Jonsonian Discriminations: The Humanist Poet and the Praise of True Nobility</title>. Toronto: U of Toronto P, 1992.</bibl>
								<bibl>McCrea, Andrea. <title level="m">Constant Minds: Political Virtue and the Lipsian Paradigm in England, 1584-1650</title>. Toronto: U of Toronto P, 1998.</bibl>
								<bibl>McPherson, David. <title level="a">Ben Jonson's Library and Marginalia: An Annotated Catalogue</title>. <title level="j">Studies in Philology</title> 71.5 (1974): 3-106. </bibl>
								<bibl>Parfitt, George. <title level="a">History and Ambiguity: Jonson's 'A Speach according to Horace'</title>. <title level="j">Studies in English Literature</title> 19 (1979): 85-92.</bibl>
								<bibl>Probst, Neil, and Robert C. Evans. <title level="a">Jonson, Seneca, Homer, and Lipsius: Unreported Allusions in <title level="m">The King's Entertainment at Welbeck</title>
									</title>. <title level="j">Notes and Queries</title> 239.4 (1994): 519-20. </bibl>
								<bibl>Salmon, J. H. M. <title level="a">Seneca and Tacitus in Jacobean England</title>. In <title level="m">The Mental World of the Jacobean Court</title>, ed. Linda Levy Peck. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1991. 169-88.</bibl>
								<bibl>
									<title level="m">Webster's Biographical Dictionary</title>. Springfield, MA: Merriam, 1974.</bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<!--webbot bot="include" u-include="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/emls footer.html" tag="body" startspan -->
						</p>
						<p>[http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/EMLS footer.html]</p>
						<!--webbot bot="include" endspan i-checksum="20494" -->
						<byline>(RCE, LB, RGS, 27 February 1998)</byline>
					</div3>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls4-1heanshak" n="2" type="article">
					<!-- <img src="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/header2.gif" alt="early" modern literary studies width="283" height="87"> -->
					<head>Petruchio's Horse: Equine and Household Mismanagement in <title level="m">The Taming of the Shrew</title>
					</head>
					<opener>
						<name>Peter F. Heaney</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>Staffordshire University</addrLine>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href="mailto:p.f.heaney@staffs.ac.uk"> -->P.F.Heaney@staffs.ac.uk<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Heaney, Peter F. <title level="a">Petruchio's Horse: Equine and Household Mismanagement in <title level="m">The Taming of the Shrew</title>
						</title>. <title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 4.1 (May, 1998): 2.1-12 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/heanshak.html"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/heanshak.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;.</p>
					<div3>
						<p n="1">There are very few horses worth noting in the Shakespearean canon. There are plenty of horses, of course -- the plays are littered with them. But not many are singled out for attention. One recalls Richard III's memorably unavailable horse (V.iv.7), Richard II's much-mourned <q direct="y">roan Barbary</q> (V.v.78-94) -- Bolingbroke helped himself to Richard's favourite horse as well as his crown -- and the gift to Timon of <q direct="y">Four milk-white horses, trapp'd in silver</q> (I.ii.179-80). There is also Adonis' <q direct="y">trampling courser</q> which is rather more interested in Venus' <q direct="y">breeding jennet</q> than Adonis is in Venus. This is a splendid beast:<q type="block">
								<lg type="verse">
									<l>Round-hoof'd, short-jointed, fetlocks shag and long,</l>
									<l>Broad breast, full eye, small head and nostril wide,</l>
									<l>High crest, short ears, straight legs and passing strong,</l>
									<l>Thin mane, thick tail, broad buttock, tender hide:</l>
									<l>Look, what a horse should have he did not lack,</l>
									<l>Save a proud rider on so proud a back. (295-300)</l>
								</lg>
							</q> This horse does indeed have everything, which is more than can be said for his master. There are only two other horses worthy of mention. One is the Dauphin's <q direct="y">beast for Perseus</q> in <title level="m">Henry V</title>. The Dauphin does not descend to anything so base as mere description; his horse can be expressed only through the hyperbole of <q direct="y">pure air and fire . . . the dull elements of earth and water never appear in him</q>; and <q direct="y">When I bestride him, I soar, I am a hawk: he trots the air; the earth sings when he touches it</q> (III.vii.15.25). Alas, this most significant of horses, this <q direct="y">prince of palfreys,</q> fit for <q direct="y">a sovereign's sovereign to ride on,</q> worthy recipient of the sonnets his master addresses to him, is a mere <emph rend="italics">palfrey</emph>:<q direct="y">a saddle-horse, as distinguished from a war-horse, <emph rend="italics">esp.</emph> a small saddle-horse for ladies</q> (<title level="m">OED</title>). So much for the Dauphin's prowess in battle. Much space is given to this fatuous dialogue in the French camp, a necessary (patriotic) reassurance for the Elizabethan censor, possibly concerned at the over-bloody threats issued from the English camp a few minutes earlier. Talk from Henry of massacre of the old, rape of daughters, and <q direct="y">naked infants spitted upon pikes</q> is perhaps a little more palatable in the context of an enemy so degenerate that it has made its (male) horse its mistress. The Dauphin's horse, therefore, becomes a significant sign in the subversive web of <title level="m">Henry V</title>; we are invited to jeer at the Dauphin's foolish affection for his horse, but also to note the sickness of the English enterprise, as hinted at by the condition of <emph rend="italics">their</emph> horses (and also the English army): <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>The horsemen sit like fixed candlesticks,</l>
									<l>With torch-staves in their hand; and their poor jades</l>
									<l>Lob down their heads, dropping the hides and hips,</l>
									<l>The gum down-roping from their pale-dead eyes,</l>
									<l>And in their pale dull mouths the gimmal'd bit</l>
									<l>Lies foul with chaw'd grass, still and motionless . . . . (IV.ii.45-50)</l>
								</lg>
							</q>These lines are, of course, the hostile Grandpr&eacute;'s; but more significant is that they follow Henry's rout at the hands of Williams in the previous scene.<ref target="emls4-1heanshakn1">[1]</ref> The horses are not included for decorative purposes only. As elsewhere in Shakespeare, the reader has to pay attention to the text and any clues it might offer.</p>
						<p n="2">Such attention to metaphor<ref target="emls4-1heanshakn2">[2]</ref> (or, more accurately, perhaps, suggestion by analogy) in <title level="m">The Shrew</title> must lead the reader to Petruchio's horse. No Shakespearean horse, not even the Dauphin's, is given a fraction of the space devoted to this extraordinary creature. When Petruchio finally turns up, late, for his marriage to Katherine, he is (to borrow from <title level="m">King Lear</title>) <q direct="y">fantastically dressed.</q> This is as nothing to the state of his horse. Biondello, one of a number of pert lower-orders in the <title level="m">Shrew</title>, provides this preludary tour-de-force, to prepare the way for the great shrew-tamer general, Petruchio:<q type="block">Why, Petruchio is coming in a new hat and an old jerkin, a pair of old breeches thrice turned, a pair of boots that have been candle-cases, one buckled, another laced, an old rusty sword ta'en out of the town-armoury, with a broken hilt, and chapeless; with two broken points; his horse hipped -- with an old mothy saddle and stirrups of no kindred -- besides, possessed with the glanders and like to mose in the chine, troubled with the lampass, infected with the fashions, full of windgalls, sped with spavins, rayed with the yellows, past cure of the fives, stark spoiled with the staggers, begnawn with the bots, swayed in the back and shoulder-shotten, near-legged before, and with a half-cheeked bit and a head-stall of sheep's leather, which, being restrained to keep him from stumbling, hath been often burst and new-repaired with knots; one girth six times pieced, and a woman's crupper of velure, which hath two letters for her name fairly set down in studs, and here and there pieced with pack-thread. <ref target="emls4-1heanshakn3">[3]</ref>
							</q> Not surprisingly, all editors of the play have great fun explaining the animal's diseases. Shakespeare, one suspects, had been drinking deep with some of his farrier friends, and just had to show off his newly-acquired knowledge. It seems more likely, though, that he was offering a highly visible clue. To what? For all the space they devote to explaining the lampass, the glanders, the staggers and the bots (and the rest), editors fail to say what the <emph rend="italics">point</emph> of all this is. This is not just a sick horse; this horse is diseased on an epic scale. Thus, when the Arden edition reaches <q direct="y">like to mose in the chine,</q> the editor is happy to declare: <q direct="y">No-one knows what this means.</q> (226n)</p>
						<p n="3">It is worth giving these diseases just a little further scrutiny. Equine mismanagment on this scale should remind us -- as it may well have reminded at least some members of a contemporary audience -- of the growing interest in household management to be found in the late sixteenth century. Petruchio's wretched horse is a symptom of his master's cruel <emph rend="italics">mis</emph>management. The text invites us to make analogous connections between some of his unfortunate horse's (noticeably related) characteristics and several of Petruchio's own. <q direct="y">Glanders</q> is <q direct="y">a contagious disease in horses, the chief symptoms of which are swellings beneath the jaw and discharge of mucous matter from the nostrils</q> (<title level="m">OED</title>). <q direct="y">Mose in the chine</q> has much the same meaning, and <q direct="y">the lampass</q> causes swelling in the roof of the mouth. A similar affliction in the same region is <q direct="y">the fives,</q> which causes swelling behind the ear. For good measure, this equine wreck also suffers from the <q direct="y">fashions,</q> or farcy, which manifests itself in tumour-like growths, and <q direct="y">windgalls,</q> soft tumours or swellings on the fetlock, so called because they were thought to have contained air. The <q direct="y">spavins</q> is yet another disease resulting in swelling (in this case of the legs); <q direct="y">the staggers</q> is a distemper of the head, <q direct="y">a dizzy madness</q> (Markham, quoted by Morris, 228-9n). It seems unlikely that this passage is no more than a display of farrier-speak pyrotechnics: in the repetition of the various and manifold swellings, tumours and growths given to Petruchio's horse, there is a consistency, a coherence that denies the likelihood of mere accident. Is there not, at least, an analogical application of all this to the great Woman-Tamer himself? Does he not exhibit disease of the mouth? Is he not gifted, moreover, with the most outrageously inflated ego? On the first count, Petruchio is extraordinarily voluble: as Stevie Davies points out (6) he is given many more lines to speak than anyone else in the play: he has 564 lines to Katherine's 207, with everybody else having far fewer (for example Baptista has 160, Lucentio 153, and Bianca a mere 67). As to Petruchio's ego (not unrelated to his pursuit of power over words), it is monstrous, all-consuming, inflicted on all who conceivably might compete with him for authority or mastery.</p>
						<p n="4">This <q direct="y">condition</q> of Petruchio's should at the very least make one hesitate before endorsing the view that the <title level="m">Shrew</title> is four-square behind Petruchio's manic misogyny. Is his rabid patriarchalism role-play, or the product of a <q direct="y">disordered</q> mind? Petruchio is not, of course, insane; he is a man of <q direct="y">policy,</q> of calculation; but, as Jeanne Addison Roberts points out, <q direct="y">There [are] some overtones of the monster in Petruchio right from the start</q> (159-171). Grumio, who should know, declares to anyone who might help save his ears from destruction, <q direct="y">My master is mad</q> (I.ii.18). Katherine, even before the arrival of the stricken horse and its master, before the wedding, describes Petruchio as <q direct="y">a mad-brain'd rudesby</q> (III.ii.10); the sedate Gremio, in his account of the wedding, echoes the phrase, referring to Petruchio as the <q direct="y">mad-brain'd bridegroom</q> (III.ii.161). This <q direct="y">madness</q> and the violence that accompanies it may be seen to be a role played by Petruchio to gain the desired end -- the <q direct="y">taming</q> of Katherine. This is an argument put forward by Brian Morris in the Arden introduction (133-136). What Petruchio achieves, in this view, is a metamorphosis, a change wrought by educating Katherine out of her shrewishness. Jeanne Addison Roberts goes further, suggesting that Petruchio himself metamorphoses, is tamed: he <q direct="y">[gives] up his view of Katherine as goods and chattels or as his horse or his falcon . . .</q> (171). Neither position fully explains the sheer weight of equine decay that constitutes Petruchio's horse: if its body has a sound organ or limb, we are not told about it. Petruchio is characterised with similar consistency: he begins in manic mode and sustains his disorderly regime until he achieves the kind of <q direct="y">order</q> he requires.</p>
						<p n="5">The condition of Petruchio's horse directs our attention specifically to head and mouth, Petruchio's: ego and mouth. We are given a dose of both early in the play, when he casts himself as swashbuckling hero of the wars (unspecified), undaunted in the face of cannon and artillery (and, for good measure, the untamed beasts of the jungle):<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Think you a little din can daunt mine ears?</l>
									<l>Have I not in my time heard lions roar?</l>
									<l>Have I not heard the sea, puff'd up with winds,</l>
									<l>Rage like an angry boar chafed with sweat?</l>
									<l>Have I not heard great ordnance in the field,</l>
									<l>And heaven's artillery thunder in the skies?</l>
									<l>Have I not in a pitched battle heard</l>
									<l>Loud 'larums, neighing steeds, and trumpets' clang?</l>
									<l>And do you tell me of a woman's tongue,</l>
									<l>That gives not half so great a blow to hear</l>
									<l>As will a chestnut in a farmer's fire?</l>
									<l>Tush, tush, fear boys with bugs! (I.ii.198-209)</l>
								</lg>
							</q>This is jolly bombast, but also windy rhetoric, full of sound and fury. Those who see Petruchio as a player of roles (notably the cruel hawkmaster and servant-beater of Act IV), should remember that his characteristic violence and braggadocio are on show when no role is called for (see, for example, the attack on Grumio, referred to above). One of the symptoms of Petruchio's <q direct="y">condition</q> is an obsessive self-interest, a disorderly construct of the world (one which neglects all other concerns, individual and social). This can scarcely be called irrational, since it is firmly rooted in monstrously egotistical self-interest; when he arrives in Padua, he is prepared to marry any woman, if she is wealthy enough: <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Signior Hortensio, 'twixt such friends as we</l>
									<l>Few words suffice; and therefore, if thou know</l>
									<l>One rich enough to be Petruchio's wife,</l>
									<l>As wealth is burden of my wooing dance,</l>
									<l>Be she as foul as was Florentius' love,</l>
									<l>As old as Sibyl and as curst and shrewd</l>
									<l>As Socrates' Xanthippe, or a worse,</l>
									<l>She moves me not, or not removes, at least,</l>
									<l>Affection's edge in me, were she as rough</l>
									<l>As are the swelling Adriatic seas:</l>
									<l>I come to wive it wealthily in Padua;</l>
									<l>If wealthily, then happily in Padua. (I.ii.60-71)</l>
								</lg>
							</q> But to achieve this desirable end, Petruchio overturns all that might rationally be seen as <q direct="y">orderly</q> in the imposition of his own lunatic <q direct="y">order,</q> through a taming process which horrifies even the misogynist patriarchs of Padua. Violence, actual or threatened, is a symptom of this disorder, and is the basis of all his proceedings; even his wooing of Katherine does violence to language, meaning and truth (notably his inversion of all the information he has been given about Katherine). He makes it clear at the outset that he will use violence against Katherine if necessary: <q direct="y">I swear I'll cuff you if you strike again</q> (II.i.216). Petruchio's behaviour at the wedding is more than a <q direct="y">farcical exaggeration of normal masculine behaviour</q> (Kahn 109), it is the obverse of everything that bourgeois Padua expects of him; Gremio's account of the wedding, in tones of lip-smacking horror, describes Petruchio stamping, swearing at the priest and striking him, and throwing wine in the sexton's face (III.ii.147-173). Gremio concludes that Petruchio is <q direct="y">a devil, a very devil, the devil's dam,</q> and <q direct="y">Such a mad marriage never was before</q> (III.ii.146; 172). The violence continues when Petruchio carries Katherine off by main force (marital rape?), threatening death and destruction to anyone who gets in his way. It is scarcely plausible to argue that all this is merely role-play, part of Petruchio's <q direct="y">education</q> of Katherine.<ref target="emls4-1heanshakn4">[4]</ref> Rather, this extravagant violation of the quintessential symbol of social cohesion is consistent with earlier self-assertion: as noted above, our first encounter with Petruchio has him wringing Grumio's ears. It is consistent also with the <q direct="y">policy</q> he adopts when they return to Petruchio's country house. Here is more <q direct="y">disorder</q>: the master strikes and kicks his servants, wholesome food is thrown wantonly about, the natural functions of eating and sleeping are denied to Katherine, the conjugal bed made a place of disturbance and unrest.</p>
						<p n="6">Petruchio's <q direct="y">policy</q> of household mismanagement would not have been much favoured by contemporary humanist writers. As Lorna Hutson has shown, much was written in the sixteenth century about conjugal responsibilities within a wider context of household management. The writings of the Greek philosopher Xenophon were highly influential; amongst other works, his <title level="m">Oeconomicus</title> (<title level="m">The Science of Good Husbandry</title>), and <title level="m">Cyropaedia</title> (<title level="m">The Education of Cyrus</title>), were both translated into English in the sixteenth century. Essential to these studies is the representation of women and their role within marriage, together with advice to husbands on the organisation of their households, and the management of their wives. A repeated motif in these essays, sermons and books of domestic conduct is the correlation made between horse-training and wife-training. In Xenophon's <title level="m">Oeconomicus</title>, Socrates declares:<q type="block">I canne show you some men, the which have so used and ordered their wives, that they comfort and help them towards the increasyng of their house; and some that have such wives, the which utterly destroi the hous; and so for the moste part of men have . . . a horse, most commonly, if he be skittish, and doe some displesure, we blame the breker. And a wyfe likewise . . . if he do not teach hir, if she be rude, unwomanly, and wytles, is not he to be blamed? (qtd. Hutson 34)</q> Hutson argues that this <q direct="y">lesson</q> in <q direct="y">exemplarity</q> is directed rather at the man than the woman: <q direct="y">Exemplarity does not, after all, mean learning by example; it means <emph rend="italics">teaching</emph> by example</q> (34). If a woman is <q direct="y">wytles,</q> the blame is her husband's. What instruction is to be acquired from the <q direct="y">example</q> of Petruchio's horse? In the context of good husbandry, the wretched animal assumes a significance of Platonic proportions. Xenophon's <q direct="y">political romance</q>
							<ref target="emls4-1heanshakn5">[5]</ref>
							<title level="m">Cyropaedia</title>, the education of Cyrus the Great, founder of the Persian empire, insists on the value of kindness. (This kindness was to be extended not only to humans. Cyrus' army, according to Xenophon, followed him because they loved him, and because he fed and paid them; but it is to be offered also to horses.) In the <title level="m">Oeconomicus</title>, moreover, Socrates declares that a neglected horse cannot be called a <q direct="y">good,</q> since it will not be <q direct="y">beneficial to [his] master.</q>
							<ref target="emls4-1heanshakn6">[6]</ref> How, one is entitled to ask, did Petruchio's horse get like that? There is a further point to be made about Petruchio and horses. On the journey to his house after the travesty of a wedding, Katherine's horse falls, <q direct="y">in a miry place,</q> with Katherine under it. Her gallant knight, far from rescuing her, leaves her <q direct="y">with the horse upon her,</q> in order to beat his servant, Grumio. Katherine wades through the dirt to pluck Petruchio off. Is this incident also part of the grand design, the <q direct="y">policy</q>? Or merely another example of Petruchian incompetence? In all the many works of household management in this burgeoning genre, unskilful management is seen and condemned as profitless as well as foolish, a moral failure.</p>
						<p n="7">Erasmus, the great sixteenth-century humanist and commentator-instructor on household management (and marriage in particular), is often cited by those seeking evidence of sixteenth-century misogyny. Yet, in his <q direct="y">Colloquy</q> on marriage, he has things to say about domestic <q direct="y">mis-rule,</q> which have a direct bearing on Petruchio's taming <q direct="y">policy</q> (as stated in Act IV). This clearly offends against Erasmus' idea of domestic peace and order. Erasmus issues a severe warning against this violation:<q type="block">Above all, beware that you moove no brawles in chamber or in bedde: but bee carefull that there all things bee pleasaunt and merrie. For if that place which is consecrated to the putting away of all offences, and to the restoring of love, be profaned with strife and greefe, then all remedies of reconciliation are gone.<ref target="emls4-1heanshakn7">[7]</ref>
							</q> Who is the Shrew? Frances Dolan decides Petruchio is <q direct="y">a temporary shrew,</q> which seems over-generous. She is nearer the mark when she points to Petruchio's desecration of <q direct="y">chamber</q> and <q direct="y">bedde</q>: <q direct="y">Petruchio creates chaos in the two central locations of marriage, the sites of greatest intimacy and greatest risk</q> (Introduction 20). By flinging meat at the servants, and tearing the very bed asunder, Petruchio is continuing his reign of chaos, profaning the consecrated. There is more. His <q direct="y">rule</q> includes determining what Katherine is to wear, even the preference in clothes she is to have. Here, as in all Petruchio's dealings with Katherine, there is implicit violence, and violence also offered to the tailor, who cannot understand why an order placed, and words written, no longer have any meaning. But meaning is precisely what Petruchio has fractured: words do not mean what they have always meant, time changes as he decrees, and the sun is the moon when he so declares it to be. All this masterful nonsense is the world (forcibly) refashioned by Petruchio: <q direct="y">This gallant will command the sun,</q> remarks Hortensio to himself (IV.iv.188). It is scarcely a coincidence that words connoting madness in <title level="m">The Taming of the Shrew</title> occur so frequently;<ref target="emls4-1heanshakn8">[8]</ref> a world (Petruchio's) in which so much -- financially, socially, emotionally -- depends on the taming of one woman's spirit is one seriously (or farcically) out of joint.</p>
						<p n="8">Petruchio's seizure of the means of communication is an act of terrorism. Petruchio's monstrously inflated ego manifests itself in his first meeting with Katherine, the wit-bout in Act II, in which Petruchio's immediate assault, on a woman he has never met before, is itself a form of verbal rape:<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>
										<emph rend="bold">Pet</emph>. Good morrow, Kate; for that's your name, I hear.</l>
								</lg>
								<lg>
									<l>
										<emph rend="bold">Kath</emph>. Well have you heard, but something hard of hearing;</l>
									<l>They call me Katharine that do talk of me.</l>
								</lg>
								<lg>
									<l>
										<emph rend="bold">Pet</emph>. You lie, in faith; for you are call'd plain Kate,</l>
									<l>And bonny Kate and sometimes Kate the curst;</l>
									<l>But Kate, the prettiest Kate in Christendom,</l>
									<l>Kate of Kate Hall, my super-dainty Kate,</l>
									<l>For dainties are all Kates, and therefore, Kate,</l>
									<l>Take this of me, Kate of my consolation,</l>
									<l>Hearing thy mildness prais'd in every town,</l>
									<l>Thy virtues spoke of, and thy beauty sounded,</l>
									<l>Yet not so deeply as to thee belongs,</l>
									<l>Myself am mov'd to woo thee for my wife. (182-194)</l>
								</lg>
							</q>Petruchio bombards Katherine with the form of herself she has just denied him; he imposes upon her his heavily ironical character of her. His speech bounces and surges with the bombastic self-confident rhythms reserved for him in the play.<ref target="emls4-1heanshakn9">[9]</ref> The <title level="m">Shrew</title> is undeniably a play about mastery, specifically of language. There is indeed a <q direct="y">struggle . . . over possession of the word</q> (Davies 7). In this first meeting, with all the assurance of the <q direct="y">mad-brain'd</q> misogynist, Petruchio attempts to overwhelm Katherine, to drown her in a welter of words. Much of his first speech (above) is alliterative nonsense, designed to intimidate; some of it is offensive, sexually reductive -- Kate as <q direct="y">cate</q> = <q direct="y">dainty</q> (and therefore consumable), Katherine is his <q direct="y">consolation.</q> Katherine is not overwhelmed in this initial skirmish, but trades word for word, until Petruchio resorts to obscene innuendo (<q direct="y">my tongue in your tail</q> [216]), and the threat of violence. At the end of the skirmish, he returns to his initial barrage: <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>For I am he am born to tame you, Kate,</l>
									<l>And bring you from a wild Kate to a Kate</l>
									<l>Conformable as other household Kates. (269-271)</l>
								</lg>
							</q>Petruchio assaults her with <q direct="y">Kate</q> no fewer than twenty-eight times in this encounter; only twice is she allowed the <q direct="y">Katherine</q> she offers him. It is unremitting, sexual aggression; Katherine's character of Petruchio as <q direct="y">A madcap ruffian and a swearing Jack,/That thinks with oaths to face the matter out</q> (281-2), anticipates her later <q direct="y">mad-brain'd rudesby</q> (III.ii.10). Even before the analogy with the grotesque horse, Petruchio's <q direct="y">pathologically violent</q> linguistic inflation should remind the reader to give due respect to what the text is presenting (Davies 6). Words heaped up, as they are here, amount to something. There are other examples, such as the flamboyant act of piracy at the end of the wedding scene which is prefaced by a speech peppered with imperatives: <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Obey the bride . . .</l>
									<l>Go to the feast, revel and domineer,</l>
									<l>Carouse full measure to her maidenhead,</l>
									<l>Be mad and merry, or go hang yourselves . . . .</l>
									<l>Nay, look not big, nor stamp, nor stare, nor fret . . . .</l>
									<l>. . . Touch her whoever dare! (221-231)</l>
								</lg>
							</q>
						</p>
						<p n="9">Petruchio, typically, has the bit between his teeth (an appropriate metaphor). All this afflatus, moreover, is before the self-proclaimed <q direct="y">reign</q> has begun (see IV.i.175-198).<ref target="emls4-1heanshakn10">[10]</ref> Petruchio's language, and behaviour, are not only authoritarian, but are also larded with pompous pieties. <q direct="y">To me she's married, not unto my clothes</q> (III.ii.115), is bettered by an attack of proverbial wisdom in Act IV:<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Our purses shall be proud, our garments poor,</l>
									<l>For 'tis the mind that makes the body rich,<ref target="emls4-1heanshakn11">[11]</ref>
									</l>
									<l>And as the sun breaks through the darkest clouds,</l>
									<l>So honour peereth in the meanest habit. (IV.iii.168-171)</l>
								</lg>
							</q> This is empty platitude, part of Petruchio's endless web of words; it follows Katherine's explosion, after the provocation of the <q direct="y">lewd</q> and <q direct="y">filthy</q> hat: <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Why, sir, I trust I may have leave to speak,</l>
									<l>And speak I will. I am no child, no babe.</l>
									<l>Your betters have endur'd me say my mind,</l>
									<l>And if you cannot, best stop your ears.</l>
									<l>My tongue will tell the anger of my heart,</l>
									<l>Or else my tongue concealing it will break,</l>
									<l>And rather than it shall, I will be free</l>
									<l>Even to the uttermost, as I please, in words. (IV.iii.73-80)</l>
								</lg>
							</q>
						</p>
						<p n="10">Some recent<ref target="emls4-1heanshakn12">[12]</ref> post-feminist criticism of the play has taken particular account of sixteenth-century representations of women (in writings about 'domestic conduct'). The result has been a move away from the simplistic, angry reading of Charles Marovitz (see note 6, above -- <q direct="y">a detestable story about a woman who is brainwashed</q>), giving way to more <q direct="y">liberal</q> interpretations. Penny Gay is one of the latest of the former school. She maintains that the play has only been popular so long because it reinforces patriarchal prejudices: <q direct="y">The play enacts the defeat of the threat of a woman's revolt . . . [arguing] that the cruel treatment is for the victim's good, to enable her to become a compliant member of patriarchal society.</q>
							<ref target="emls4-1heanshakn13">[13]</ref> This approach is too simply dependent on plot and dramatic action -- the text itself is relegated from view. Too readily, such commentators on the play and the period quote their favourite misogynist gobbets from sixteenth-century writers on marriage and stand back as if the case is proved (Gay is not one of these). Because the scenario under scrutiny is cruelly patriarchal, Erasmus is quoted on patriarchal authority -- but his liberal-humanist ideas of equality within marriage are not. It should be of no great consequence that Bishop Aylmer<ref target="emls4-1heanshakn14">[14]</ref> had violent anti-woman tendencies, although it is certainly entertaining to quote what he had the temerity to say in a sermon before Gloriana herself:<q type="block"> Women are of two sorts: some of them are wiser, better learned, discreeter, and more constant than a number of men ; but another and worse sort of them are fond, foolish, wanton, flibbergibs, tattlers, triflers, wavering, witless, without council, feeble, careless, rash, proud, dainty, tale-bearers, eavesdroppers, rumour-raisers, evil-tongued, worse-minded, and in everyway doltified with the dregs of the devil's dunghill. (Stone 137)</q> Aylmer appears to have started with good intentions about being even-handed which did not last. There is no reason to assume, though, that this sort of misogyny was not resisted, contested, in at least some quarters; that the <title level="m">Shrew</title>, moreover, is not one of <q direct="y">countless instances of resistance to dominant discourses</q> (Traub 16). It is with the <q direct="y">discourse</q> of the text that commentators should engage. Another such <q direct="y">instance</q> is found in the work of Sir Thomas Smith, a sixteenth-century constitutional authority. In his <title level="m">De Republica Anglorum</title>, he makes plain the law of property as it applies to marriage and to the woman's possessions (which became her husband's, of course). But he also sets the law within a context that has a particular resonance for the <title level="m">Shrew</title>: <q type="block"> God hath given to the man great wit, bigger strength, and more courage to compell the woman to obey by reason or force: and to the woman, bewtie, a faire countenaunce, and sweete wordes to make the man to obey her againe for love. Thus ech obeyeth and commaundeth other, and they two togeather rule the house. The house I call here: the man, the woman, their children, their servants bond and free, their cattell, their household stuffe, and all other things, which are reckoned in their possession . . . . (Thomas Smith 23)</q>So much for Petruchio's <q direct="y">She is my goods, my chattels, she is my house,/My household stuff . . . my anything . . .</q> (III.ii.228-230). Petruchio's view of marriage is refuted even more forcefully by Henry Smith, a Puritan preacher well known in London in the 1590s: <q direct="y">[The husband] may not say as Husbands are wont to say, that which is thine is mine, and that which is mine is mine owne: but that which is mine is thine, and my selfe too.</q>
							<ref target="emls4-1heanshakn15">[15]</ref> But a half-awake reader will have no difficulty in recognising familiar symptoms in the manic verbosity of Petruchio's <q direct="y">chattels</q> speech: <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>I will be master of what is mine own.</l>
									<l>She is my goods, my chattels, she is my house,</l>
									<l>My household stuff, my field, my barn,</l>
									<l>My horse, my ox, my ass, my any thing,</l>
									<l>And here she stands. Touch her whoever dare! (III.ii.227-231)</l>
								</lg>
							</q>The irony of this piece of macho posturing lies in the forfeiting by Petruchio of his credit as the master of his <q direct="y">goods,</q> his household. And while the groundlings at a performance of the <title level="m">Shrew</title> at Shakespeare's Globe would no doubt have howled with glee at the woman-taming, there would also, equally doubtless, be some, who, having read their Xenophon, would have derived some entertainment from the sight of Petruchio as clown, <q direct="y">patched fool.</q>
							<ref target="emls4-1heanshakn16">[16]</ref>
						</p>
						<p n="11">Commentators are sharply divided about Katherine's speech at the end of the play, where she proclaims Petruchio to be her lord and master (V.ii.137-180). For Marovitz this speech is <q direct="y">redolent of the Moscow Trials . . . the haughty and independent creature we encountered in the first scenes [is] now transformed into a tame and docile domesticated lackey</q> (Marowitz 22). Lisa Jardine, on the other hand, suggests that Katherine's account of female indebtedness is deliberately over-blown, that it is Petruchio who is the dependent, on Katherine's fat dowry -- a truth brought home by this speech (60-1). Karen Newman is impressed by Katherine's sheer loquacity; <q direct="y">discourse is power</q> (46), and Katherine is given the last word, at length (this is easily the longest speech in the play). This is submission? In this speech, Katherine parades all the contemporary patriarchalisms:<q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Thy husband is thy lord, thy life, thy keeper,</l>
									<l>Thy head, thy sovereign; one that cares for thee,</l>
									<l>And for thy maintenance; commits his body</l>
									<l>To painful labour both by sea and by land,</l>
									<l>To watch the night in storms, the day in cold,</l>
									<l>Whilst thou liest warm at home, secure and safe . . . . (V.ii.147-152)</l>
								</lg>
							</q> Katherine has memorably captured the distemper that characterises Petruchio: Petruchio's tongue (Davies 41 [adapted and modified]). Given the opportunity by the word-spinner himself, she rises to the occasion, creating a monstrously-inflated vision of subjection. Here is slavery welcomed with enthusiasm! It is impossible not to be aware of the irony of all this, when one remembers the <q direct="y">warmth</q> and <q direct="y">security,</q> the <q direct="y">care</q> and maintenance Katherine has experienced over the previous few days. If this is submission, it is submission only to the realities of power in gender-relations: <q type="block">
								<lg>
									<l>Come, come, you froward and unable worms,</l>
									<l>My mind hath been as big as one of yours,</l>
									<l>My heart as great, my reason haply more,</l>
									<l>To bandy word for word and frown for frown.</l>
									<l>But now I see our lances are but straws,</l>
									<l>Our strength as weak, our weakness past compare . . . . (170-175)</l>
								</lg>
							</q> Katherine accepts that there is no future in taking arms against the prevailing power-structures, the entire patriarchal social order, especially when her lord and master's version of that order verges on the lunatic.<ref target="emls4-1heanshakn17">[17]</ref> There is Machiavellian <emph rend="italics">real-politik</emph> in this speech (and a shrewd perception of husband-management); when one couples the nature of that insight of Katherine's with the energy and relish of its delivery, it is difficult to see how an ironical reading can be resisted. And when Katherine offers to place her hand beneath Petruchio's foot, the humiliation is complete -- Petruchio's, not Katherine's. As Frances Dolan points out, this part of the wedding ritual had been officially prohibited for some forty years before the first production of the <title level="m">Shrew</title> (35). It is a devastating final blow; Petruchio is sufficiently disconcerted, for the only time in the play, to have nothing to say, beyond a feeble <q direct="y">There's a wench!</q> with the offer of a kiss.</p>
						<p n="12">This, then, is the lunatic husbandman Katherine's father is content to deliver her to, dowry and all. There is <emph rend="italics">no</emph> reason to assume that a sixteenth-century liberal-humanist would find Petruchio an acceptable son-in-law. If there is a degree of amusement to be derived from Petruchio's company -- and the male section of the audience at least would have to admit that there is -- it is of a similar kind to that accorded other carnivalesque Shakespearean figures, such as Falstaff, Lucio (<title level="m">Measure For Measure</title>) and Sir Toby Belch. Such as these are <q direct="y">licensed fools,</q> lords of misrule, who are given just enough rope, and no more, before their <q direct="y">rule</q> is terminated. Petruchio is cast in this mould. In his case, though, there is a difference: he also wields patriarchal authority in his anarchic grasp. Whereas Sir Toby's rule, for example, ends in bitterness, recriminations and a broken head, Petruchio's <q direct="y">licence</q> is not revoked, his taming programme is tolerated, though viewed with some discomfort even by patriarchal Padua. A more useful comparison, perhaps, is with Prince Hal, an equally successful Machiavellian. Like Petruchio, Hal engages with disorder as an integral part of <emph rend="italics">his</emph> policy; he exploits the Tavern crowd so that he can emerge from behind the <q direct="y">base contagious clouds</q> of his <q direct="y">loose behaviour</q> (I.ii.192-212), in sun-like majesty. However, the <q direct="y">order,</q> whether monarchical or patriarchal, thus established in both these plays is surely problematised. Hal's success as prince-in-waiting and as sun-king is shown to derive from his calm duplicity, an essential weapon of the successful monarch, Machiavelli's <q direct="y">novus Princeps.</q> Petruchio's methods are similarly problematic: they, like his horse, are grotesque. The horse is a living gargoyle, and its pathetic condition is symptomatic of its owner's monstrous and cruel mismanagement.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<p>
							<list>
								<head>Notes</head>
								<item id="emls4-1heanshakn1">1. Henry's defence of his <q direct="y">cause</q> is given short shrift by blunt Private Williams (see IV.i). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1heanshakn2">2. We have Jacques Derrida's authority for such attention. In his essay <q direct="y">White Mythology: Metaphor in the Text of Philosophy,</q> Derrida argues for the <emph rend="italics">usure</emph>, or accumulated force (with compound interest!) of metaphor: <q direct="y">How can we make this sensible except by metaphor? which is here the word <emph rend="italics">usure</emph>. In effect, there is no access to the usure of a linguistic phenomenon without giving it some figurative representation</q> (209). It is the contention of this essay that any reading of the <title level="m">Shrew</title> must give due weight to whatever leading is offered by the text. Petruchio's horse is a very powerful <q direct="y">leading.</q>
								</item>
								<item id="emls4-1heanshakn3">3. III.ii.41-61. All quotations from the <title level="m">Shrew</title> are from the Arden edition, ed. Brian Morris. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1heanshakn4">4. Amongst those who make a <q direct="y">literal</q> reading of Petruchio's methods are Alexander Leggatt and Charles Marovitz. Leggatt is evidently uneasy at what might be construed as cruelty, but nevertheless concludes: <q direct="y">The taming of Katherina is not just a lesson but a game -- a test of skill and a source of pleasure</q> (56). (Pleasure for whom, one might ask.) Marovitz, at the other end of the spectrum, is angrily indignant; the Shrew is <q direct="y">a detestable story about a woman who is brainwashed by a scheming adventurer as cruel as he is avaricious</q> (22). To see Katherine as brainwashed is to miss something. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1heanshakn5">5. So described by the Bishop of Hereford in his Introduction to the Everyman edition of Xenophon's <title level="m">Cyropaedia</title> (xii). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1heanshakn6">6. <title level="m">Complete Works</title> (646). Xenophon's concern that horses should be well-treated is a constant theme in his writing. See also his treatise <title level="m">On Horsemanship</title>, translated into English in 1584 (717-728). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1heanshakn7">7. One of the <title level="m">Colloquies</title>, <q direct="y">A Very Excellent Dialogue betweene a good Woman and a Shrew</q> [1523] (13). One of Erasmus' speakers in this <q direct="y">dialogue</q> presents the orthodox position on male authority etc., in marriage. The other -- the Shrew -- is given a powerful case, her grievances are substantial, and are aired at length: <q type="block">
										<q direct="y">When he cometh home drunke at midnight, he lieth snorting all night, and many times he berayeth his bed with vomiting . . . I vow I would I were hanged if I had not rather lie with a sow that hath pigges than with such a husband . . . . </q> (2)</q>
									<q type="block"> . . . </q>
									<q direct="y">Unhappy is the state of wives, if they must be obedient and diligent to please their husbands that are angry, drunke, and given to all naughtinesse. (9)</q> Erasmus' Shrew is given spirit as well as cause. Asked how she reacts to a tale of blatant infidelity in a husband, she explodes: <q type="block">If I had been his wife, I would have flowne in his beloveds face, and torne her haire off her head, and when he had gone out to dinner or supper with her, I would have crowned him with a pis-pot, so that he might have gone anointed to his banquet . . . . (12)</q>It is interesting to consider the likely readership of this piece -- especially in the original Latin. Even the voice of gentle orthodoxy in this dialogue is prepared to acknowledge <q direct="y">Here is a time when a woman may in good earnest admonish her husband, if it bee in a weightie matter</q> (14). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1heanshakn8">8. Of the comedies, only <title level="m">Twelfth Night</title>, where Malvolio is incarcerated for alleged madness in a conspiracy against him, and <title level="m">The Comedy of Errors</title>, the plot of which hinges on endless mistaken identities, have more. These two, like <title level="m">The Taming of the Shrew</title>, make <q direct="y">madness</q> a central motif. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1heanshakn9">9. This manic, Pythonesque quality is the hallmark of John Cleese's performance for the BBC television production, directed by Jonathan Miller (1980). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1heanshakn10">10. The point is that all this verbiage can scarcely be designated part of Petruchio's proclaimed grand design of taming Katherine, since -- he declares -- that has its beginning when the happy couple return to Petruchio's house in Verona. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1heanshakn11">11. This is rich indeed from one who has just acquired a hefty dowry. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1heanshakn12">12. See, for example, Frances Dolan (ed.), and Emily Detmer. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1heanshakn13">13. Gay (86). Gay doubts if the <title level="m">Shrew</title> would still be performed if it didn't have Shakespeare's name attached to it. That is also Stevie Davies' view. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1heanshakn14">14. John Aylmer (1521-94), consecrated Bishop of London, 1577 (<title level="m">DNB</title>). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1heanshakn15">15. Henry Smith (67). Kate Aughterson, in her collection of extracts <title level="m">Renaissance Woman</title>, includes parts of this sermon appropriate to her thesis on patriarchal gender constructions, but omits this bit. Juliet Dusinberre, while otherwise more balanced in her reading of contemporary commentators, also makes no mention of this comment. </item>
								<item id="emls4-1heanshakn16">16. As Bottom would have it (<title level="m">A Midsummer Night's Dream</title>, IV.i.208). </item>
								<item id="emls4-1heanshakn17">17. John Knox was not known for his advocacy of <q direct="y">the regiment of women</q>; however, he would not have found Petruchio's reign too palatable either: <q direct="y">Who can deny that it repugneth to nature . . . that the foolish, mad and frenetic shall govern the discreet . . . ?</q> (9). Katherine cannot be described as <q direct="y">discreet</q> whereas Petruchio, on the other hand, might well be described as <q direct="y">foolish, mad and frenetic.</q>
								</item>
							</list>
						</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>Works Cited</head>
						<p>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl>Aughterson, Kate, ed. <title level="m">Renaissance Woman</title>. London: Routledge, 1995.</bibl>
								<bibl>Davies, Stevie. <title level="m">The Taming of the Shrew</title>. London, Harmondsworth: Penguin Critical Studies, 1995.</bibl>
								<bibl>Derrida, Jacques. <title level="a">White Mythology: Metaphor in the Text of Philosophy</title>. In <title level="m">Margins of Philosophy</title>. Trans. Alan Bass. London: Harvester Wheatsheaf, 1982. 207-271.</bibl>
								<bibl>Detmer, Emily. <title level="a">Civilising Subordination: Domestic Violence in <title level="m">The Taming of the Shrew</title>
									</title>. <title level="j">Shakespeare Quarterly</title> 48.3 (1997): 273-295.</bibl>
								<bibl>Dusinberre, Juliet. <title level="m">Shakespeare and the Nature of Women</title>. London: Macmillan, 1975.</bibl>
								<bibl>Erasmus, Desiderius. <title level="a">Utile Dulce: A Very Excellent Dialogue betweene a good Woman and a Shrew</title>. Trans. William Burton, London, 1606. Amsterdam: Theatrum Orbis Terrarum; New York: Da Capo P, 1973: 1-17.</bibl>
								<bibl>Gay, Penny. <title level="m">As She Likes It: Shakespeare's Unruly Women</title>. London: Routledge, 1994.</bibl>
								<bibl>Hutson, Lorna. <title level="m">The Usurer's Daughter: Male Friendship and Fictions of Women in Sixteenth-Century England</title>. London: Routledge, 1994.</bibl>
								<bibl>Jardine, Lisa. <title level="m">Still Harping on Daughters</title>.  London: Harvester Wheatsheaf, 1983.</bibl>
								<bibl>Kahn, Coppelia. <title level="m">Man's Estate: Masculine Identity in Shakespeare</title>. Los Angeles and London: U of California P, 1981.</bibl>
								<bibl>Knox, John . <title level="a">The First Blast of the Trumpet Against the Monstrous Regiment of Women</title>. In <title level="m">On Rebellion</title>. Ed. Roger A. Mason. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1994: 3-48.</bibl>
								<bibl>Leggatt, Alexander. <title level="m">Shakespeare's Comedy of Love</title>. London: Methuen &amp; Co., 1984.</bibl>
								<bibl>Markham, Gervase. <title level="m">How to Choose</title>, <title level="m">Ride, Train, and Diet both Hunting Horses and Running Horses . . . . Also a Discourse of Horsemanship</title>. London, 1593.</bibl>
								<bibl>Marovitz, Charles. <title level="m">Recycling Shakespeare</title>. Basingstoke and London: Macmillan, 1991.</bibl>
								<bibl>Newman, Karen. <title level="a">Renaissance Family Politics and Shakespeare's <title level="m">The Taming of the Shrew</title>
									</title>. <title level="m">Shakespeare's Comedies</title>. Ed. Gary Waller. London and New York: Longman, 1991. 39-55.</bibl>
								<bibl>Roberts, Jeanne Addison. <title level="a">Horses and Hermaphrodites: Metamorphoses in <title level="m">The Taming of the Shrew</title>
									</title>. <title level="j">Shakespeare Quarterly</title> 34 (1983): 159-171.</bibl>
								<bibl>Shakespeare, William. <title level="m">The Taming of the Shrew</title>. Ed. Brian Morris. London and New York: Methuen, 1981.</bibl>
								<bibl>---.<title level="m"> The Taming of the Shrew</title>, <title level="m">Texts and Contexts</title>. Ed. Frances Dolan. Boston, New York: Bedford Books of St Martin's P, Macmillan Press Ltd, 1996.</bibl>
								<bibl>---. <title level="m">The Taming of the Shrew</title>. Ed. H. J. Oliver. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1982.</bibl>
								<bibl>---. <title level="m">The Taming of the Shrew</title>. Ed. G. R. Hibbard. Harmondsworth: Penguin Books, 1968.</bibl>
								<bibl>Smith, Henry. <title level="m">A Preparative to Mariage</title>. London, 1591. New York: Walter J. Johnson Inc., Theatrum Orbis Terrarum, Ltd., 1975.</bibl>
								<bibl>Smith, Thomas. <title level="m">De Republica Anglorum</title> [<title level="m">A Discourse on the Commonwealth of the English</title>]. Ed. L. Alston. Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1906.</bibl>
								<bibl>Stone, Lawrence. <title level="m">The Family, Sex and Marriage in England 1500-1800</title>. Harmondsworth: Penguin Books, 1979.</bibl>
								<bibl>Traub, Valerie. <title level="m">Desire and Anxiety: Circulations of Sexuality in Shakespearean Drama</title>. London: Routledge, 1992.</bibl>
								<bibl>Xenophon. <title level="m">Oeconomicus</title>, and <title level="m">The Art of Horsemanship</title>, in <title level="m">Complete Works</title>. Trans. Ashley, Spelman, Smith, Fielding et al. Edinburgh: William P. Nimmo, 1877.</bibl>
								<bibl>---. <title level="m">Cyropaedia</title>. Trans. H.G. Dakyns. London: Dent, 1914.</bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<!--webbot bot="include" u-include="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/emls footer.html" tag="body" startspan -->[http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/EMLS footer.html]<!--webbot bot="include" endspan i-checksum="20494" -->
						</p>
						<byline>(PH, LB, RGS, 2 April 1998)</byline>
					</div3>
				</div2>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="issuesection">
				<head>Note</head>
				<div2 id="emls4-1fitzspen" n="3" type="notearticle">
					<!-- <img src="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/header2.gif" alt="early" modern literary studies width="283" height="87"> -->
					<head>
						<q direct="y">Corrupt with goodly meede</q>: Munera and Medusa in Book 5 of Spenser's <title level="m">The Faerie Queene</title>
					</head>
					<opener>
						<name>Joan Fitzpatrick</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>Shakespeare Institute</addrLine>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href="mailto:j.fitz@mcmail.com"> -->j.fitz@mcmail.com<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Fitzpatrick, Joan. <title level="a">
							<q direct="y">Corrupt with goodly meede</q>: Munera and Medusa in Book 5 of Spenser's <title level="m">The Faerie Queene</title>
						</title>. <title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 4.1 (May, 1998): 3.1-7 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/fitzspen.html"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/fitzspen.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;.</p>
					<div3>
						<p n="1">In Book 5 canto 2 of Spenser's <title level="m">The Faerie Queene</title> lawless corruption is gendered and sexualized in the figure of Munera. She is the daughter of the villain Pollente who, with his groom Guizor, robs and kills anyone who wishes to pass over his bridge. Munera receives the stolen goods from her father and this corruption is symbolized by her golden hands and silver feet which <q direct="y">sought vnrighteousnesse, and iustice sold</q> (5.2.26.8).<ref target="emls4-1fitzspenn1">[1]</ref> When she realises that she is to be punished for her actions Munera attempts to bribe Talus, the iron man who serves Artegall, with gold. Before killing her, Talus cuts off Munera's hands and feet, destroys the stolen gold she has received from her father and sets fire to their castle. Considering Spenser's interest in classical mythology, outlined in Henry Gibbons Lotspeich's <title level="m">Classical Mythology in the Poetry of Edmund Spenser</title>, it is probable that Munera has a classical antecedent: Medusa, the once beautiful woman turned monster of Greek mythology who suffered decapitation at the hands of Perseus. </p>
						<p n="2">Given her deeds, Munera's name appears to come from the Latin plural noun <emph rend="italics">munera</emph> (gifts) and because of thematic links many critics have identified Munera with Langland's corrupt Lady Meed.<ref target="emls4-1fitzspenn2">[2]</ref> The full extent of the meed/Munera connection has not, however, been hitherto explored. The OED records the use of <emph rend="italics">meed</emph> as early as the tenth century to denote <q direct="y">That which is bestowed in requital of labour or service, or in consideration of (good or ill) desert; wages, hire; recompense, reward</q> (OED meed <emph rend="italics">sb</emph>. 1). It also carries a more specifically negative meaning of <q direct="y">Reward dishonestly offered or accepted; corrupt gain; bribery,</q> which was in use from the fourteenth century (OED meed <emph rend="italics">sb</emph>. 2). Spenser used the word <emph rend="italics">meed</emph>, spelt <emph rend="italics">meede</emph>, throughout <emph rend="italics">The Faerie Queene</emph> to denote reward in general but in the Munera episode <emph rend="italics">meede</emph> and its plural <emph rend="italics">meedes</emph> is used in the more specific sense of corrupt reward. The OED records yet another variant spelling, <emph rend="italics">mede</emph>, in use from the twelfth to the seventeenth century. This last form is a homograph of a completely different word, <emph rend="italics">Mede</emph>, recorded in the OED as denoting a native or inhabitant of Media (OED Mede <emph rend="italics">sb</emph>. 1). There are good reasons to believe that the polysemous associations evoked by <emph rend="italics">mede</emph> were exploited by Spenser in the Munera episode. </p>
						<p n="3">The Medians established an empire in Media in Persia in the seventh century BC. The word <emph rend="italics">Mede</emph>, denoting one of these people, derives from the Latin word <emph rend="italics">Medus</emph> which was the name of the eponymous hero of the Medes, son of Aegeus and Medea (Oxford Latin Dictionary Medus<emph rend="superscript">2</emph>), and which also meant <q direct="y">Of or belonging to the Medes, Median</q> (Oxford Latin Dictionary Medus<emph rend="superscript">1</emph>).</p>
						<p n="4">In <emph rend="italics">The Faerie Queene</emph> the epithet 'Persian' is used by Spenser to describe the great wealth and luxury associated with the enemies of Christian knights. For example Duessa wears what looks like <q direct="y">a <emph rend="italics">Persian</emph> mitre on her hed</q> (1.2.13.4); Lucifera's court is so sumptuous that <q direct="y">In liuing Princes court none euer knew / Such endlesse richesse, and so sumptuous shew; / Ne <emph rend="italics">Persia</emph> selfe, the nourse of pompous pride / Like euer saw</q> (1.4.7.4-7); Malecasta sits on <q direct="y">a sumptuous bed, / That glistred all with gold and glorious shew, / As the proud <emph rend="italics">Persian</emph> Queenes accustomed</q> (3.1.41.2-4). Spenser's Persian figures are antithetical to Christianity and their affluence denotes dishonest reward. When Spenser evoked Persians it was invariably in the context of excess and corruption. His Persian protagonists use their wealth and luxury to attempt the seduction of good Christian knights throughout the poem. Munera and her father Pollente are corrupt in just such a Persian way: Munera receives stolen riches from her father and attempts to use her wealth in order to seduce Talus, a just figure. </p>
						<p n="5">The classical figure who provides the bridge between Spenser's general anti-Persian characterizations and the concrete person of Munera is Medusa, the Gorgon in Greek mythology. Although it is not clear how much of his classical learning was acquired via ancient languages and how much via English, Spenser's knowledge of the classics is undisputed (Steadman 587). There are strong thematic links between Munera and Medusa. Both women are beautiful; Munera is <q direct="y">full faire</q> (5.2.10), she has <q direct="y">faire lockes,</q> a <q direct="y">goodly hew</q> (5.2.25), and a <q direct="y">sclender wast</q> (5.2.27). Similarly Medusa, before she is transformed by Minerva, is described as a great beauty in Ovid's <title level="m">Metamorphoses</title>: <q direct="y">She was once most beautiful in form, and the jealous hope of many suitors. Of all her beauties, her hair was the most beautiful</q> (Ovid 4.793-95). Both women are seducers. The attractive Munera attempts to seduce using wealth (<q direct="y">She ment him to corrupt with goodly meede</q> [5.2.23]), and Medusa has been punished by Minerva for her lack of chastity: <q direct="y">'Tis said that in Minerva's temple Neptune, lord of the Ocean, ravished her</q> (Ovid 4.797-98). Both women have unnatural, prodigious body parts: Munera's hands and feet are made of metal and Medusa's hair consists of snakes. Both are associated with cold, hard, natural but inorganic materials: Munera with gold and silver, Medusa with the stone into which she transforms any man who looks upon her. But perhaps the most striking link between the two figures is that found in Apollodorus's version of the Medusa story where the Gorgons are said to have <q direct="y">heads twined about with the scales of dragons, and great tusks like swine's, and <emph rend="italics">brazen hands</emph>, and golden wings, by which they flew; and they turned to stone such as beheld them</q> (Apollodorus 2.4.2; my emphasis). </p>
						<p n="6">Available to Spenser was yet another meaning for <emph rend="italics">Mede</emph>: <q direct="y">a precious stone described by ancient writers, said to be found in Media</q> (<emph rend="italics">sb</emph>. 2). Duessa and Lucifera, associated by Spenser with Persian excess, are surrounded by precious stones and metals. Both Munera and Medusa have precious extremities yet whilst the latter changes others into stone Munera is apparently a victim, not an agent, of petrifaction. The visceral power of their stories depends on revulsion of the substitution of hard inorganic matter for flesh. </p>
						<p n="7">The construction of both figures reveals an anxiety towards female beauty and its perceived capacity for inflicting harm which appears to be focused on the metamorphosis of flesh. Typical of his eclecticism, it seems that Spenser used details from the legend of Medusa in his construction of Munera. She is a Medusa figure, a beautiful woman with the power to corrupt and destroy men. Both Munera and Medusa can be linked with <emph rend="italics">mede</emph> (reward) and the place Media, in Persia, which symbolizes the East and the non-Christian, the infidel.</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<p>
							<list>
								<head>Notes</head>
								<item id="emls4-1fitzspenn1">1. Quotations of the poem are from Spenser (Hamilton, ed.).</item>
								<item id="emls4-1fitzspenn2">2. For example see Spenser ([Gough, ed.], 176); Hough (194);Spenser ([Hamilton, ed.] 526) and Heale (481).</item>
							</list>
						</p>
					</div3>
					<div3>
						<head>Works Cited</head>
						<p>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl>Apollodorus. <title level="m">The Library</title>. Vol. 1. Trans. James George Frazer. 2 vols. London: William Heinemann, 1921.</bibl>
								<bibl>Glare, P.G.W., ed. <title level="m">Oxford Latin Dictionary</title>. 2 vols. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1976.</bibl>
								<bibl>Heale, Elizabeth. <title level="a">Munera</title>. <title level="m">The Spenser Encyclopedia</title>. Ed. A.C. Hamilton. Toronto: U of Toronto P, 1990. 481.</bibl>
								<bibl>Hough, Graham. <title level="m">A Preface to</title> The Faerie Queene. London: Gerald Duckworth, 1962.</bibl>
								<bibl>Lotspeich, Henry Gibbons. <title level="m">Classical Mythology in the Poetry of Edmund Spenser</title>. Princeton: Princeton UP, 1932.</bibl>
								<bibl>Ovid. <title level="m">Metamorphoses</title>. Vol. 1. Trans. Frank Justus Miller. 2 vols. London: William Heinemann, 1916.</bibl>
								<bibl>Spenser, Edmund. <title level="m">The Faerie Queene</title>. Ed. A.C. Hamilton. London: Longman, 1977.</bibl>
								<bibl>---. <title level="m">The Faerie Queene Book V</title>. Ed. Gough, Alfred B. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1918.</bibl>
								<bibl>Steadman, John M. <title level="a">Spenser's Reading</title>. <title level="m">The Spenser Encyclopedia</title>. Ed. A.C. Hamilton. Toronto: U of Toronto P, 1990. 587.</bibl>
							</listBibl>[http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/EMLS footer.html]<!--webbot bot="include" endspan i-checksum="20494" -->
						</p>
					</div3>
					<!--webbot bot="include" u-include="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/emls footer.html" tag="body" startspan -->
					<byline>(JF, LB, RGS, 9 April 1998)</byline>
				</div2>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="issuesection">
				<head>Reviews</head>
				<div2 id="emls4-1revjoh3" n="4" type="review">
					<head>John Peacock. <title level="m">The Stage Designs of Inigo Jones: The European Context.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1995. 387 pp. + 195 plates. ISBN 0 521 418127 Cloth.</head>
					<!--<img src="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/header2.gif" alt="early" modern literary studies width="283" height="87"> -->
					<opener>Review by <name>A.W. Johnson</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>&Aring;bo Akademi University</addrLine>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href="mailto:anthony.johnson@abo.fi"> -->anthony.johnson@abo.fi<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Johnson, A.W. <title level="a">Review of <title level="m">The Stage Designs of Inigo Jones: The European Context</title>
						</title>. <title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 4.1 (May, 1998): 4.1-9 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/rev_joh3.html"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/rev_joh3.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;.</p>
					<p n="1">It is now almost twenty-five years since the quadricentennial festivities which revivified the reputation of Inigo Jones. In 1973,<title level="m"> The King's Arcadia</title> -- spearheaded by John Harris, Stephen Orgel and Roy Strong -- swept aside many of the older, duller, assumptions which had straight-jacketed Jones in the mould of Palladian/Scamozzian architect and copyist, replacing them with a new and less reductive picture. Jones, as the exhibition catalogue made plain, had occupied a central position in the Jacobean and Caroline cultural scene -- not only as an architect but also as a painter, collector, connoisseur, neo-Platonist, art theorist, fashion designer and masque maker. His sources had been plural: his achievement, manifold. Nor was such a verdict supported by the exhibition alone, for the almost simultaneous appearance of Orgel and Strong's two volume edition, <title level="m">Inigo Jones: The Complete Court Masques,</title> shored up their subject's reputation as a major artist and scenic designer at the same time as it helped to promote a revival of interest in masque as a genre. After Orgel and Strong, Jones's stage architecture could never again be simply written off (<emph rend="italics">pace</emph> John Summerson in the 1960s) as <q direct="y">nonsense architecture,</q>
						<q direct="y">in the proper dominion of nonsense.</q> The masque had come to be understood as a major site for cultural negotiation -- and Jones's work had become its clearest, as well as its most fully documented, <emph rend="italics">exemplum</emph>.</p>
					<p n="2">Since that time, Jonesian scholarship has blossomed on a variety of fronts. Most notably, following John Newman's meticulous charting of chronological changes in Jones's handwriting, it became possible -- as Gordon Higgott and John Harris demonstrated in their edition of <title level="m">The Complete Architectural Drawings</title> -- to map out at least some of the contours of his intellectual development from a reading of the annotated volumes from his library and to correlate the results with the dated architectural and scenic designs. In this way Jones's collection of (mainly) Italian books, as well as his drawings, began to emerge as significant witnesses not only to the range of his borrowing and adaptation, but also as indices to the moments of cultural transmission in which he did so. And accordingly -- as my own doctoral transcriptions of Jones's annotated Vasari, Plato and 1614 Plutarch attempted to show -- the 1980s offered researchers the possibility of a new synergy in Jones studies: an approach which promised to transcend the monocularities of scholarship within the various specialized fields of Jones's creative output and gestured towards a more unified view of his achievement as a whole.</p>
					<p n="3">That such a promise has taken so long to be fulfilled is no doubt due in the main to the formidable difficulties involved in conducting interdisciplinary studies. John Peacock -- as a Lecturer in English Literature with some twenty years' experience of writing on Jones for the art journals -- is well qualified to undertake such a task; yet nevertheless it is something of a tribute to his abilities that <title level="m">The Stage Designs of Inigo Jones</title> manages to bring together the diversity of Jones's achievement with such apparent ease, forming a whole which is much greater in scope than the sum of its parts. Peacock's method is simple, moving in successive chapters through discussions of Jones's relation to the theory and practice of imitation; to the masques as pictures; to architecture; to figures; and on to ornament and antiquity. But it is also strategic. For unlike architectural historians such as Andor Gomme -- who do not seem to consider scenography, for instance, to lie within the bounds of architecture proper -- Peacock is at pains to show how Jones constructed a theory and praxis which pre-empted such divisiveness and unified his endeavour throughout the whole spectrum of his activities. Hence he reminds his readers that Vitruvius had <q direct="y">treated stage design as a part of architecture</q> (56), and that, for Jones -- via a reading of Daniele Barbaro's commentary on Vitruvius -- <emph rend="italics">sc&aelig;nographia</emph> is therefore <q direct="y">not only a province of architecture, and an essential preparation for the architect, it is a fundamental element of architectural design</q> (58). Hence, too, he is able to stress -- from Jones's annotations to Vasari -- that, in practice, <q direct="y">stage design is to be included among the<emph rend="italics"> arti del disegno</emph>
						</q> (50). In this way Jones's fragmentary writings, along with the sketches and drawings, become a kind of unofficial substitute for the more systematic <q direct="y">
							<emph rend="italics">cours d'architecture</emph>
						</q> of the European tradition (112). And correspondingly, <title level="m">The Stage Designs of Inigo Jones</title> is able to break through into a new, more integrated, reading of the intellectual biography of its subject.</p>
					<p n="4">Before descending, however, into the detailed consideration of Jones's visual imagination which fills out the body of the book, Peacock uses Jones's marginalia as an entr&eacute;e into the vexed question of the latter's approach to the theory and practice of imitation. In paraphrase of Vasari, Jones had noted that <q direct="y">gudd / manner coms by Copii/nge ye fayrest thinges</q>; and Peacock -- having registered a tension between Newman's praise of Jones's <q direct="y">copying</q> and Strong's attack on it -- opts for the more affirmative approach. Where for Gauguin (cited as an epigraph to the first chapter), <q direct="y">L'artiste sera ou plagiaire ou r&eacute;volutionnaire</q> (6), Peacock's Jones emerges as something of a revolutionary plagiarist, or (to put it less pejoratively), as a revolutionary synthesist. Since, for Jones, <q direct="y">imitativeness is a philosophical receptiveness</q> (27), he is content to commit himself to <q direct="y">a lifetime of imitation</q> (32): importing his images from their predominantly French and Italian source cultures through what amounted to <q direct="y">a campaign of grand larceny</q> (13). And since the tastes of his English clientele were, for the most part, unaccustomed to the nuances of the traditions from which such images were borrowed, Jones's function as imitator was supplemented to a large extent by his necessary (and significant) role as a cultural mediator and educator.</p>
					<p n="5">The richness of the book's central chapters is testimony enough to the fecundity of such an approach. As a counterpoise to over-literary <q direct="y">Jonsonian</q> representations of masque as a form, for example, the Jonesian masque is used as a means of tracing out phases in the visual development of the English imagination: from emblematic tableau, to picture, to the landscapes and self-referential architectural scenery of the pastorals or the late masques -- bounded by ornamented proscenia which stand as majestic <q direct="y">frontispieces</q> to the whole (259). Nor are these moves perceived in terms of oversimplified linearities. Even within a relatively restricted topic such as Jones's reinvention of the Satyric Scene, Peacock emphasises how Jones sought to reconcile opposing tensions from his inherited tradition: working the pictorial inspiration of, say, Tempesta and Bril into viable stage sets; or conversely, but equally successfully, adapting preformed scenes (such as those of Parigi) in order to render them more pictorial (192). It is an argument which is supported -- as elsewhere in the volume -- by a generous supply of photographic plates which enable the reader (at the cost of a little labour) to engage at first hand with the subtleties of Jones's borrowings and transformations.</p>
					<p n="6">By keeping such a tight rein on the relation between the visual and textual levels of argumentation in his book, Peacock is able to demonstrate -- rather than merely asserting -- a number of key strands in Jonesian practice. He reveals, for instance, the masque-maker's habit of magnifying small items from the collections of Arundel or the King in order to generate special effects (47). He leads the reader through the complexities of ornamental decorum implicit in Jones's assimilation of the fantastic and the <emph rend="italics">grottesche.</emph> He traces borrowings through the labyrinthine paths of Renaissance print books and is particularly convincing on his subject's use of Marcantonio Raimondi and the prints of his successors (125); on the importance of Riccio via Andreani (211) -- or, even more markedly, on Rosso, via the <title level="m">Livre de la Toison d'or</title> (242) -- as dynamic inspirational forces in the development of the Jonesian aesthetic. And in the later stages of the volume, Peacock is able to bring together image and text to spectacular effect when he feeds Jones's relation to the iconography of Trajan and Constantine into a socio-political reading of the masques and entertainments for Prince Henry (290-2). By the end of the volume, Peacock's Jones has emerged triumphant as a <q direct="y">classical mannerist</q> who has educated an English Protestant taste wary of the visual arts, eliminated his opposition and <q direct="y">reformed</q> the divergent forces of his own source materials into a distinctive and unified aesthetic which is devoted, in the main, to the celebration of monarchic power. Tellingly, for Peacock, the mature Jones was able to enjoy a <q direct="y">personal rule</q> over the masque productions, figuring implicitly as the King's <q direct="y">double,</q> identifying his cultural politics <q direct="y">with the principles of Charles's rule,</q> and fortifying the effect of his designs <q direct="y">without as it were breaking cover and surrendering the role of hidden persuader</q> (325).</p>
					<p n="7">Overall, <title level="m">The Stage Designs of Inigo Jones</title> is a beautifully crafted and meticulously argued book, presenting its main thesis convincingly and with great lucidity. However, lucidity has its price, and there are some moments, understandably enough, where Peacock appears to over-polarise his subject, gaining clarity at the expense of a certain amount of complexity in his account of the issues involved. A case in point might be in his reassessment of Jacobean romanticism (74-81), where he is excellent on the French sources (particularly from the Ch&acirc;teau d'Anet) for <title level="m">Oberon,</title> but completely neglects the simultaneous importance of Italian texts, such as the <title level="m">Hypnerotomachia Poliphili.</title> Similarly, Jones's visualism is characterised throughout the volume in an antithetical relation to Jonson's verbalism, a perspective which owes more to the extremities of their final quarrel in the 1630s than it does to their highly successful (if fraught) partnership over the previous twenty seven years. After all, Jonson -- trained in building and possessing his own copies of Vitruvius -- may have known as much as Jones did about architecture when they first collaborated in 1605; and the dynamism of their early relationship could be explained, in part at least, by the possibility that they were so similar in outlook that they tended to intrude on one another's territory. Accordingly, Peacock is perhaps overdoing it in thinking that Jonson <q direct="y">must</q> have needed Jones's prompting to help explain the novel use of perspective in <title level="m">The Masque of Blackness</title> (162); since Jonson had been interested in the subject for some years (c.f. his dedicatory poem for Nicholas Breton (1600), or the early fascination with painting evinced by his prefatory poem to Thomas Wright's <title level="m">The Passions of the Minde</title>). Likewise, Jones and Jonson do not need to have related antagonistically to the subject of fantasy in the antimasque (138-147). For although, as Peacock argues, Jonson's comic drama does proclaim its <q direct="y">fidelity to an Aristotelian imitation of drama</q> (139), the case of the masque (as Ben well knew), constituted a different package of generic precepts. Jonson, it is worth remembering, had experienced visions, composed poetry out of his dreams, and confessed to sitting up all night imagining armies playing around his big toe. And as Jones (who, like Jonson, was guarded in his approach to the fantastic) could find his way to sanctioning moments when the <q direct="y">Immaginacy</q> could be set free and sometimes fly out <q direct="y">licenciously</q>; so Jonson -- in his <title level="m">Discoveries</title> -- made it clear that, on occasion, he did not forbid <q direct="y">the steering out of our sayle,</q> at moments of inspiration.</p>
					<p n="8">Perhaps more damaging than these small details of emphasis is Peacock's circumspection about those aspects of Jones's personality which were not appealing. There is ample warrant, from the records of his workmen or ambassadorial comment to suggest that like the poet, the architect grew more difficult, intractable and inflexible as he aged; and that, to some extent at least, this rigidity hardened into the work itself. In a diatribe against Jonson, the aged Jones claimed that he himself had been the storehouse of the poet's <q direct="y">plotte<emph rend="italics">s</emph>
						</q>; and later in the same piece he had quipped that in the latter's verse the best was translation while the worst was the poet's own. Similarly, some years earlier, he had made it clear on page 283 of his Vasari that <q direct="y">he who hath not desine and great Inuentio<emph rend="italics">n</emph> of himsealfe shal euer be Poore of graace[,] perfectio<emph rend="italics">n </emph>and Iudgment In great Compositions of archetetture.</q> Jones, in other words, was clear enough about the ethical issues raised by imitation and was able to blame the thefts of others at the same time as, in the later years, he borrowed and delegated with an increasing pragmatism which is somewhat played down in the book. (Without further evidence it is surely not quite fair, for instance, to lay the aesthetic conservatism of the designs for <title level="m">Artenice</title> at the feet of Henrietta Maria (87-8), on the assumption that <q direct="y">she must have ordered Jones</q> to follow the scenographic conventions of the H&ocirc;tel de Bourgogne.) Despite the attraction of Peacock's affirmatory vision, Strong's questions about the reactionary and unregenerate side of Jones's relation to plagiarism still stand.</p>
					<p n="9">If, as seems likely, this splendid book is to endure as the major contribution to Jones studies of the present decade, it may not be out of place to suggest that the publishers consider a paperback reprint at a price which will make it more accessible to the new generation of Jonesian post-graduates.</p>
					<div3>
						<head>Works Cited</head>
						<p>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl>Harris, J. and G. Higgot. <title level="m">Inigo Jones: Complete Architectural Drawings</title>. New York: The Drawing Center, 1989.</bibl>
								<bibl>---, S. Orgel and R. Strong. <title level="m">The King's Arcadia: Inigo Jones and the Stuart Court</title>. London: Arts Council of Great Britain, 1973.</bibl>
								<bibl>Johnson, A.W. <title level="a">'Angles, Squares, or Roundes': Studies in Jonson's Vitruvianism.</title> Doctoral dissertation, 2 vols. Oxford U, 1987.</bibl>
								<bibl>---. <title level="m">Ben Jonson: Poetry and Architecture</title>. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1994.</bibl>
								<bibl>---. <title level="m">Three Volumes Annotated by Inigo Jones: Vasari's <title level="a">Lives</title> (1568), Plutarch's <title level="a">Moralia</title> (1614), Plato's <title level="a">Republic</title> (1554).</title> &Aring;bo Akademi U, 1997.</bibl>
								<bibl>Jonson, Ben. <title level="m">Ben Jonson</title>. Ed. C.H. Herford and P. and E. Simpson. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1925.</bibl>
								<bibl>Newman, J. <title level="a">'The Dating of Inigo Jones's Handwriting,' typescript from 'Essays Presented to Professor Peter Murray'</title>. London: U of London, 1980.</bibl>
								<bibl>---. <title level="a">Italian Treatises in Use: The Significance of Inigo Jones's Annotations.</title>
									<title level="m">Les trait&eacute;s d'architecture de la Renaissance</title>. Ed. Jean Guillaume. Paris: Picard, 1988. 435-41.</bibl>
								<bibl>---. <title level="a">Inigo Jones's Architectural Education before 1614.</title>
									<title level="m">Architectural History</title> 35 (1992): 18-50.</bibl>
								<bibl>Orgel, S. and R. Strong. <title level="m">Inigo Jones: The Theatre of the Stuart Court</title>. London: Sotheby Parke Bernet, 1973.</bibl>
								<bibl>Plato. <title level="m">La Republica di Platone</title>. Tr. Pamphilo Fiorimbene. Venice: Appresso Gabriel Giolito de Ferrari, et fratelli, 1554.</bibl>
								<bibl>Plutarch. <title level="m">Opuscoli morali, di Plutarco Cheronese</title>. Tr. Marc Antonio Gandino. Venice, 1614.</bibl>
								<bibl>Summerson, J.N. <title level="m">Inigo Jones</title>. Harmondsworth, UK: Penguin Books, 1983.</bibl>
								<bibl>Vasari, Giorgio. <title level="m">Delle vite de' piu eccellenti pittori scultori et architettori.</title> Florence: Appresso i Giunti, 1567.</bibl>
								<bibl>Vitruvius Pollio, Marcus. <title level="m">I dieci libri dell'architettura di Vitruvio</title>. Ed, tr. Daniele Barbaro. Venice: Edizioni Librarie siciliane, 1567.</bibl>
							</listBibl>
						</p>
						<p>
							<!--webbot bot="include" u-include="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/emls footer.html" tag="body" startspan -->[http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/EMLS footer.html]<!--webbot bot="include" endspan i-checksum="20494" -->
						</p>
					</div3>
					<byline>(LH, AWJ, RGS, 30 March 1998)</byline>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls4-1revgoo6" n="5" type="review">
					<!-- <img src="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/header2.gif" alt="early" modern literary studies width="283" height="87"> -->
					<head>Harry Keyishian. <title level="m">The Shapes of Revenge: Victimization, Vengeance, and Vindictiveness in Shakespeare</title>. Atlantic Highlands, N.J.: Humanities P International Inc., 1995. ISBN 0 391 03828 1 Cloth. US $39.95.</head>
					<opener>Review by <name>Bryan N.S. Gooch</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>University of Victoria</addrLine>
						</address>
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Gooch, Bryan N.S. <title level="a">Review of <title level="m">The Shapes of Revenge: Victimization, Vengeance, and Vindictiveness in Shakespeare</title>.</title>
						<title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 4.1 (May, 1998): 5.1-6 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/rev_goo6.html"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/rev_goo6.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;.</p>
					<p n="1">Harry Keyishian rightly recognises that distinction between various manifestations of revenge is crucial in coming to terms not only with many of Shakespeare's characters -- and some were notable and clearly nasty avengers of perceived yet unsubstantiated wrong -- but also with his social and moral milieu. <title level="m">The Shapes of Revenge</title> is a well organised, economically argued, historically grounded text which looks systematically at types of vengeance and the nature of a good number of avengers and victims. The reader is left in no doubt that the label <q direct="y">revenge play</q> is as undiscriminating as it is unhelpful; equally clear is the necessity to assess the concept of retribution in Shakespearean drama through Elizabethan or Jacobean eyes rather than through a twentieth-century moralistic glass. Here the Introduction and first chapter are central to an understanding of Keyishian's approach. He differentiates early, for example, between the motivation and actions of a Macduff and the cruelty of, say, an Iago who drives on for imagined reasons, or pure vindictiveness, or perceived diminution (perhaps justified) of public image. Moreover, the author clearly presents in Chapter I, <q direct="y">Victimization and Revenge: Renaissance Voices,</q> a useful survey of the problem, drawing from books on the passions and moving on to consider not only the power of the revenger but the powerlessness of victims, e.g., the Duchess of Gloucester, Ophelia, Desdemona and Hermione, and the notion that revenge, though bloody, can be restorative (as in <title level="m">Macbeth</title>).</p>
					<p n="2">In the second chapter, <q direct="y">Redemptive Revenge in <title level="m">Titus Andronicus</title> and <title level="m">The Rape of Lucrece</title>,</q> Keyishian's understanding of Titus' famous laugh (III.i.264) as revealing the character's appreciation of his real situation illustrates a challenging critical sensitivity as well as a solid grounding, apparent throughout the volume, in significant criticism. This chapter leads nicely to the third, <q direct="y">Problematic Revenge in <title level="m">Hamlet</title> and <title level="m">King Lear</title>.</q> Certainly, not all readers will necessarily agree with every conclusion -- an earlier comment (26) about Hamlet having fallen into a <q direct="y">suicidal depression</q> (until yanked back to sense by the Ghost) will have put some a little on guard -- but the approach is useful and focused: Keyishian deals with his <emph rend="italics">topic</emph>, not with the whole of <title level="m">Hamlet</title> or the whole, even, of the young prince, and therefore it is unfair to expect the kind of broader, more discursive commentary which would really subvert the direction of the argument. (Nevertheless, with respect to the Ghost and the moral quandary of Hamlet, the reader would find it relevant and appropriate to look at Chapter 6 of Norman Austin's splendid <title level="m">Meaning and Being in Myth</title> [University Park and London: Pennsylvania State UP, 1990], which would have been a helpful addition to Keyishian's bibliography.) The discussion of Lear is excellent, though perhaps the point that Lear fails to live up to his responsibilities as King even before the stage action commences (having decided on his country's division) and hence allows his state and family to unravel needs explicit consideration. While Lear does take some revenge, e.g., on Cordelia's murderer, Edgar is rightly seen as the real avenger, and the issue of concealment for the preservation of safety is important, as is the parallel to the guise of madness (with its various results) adopted by Hamlet. (This, of course, will prompt related ponderings on the morality of deception in Shakespeare's plays: like revenge, it proceeds from a variety of motives and produces a wide range of outcomes.) Keyishian argues that Shakespeare attempts -- not wholly successfully -- to simplify the revenge of Hamlet and Edgar by casting them as agents of divine authority, though this position itself does not seem, at first blush, completely satisfying.</p>
					<p n="3">The next stage in the process is outlined in Chapter 4, <q direct="y">Destructive Revenge in <title level="m">Julius Caesar</title> and <title level="m">Othello</title>.</q> In <title level="m">Caesar</title> there are, it is asserted, three centres or <q direct="y">lines</q> (81) of revenge, viz., Mark Antony, the Romans, and Caesar, and Keyishian sees that of the murdered Julius as unfruitful in the light of Brutus' adherence to his principles and his nobility (which even Antony acknowledges) at the end of the play. Each <q direct="y">line</q> is examined in turn in a clear-headed way, though note could also be taken of the macabre pragmatism (revenge) of Antony, Octavius, and Lepidus at the beginning of IV.i. Parallels between plays abound, and the correspondence between Antony's chillingly ironic, rhetorical toying with the crowd during the funeral oration and Iago's handling of Othello is properly instructive. The view offered is that, though destructive, the vengeance here (excluding Iago) is on the edge of vindictiveness; in this chapter, as elsewhere, quotations from the texts of the play illustrate the discussion and are themselves, rightly, the subject of critical comment. Indeed, one cannot consider <title level="m">Othello</title> without touching on vindictiveness, and that is precisely the topic of Chapter 5, which, after relevant consideration, again, of sources on the passions, moves on to deal with its manifestations in the Sonnets (here the overly-praised Youth, whose dullness and egotism Northrop Frye maligned so wittily, as Keyishian notes (105), is the victim of the poet), in <title level="m">Merchant</title> (Shylock), in <title level="m">Twelfth Night</title> (Malvolio), in <title level="m">Othello</title> (Iago), and in <title level="m">Coriolanus</title>.</p>
					<p n="4">Chapter 7, <q direct="y">Varieties of Revenge in the First Tetralogy,</q> takes into account <q direct="y">factional revenges</q> (124-128), focusing on York and Old Clifford, and then proceeds to consider Queen Margaret and Richard III, suggesting that this set of plays was, in a way, a kind of test-bed for Shakespeare in his exploration of the nature of revenge. Chapter 8 -- <q direct="y">False Investments: Leontes and Timon</q> -- brings one to two central characters who become victims of themselves and their own pride and vindictiveness. Leontes is, bluntly, what the modern age, with its curious vocabulary, would call a <q direct="y">control freak;</q> Keyishian suggests that ultimately Apollo is the central revenger: one cannot oppose the gods unpunished, and though forgiveness dominates at the end, losses of significant dimension (e.g., the deaths of Mamilius and Antigonus, the absence of 16 years of Hermione's company and Perdita's youth, and the devastation of Sicilian court life) are paid in tribute: rightly, as many critics (e.g., J.H.P. Pafford in his remarkably astute introduction to the Arden edition) have argued, enough time must pass to allow for some healing to take place (<emph rend="italics">pace</emph> those more cynical who say, merely, that poor, abandoned Perdita has to have time to grow up). Sophoclean hints are in evidence in this play, though not addressed. Ultimately, I suggest, the notion of redemption dominates the romances, and this chapter offers an intriguing if slightly uneasy coupling of plays, for Timon moves from generosity to hatred: he is finally the butt of his own deadly shafts.</p>
					<p n="5">In Chapter 8, <q direct="y">Solving the Problem,</q> one is presented with the revenger as victim. Here is a summation, with Keyishian pointing clearly to the dangers of revenge and noting the beliefs of Christians (vengeance is the right of God), the links to Platonic theory, and utilitarian arguments against vengeance. Even not taking revenge can hurt an enemy, and here one finds, logically, Alcibiades as Timon's foil, and, in the end, Prospero. Curiously, several key lines (cited in another recent review) are absent from the quoted passages, notably: <q direct="y">Though with their high wrongs I am shook to th' quick, / Yet, with my nobler reason, 'gainst my fury / Do I take part</q> (V.i.25-27). These words provide a key to an understanding of <title level="m">Winter's Tale</title> as well. Prospero learns what many of the characters in earlier plays could never grasp; certainly, Prospero achieves most of his goals, e.g., restoration of his dukedom (which he lost, after all, through negligence and misjudgment of priorities -- cf. Lear), peace with Alonso, a union of Milan and Naples through the marriage of Miranda and Ferdinand, and so on, but there is nothing to tell one in the play that -- abandonment of magic trappings and internal forgiveness not withstanding -- Antonio will ever become repentant and better than he is (and Shakespeare offers one a number of remarkably wicked brothers/uncles) or that Caliban will not simply sink back into the mire of his own depravity. <q direct="y">Contrition</q> is understood neither by opportunistic courtier or bestial savage. A point which Keyishian might also want to ponder is that beyond redress, that is, a restoration of what the modern age infelicitously calls <q direct="y">normalcy,</q> Prospero wants redemption for all, if that can be achieved. One might also ask, in this consideration of <title level="m">The Tempest</title>, just where Ariel fits in; though he is within Prospero's control, he is not without sympathy to certain agendas, and he clearly has debts to be repaid and freedom to be regained (as he reminds his magus-rescuer more than once). The book's <q direct="y">Conclusion</q> is markedly brief -- a gathering of main threads, statements as to the importance of the importance of revenge in Shakespeare (one can hardly disagree), and comments as to the significance of his character portrayals. Perhaps, by way of overview, one could also be left with a picture of how the treatment of revenge develops in terms of the society which the playwright and the modern reader share <emph rend="italics">through</emph> the canon, from early plays to late ones.</p>
					<p n="6">The appended notes and the bibliography (works cited) are a testament to Keyishian's well-read approach, and the index (which follows) is short yet sufficient. The volume is, on the whole, more than successful, and the prose is unmistakably clear (though one might wish for the exclusion of the occasional use of [trendy?] terms like <q direct="y">valorize</q>). As noted above, this is a rather focused volume, and its theme is both its virtue and, perhaps for some readers, its limitation. It is inevitable that there will be reservations of the <q direct="y">But what about . . .</q> and <q direct="y">If you were to consider . . .</q> variety, and this review raises a few of these. But that is the stuff of Shakespeare criticism. Keyishian has done well -- thoughtfully and lucidly -- what he set out to do, and students of Shakespeare ought consider his work seriously.</p>
					<div3>
						<head>Works Cited </head>
						<p>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl>Austin, Norman. <title level="m">Meaning and Being in Myth</title>. University Park: Pennsylvania State UP, 1990.</bibl>
								<bibl>Shakespeare, William. <title level="m">The Winter's Tale</title>. Ed. J.H.P. Pafford. London: Methuen, 1963.</bibl>
							</listBibl>
						</p>
						<p>
							<!--webbot bot="include" u-include="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/emls footer.html" tag="body" startspan -->[http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/EMLS footer.html]<!--webbot bot="include" endspan i-checksum="20494" -->
						</p>
					</div3>
					<byline>(LH, BG, RGS, 9 March 1998)</byline>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls4-1revivic" n="6" type="review">
					<!-- <img src="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/header2.gif" alt="early" modern literary studies width="283" height="87"> -->
					<head>Willy Maley. <title level="m">Salvaging Spenser: Colonialism, Culture and Identity</title>. London: Macmillan; New York: St. Martin's P, 1997. viii+251pp. ISBN 0 333 62942 6 Paper; 0 312 17234 6 Cloth.</head>
					<opener>Review by <name>Christopher Ivic</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>University of Western Ontario</addrLine>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href="mailto:civic@julian.uwo.ca"> -->civic@julian.uwo.ca<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Ivic, Christopher. <title level="a">Review of <title level="m">Salvaging Spenser: Colonialism, Culture and
Identity</title>
						</title>. <title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 4.1 (May, 1998): 6.1-5 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/rev_ivic.html"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/rev_ivic.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;.</p>
					<p n="1">The 1989 publication of <title level="m">Spenser and Ireland: An Interdisciplinary Perspective</title> (ed. Patricia Coughlan) marked a significant contribution to Spenser scholarship. Bringing together the work of both historians and literary historians, this collection of essays renewed critical interest in the colonial milieu in which Spenser fashioned himself a gentleman. <title level="m">Salvaging Spenser</title> engages in the revisionary project of situating Spenser's texts in the ideologically charged colonial context that informed, indeed enabled, their production. Addressing a wide range of historical, theoretical, and cultural issues, Maley provides stimulating, original analyses of topics such as the politics of Protestant plantation in Munster, the discursive struggle for English identity in Ireland, and the influence of <q direct="y">Irish English</q> on Spenser's language. By no means, however, is <title level="m">Salvaging Spenser</title> merely another addition to a burgeoning field of study. As the absence of <q direct="y">Ireland</q> from the title suggests, this book's focus on colonialism, culture and identity serves to stretch and thereby redefine the boundaries of <q direct="y">Spenser and Ireland,</q> both chronologically and geographically. </p>
					<p n="2">In fact, much of Maley's attention is directed toward the ideological legacy of Spenser's texts, especially as they (in particular the prose dialogue, <title level="m">A View of the State of Ireland</title>) impacted on the culture of Caroline and Cromwellian Ireland. In a slightly revised version of a previously published essay, <q direct="y">How Milton and Some Contemporaries Read Spenser's <title level="m">View</title>,</q> Maley highlights the crucial role that the <title level="m">View</title> -- first published by Sir James Ware in 1633, with a dedication to Sir Thomas Wentworth, earl of Stafford and Lord Deputy of Ireland -- played in the development of Anglo-Irish politics in the 1640s and beyond. For example, he considers the ideological effect of Spenser's dialogue on Milton's own officially commissioned tract on Ireland: <title level="m">Observations upon the Articles of peace with the Irish Rebels</title> (1649). While Maley's reading of the conveniently overlooked <title level="m">Observations</title> complicates conventional narratives that valorize Milton's heroic republicanism, his study of the complex and often contradictory post-1633 responses to the <title level="m">View</title> challenges reductive representations of Spenser as <q direct="y">a mere mouthpiece for the presumed policies of the presiding regime</q> (129). For Maley, then, the example of how Milton read Spenser serves to remind scholars of the need to re-examine not only Milton's but also Spenser's politics. </p>
					<p n="3">Maley's concern with seventeenth-century Anglo-Irish, or Anglo-Celtic, conflict leads him to a consideration of a hitherto unexamined topic: namely, <q direct="y">Spenser and Scotland.</q>
						<q direct="y">Spenser and Scotland</q> may appear to be an odd coupling; however, it is important to recall that the <title level="m">View</title> articulates a deep anxiety about the <q direct="y">Celtic Fringe</q>: that is, both Elizabeth's Irish kingdom/colony and England's northern Gaelic neighbours, especially those <q direct="y">Irish Scots</q> who drifted in and out of Ulster. By foregrounding <q direct="y">Spenser and Scotland,</q> Maley does well to situate Spenser's work within the larger framework of state formation within the British Isles. Rather than reinscribing a stable, monolithic English/Irish binarism, he attends to the tenuous emergence of Britishness and British identity in the early modern period. His remarkably succinct account of the British context in which Spenser's <q direct="y">national epic</q> was composed, disseminated, and suppressed speaks volumes: <q direct="y">Written in Ireland, banned in Scotland, <title level="m">The Faerie Queene</title> tells the story of the English nation from the perspective of an expatriate</q> (155). The posthumously published 1611 first Folio of Spenser's collected works heralds him as <q direct="y">England's Arch-Po&euml;t.</q> Committed to a non-anglocentric historiography, Maley carefully explores Spenser's contribution to the discursive production of the heterogeneous, intersecting, and warring cultures of the British Isles. </p>
					<p n="4">Certainly the majority of this book's close readings focus on, or around, the <title level="m">View</title> -- including a valuable chapter that provides a <q direct="y">judicial review</q> (I would add convincing critique) of Jean Brink's discussion of the censorship and authorship of the <title level="m">View</title>. Attention to Spenser's shorter poems and his epic-romance is less pronounced, at times elliptical. The opening chapter on <q direct="y">
							<title level="m">The Shepheardes Calender</title> as Colonial Text,</q> for instance, does not <q direct="y">get to</q> the pastoral poem until the chapter's concluding section; in other words, roughly six of the chapter's twenty-three pages are given over to Spenser's pastoral poem. Perhaps more energy could have been devoted to sustained readings of <title level="m">The Faerie Queene. </title>Given Maley's recent work on <q direct="y">The British Problem</q> in Shakespeare, Bacon, and Milton, it is surprising that he says little about <q direct="y">Briton moniments.</q> This is not to suggest, however, that this book suffers because it attends more to context than text. To put it in these simplistic, oppositional terms is to overlook the fact that this book's value lies precisely in its re-examination of <q direct="y">context</q> and <q direct="y">text.</q> What, I find, this books lacks in terms of close readings it more than makes up for in its examination of not only what Spenser read but also how early modern readers interpreted, appropriated Spenser. Maley's informative discussion of Ware's edition of the <title level="m">View</title> -- its excisions, its annotations, its dedicatory material -- is a prime example of Fredric Jameson's reminder that <q direct="y">texts come to us as the always-already-read; we apprehend them through sedimented layers of previous interpretations.</q> This book invites us to reflect on the ways in which we <q direct="y">get to</q> Spenser's texts. </p>
					<p n="5">
						<q direct="y">Salvaging Spenser,</q> Maley writes in his Introduction, <q direct="y">does not mean going back to some original source, but rather entails sifting laboriously through the items of wreckage washed ashore</q> (7). Maley, to be sure, does a lot of sifting, as his richly documented work attests. Included in the wreckage are a number of early modern texts that have attracted little notice from literary historians: for instance, <q direct="y">Holinshed's</q> Irish <title level="m">Chronicles</title> (1577, 1587), Richard Beacon's <title level="m">Solon His Follie</title> (1594), Lodowick Bryskett's <title level="m">Discourse of Civill Life</title> (1606), and Francis Bacon's <q direct="y">Certain Considerations Touching the Plantations in Ireland</q> (1606). Along with drawing our attention to these relatively unknown primary texts, he also retrieves a wealth of neglected secondary works. Indeed, one of the rewards of Maley's salvaging of Spenser is his recovery of the valuable historical scholarship on Spenser's Irish experience that was written in early decades of the twentieth century. Because of its historical scope and engagement with the recent work on early modern British history, this book will no doubt redirect studies of <q direct="y">Spenser and Ireland.</q>
					</p>
					<div3>
						<head>Works Cited</head>
						<p>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl>Brink, Jean. <title level="a">Constructing the <title level="m">View of the Present State of Ireland</title>.</title>
									<title level="j">Spenser Studies</title> 11 (1990): 203-28.</bibl>
								<bibl>Coughlan, Patricia, ed. <title level="m">Spenser and Ireland: An Interdisciplinary Perspective</title>. Cork: Cork UP, 1989.</bibl>
								<bibl>Jameson, Fredric. <title level="m">The Political Unconscious: Narrative as a Socially Symbolic Act</title>. Cornell: Cornell UP, 1981.</bibl>
							</listBibl>
						</p>
						<p>
							<!--webbot bot="include" u-include="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/emls footer.html" tag="body" startspan -->[http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/EMLS footer.html]<!--webbot bot="include" endspan i-checksum="20494" -->
						</p>
					</div3>
					<byline>(LH, CI, RGS, 9 March 1998)</byline>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls4-1revbly3" n="7" type="review">
					<head>Jeffrey Masten. <title level="m">Textual Intercourse: Collaboration, Authorship, and Sexualities in Renaissance Drama.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1997. 223pp + 14 illustrations. ISBN 0 521 57260 6 Cloth; 0 521 58920 7 Paper.</head>
					<opener>Review by <name>Mary Bly</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>Washington University in St. Louis</addrLine>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href="mailto:mbly@artsci.wustl.edu"> -->mbly@artsci.wustl.edu<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Bly, Mary. <title level="a">Review of <title level="m">Textual Intercourse: Collaboration, Authorship, and Sexualities in Renaissance Drama</title>
						</title>. <title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 4.1 (May, 1998): 7.1-8 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/[path]/[filename.html]"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/rev_bly3.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;.</p>
					<p n="1">Jeff Masten's <title level="m">Textual Intercourse</title> is a lucid and engrossing contribution to the study of the collaborative writing partnerships of early modern England. Masten fashions a complicated subject: the dual rhetoric of writing and sexual partnership in the seventeenth century, on the one hand, and our ability as twentieth century scholars to grasp the intricacies of that relationship, on the other. <title level="m">Textual Intercourse</title> does not simply discuss sexual intercourse and texts in one breath, it addresses <emph rend="italics">our</emph> intercourse with the text, <emph rend="italics">our</emph> fumbling, textual attempts to understand erotic relations in the early modern period.</p>
					<p n="2">Masten's book crucially depends upon a premise which twentieth century scholars, altogether too swayed by Shakespeare studies, love to ignore: <q direct="y">collaboration was a prevalent mode of textual production in the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries, only eventually displaced by the mode of singular authorship with which we are more familiar</q> (4). Masten offers a provocative corrective in his emphasis on the polyvocal construction of texts in London playhouses. He takes seriously the process which turned a collaborative manuscript into a script revised, cut and augmented by everyone from the book-holder to a <q direct="y">playhouse dramatist,</q> finally improvised and elaborated by actors in performance.</p>
					<p n="3">Yet it's one thing to write a book which insists that collaboration was the primary mode of theatrical writing in the early modern period and, of course, quite another to bring together textual production and sexual relations. Masten asserts what he calls a <q direct="y">chiastic assumption:</q> texts are produced <q direct="y">within a particular sex/gender context,</q> and gender and sexuality are at least partially produced in and by those texts (5). <title level="m">Textual Intercourse</title> contends that early modern dramatic writing occurred within the context of <q direct="y">a collaborative homoerotics</q> (37). Collaborative writing was the norm and texts themselves insistently figure the act of writing as both collaboration and homoerotic exchange. Part of Masten's argument is that collaborative texts written during a period of collaborative production (i.e., before Foucault's <q direct="y">author</q> appears), are functionally different from the collaborative texts we might produce in 1998. In Masten's words, <q direct="y">reading the languages of collaboration and authorship attentively, we will begin to see some signal differences of our culture from that of these dead men, in both their textual relations and their sexual ones</q> (4). Masten does not aim to identify familiar sex roles through his examination of an unfamiliar mode of textual production. <q direct="y">The point,</q> he writes, <q direct="y">is not to bring the Renaissance out of the closet, but to bring the closet out of the Renaissance</q> (7).</p>
					<p n="4">The first play Masten discusses is <title level="m">The Knight of the Burning Pestle</title>, <q direct="y">perhaps the most wildly collaborative play of this period</q> (23). The script, he argues, stages the constraints weighing on an <q direct="y">author,</q> if such an entity could be identified amid the welter of voices figured as authors in the <title level="m">Knight</title> (everyone from Rafe to the Citizen's Wife). To Masten, that network of voices is more relevant to interpretation of the text than is analysis of Beaumont's voice. <title level="m">Textual Intercourse</title> then moves nimbly from a discussion of the <title level="m">Knight</title>'s multiple voices to a discussion of homosocial friendship and the complex issues at the nexus of collaboration, homoeroticism and male friendship.</p>
					<p n="5">Masten's third and fourth chapters place writing partnerships within the hierarchical context of early modern England and within the language of patriarchal absolutism. Interestingly, Masten approaches the complexities of author/authority by analyzing plays in which an author is resurrected in order to re-present a play: Homer in <title level="m">The Golden Age</title>, and Gower in <title level="m">Pericles</title>. He traces an authorial presenter <q direct="y">splintered,</q> tentative, un-authorized. Masten thus locates his study <q direct="y">at a crucial moment in the history of the subject</q> (143), linking the move away from collective writing towards individual authorship to a switch in modes of government in England, from a single royal voice to more collective action (151). He suggests this shift only to qualify it, labelling it a fiction, and leaving it a question: <q direct="y">what are the relations between modes of textual production, systems of government, and modes of subjectivity?</q> (151).</p>
					<p n="6">Perhaps the only problematic area of Masten's brilliant study is a tendency to cite broad historical shifts, whether or not they are tentatively suggested (as above), or used more confidently. The final chapter of <title level="m">Textual Intercourse</title> analyzes Margaret Cavendish's negotiation of her Folio volumes within <q direct="y">the newly emergent discourse of collaborative marriage</q> (158). Masten employed this particular historical paradigm earlier in the book: Richard Braithwait's <title level="m">The English Gentleman</title>, with its homoerotic ideals of male friendship, is depicted as arriving <q direct="y">at the cusp of a companionate ideal of marriage that was radically to alter the sex/gender system</q> (30). Masten utilizes this <q direct="y">new</q> marital ideal in order to demonstrate a cultural reversal: what would have been radical (companionate marriage) becomes normal while male/male collaboration becomes <q direct="y">strange Production,</q> according to John Berkenhead's 1647 poem (136). But the historical emergence of companionate marriage is not as tidy as it appears in <title level="m">Textual Intercourse</title>. In fact, the very idea of a <q direct="y">new</q> companionate marriage has been violently attacked by historians in the years since Lawrence Stone popularized it: first by E. P. Thomas and most recently by David Cressy (1997) and Mary Prior (1997). Henry Abalone recently suggested that literary scholars have clung to the idea of companionate marriage, long after historians demanded that Stone's book be pulped, because the concept plays to a modern fantasy -- that love can produce equality.<ref target="emls4-1revbly3n1">[1]</ref>
					</p>
					<p n="7">I wonder whether something of the same fantasy might function in Masten's otherwise historically impeccable account of writing processes and attendant erotic relationships. When Masten argues that Cavendish's work <q direct="y">demonstrates the emergence of male-female collaboration out of the prior discourse of homoerotic friendship that informs the Beaumont and Fletcher volume,</q> we need to be as careful as Masten himself was about taxonomies (158). We are no more likely to grasp what was encompassed by a <q direct="y">companionate</q> marriage in 1662 than we are to grasp exactly what happened within the bounds of a male friendship figuring two bodies made into one, as in Braithwait's definition. The emergence of companionate marriage makes a neat conclusion to Masten's study, implicitly explaining the demise of homosocial writing partnerships that clearly, on some level, avoided the rigid hierarchies that inflect many male relationships in the early modern period (as argued by Stephen Orgel in <title level="m">Impersonations</title>, for example).</p>
					<p n="8">
						<title level="m">Textual Intercourse</title> is a book of startling originality. It sets a difficult precedent: not only is it historically demanding, in that Masten asks the reader to look beyond simple authorially-based monographs and trace the contexts and constraints of the early modern theatrical world, but it challenges the imagination as well. At its very best, queer theory links attention to historical fact with a creative energy that admits the difficulties of historical reconstruction -- whether the subject is texts or sexes. Masten's examination of cultural meaning alternates between analysis, history and manifesto. As <title level="m">Textual Intercourse</title> traces the joyous and profitable partnerships between Beaumont and Fletcher, or Shakespeare and Fletcher, Masten insistently reminds us what a keen historical and imaginative scope scholars must employ when writing about the early modern period.</p>
					<div3>
						<head>Notes</head>
						<p>
							<note id="emls4-1revbly3n1">1. Henry Abalone, as a member of a round-table discussion on early modern sexuality, <title level="m">Group for Early Modern Cultural Studies</title>, December 1997.</note>
						</p>
						<p>
							<!--webbot bot="include" u-include="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/emls footer.html" tag="body" startspan -->[http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/EMLS footer.html]<!--webbot bot="include" endspan i-checksum="20494" -->
						</p>
					</div3>
					<byline>(LH, RGS, 10 June 1998)</byline>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls4-1revfitt" n="8" type="review">
					<head>Curtis C. Breight. <title level="m">Surveillance, Militarism and Drama in the Elizabethan Era</title>. New York: St. Martin's P, 1996. 348 pp. ISBN 0 312 16406 6 Cloth.</head>
					<opener>Review by <name>Chris Fitter</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>Rutgers University-Camden</addrLine>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href= "mailto:fitter@crab.rutgers.edu"> -->fitter@crab.rutgers.edu<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
					</opener>
					<!-- <img src="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/header2.gif" alt="early" modern literary studies width="283" height="87"> -->
					<p rend="centre">Fitter, Chris. <title level="a">Review of <title level="m">Surveillance, Militarism and Drama in the Elizabethan Era</title>
						</title>. <title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 4.1 (May, 1998): 8.1-4 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/rev_fitt.html"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/rev_fitt.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;.</p>
					<p n="1">In the film <title level="m">Braveheart</title>, that festival of inane brutality, Mel Gibson, as he lies helpless in the last stages of disembowelment, yet finds the capability, bereft of his viscera, to cry boomingly aloud: <q direct="y">Freedom!</q> In the reign of Elizabeth, according to the Tillyardian and conservative view of the period that is still sometimes echoed, the many scores of men and women whose torture during interrogation we know to have been officially authorized may likewise have been able to comfort themselves with the rallying exclamation: <q direct="y">At least I'm living in the Golden Age of England!</q> The rosy conservative view of Elizabethan politics has of course been long under attack, yet most critics still posit a widespread contemporary <q direct="y">consent</q> to governance by her regime. Even the opposing <q direct="y">liberal</q> construction of that era has so far largely centred on such consent, as substantially engineered by a putative <q direct="y">theatricality</q> of power: thus the New Historicism enjoys a comfortably middle-class and literary interest in power as a lavishly aestheticized realm, focusing on gorgeous display, auratic ritual, the quelling mystique of costume. Breight's book, conversely, aspires to be a machiavellian classic: a landmark demystification of the nature, capacity and intentions of the apparatus of state power in Elizabethan England, and a revelation of the meditation of such darker truths in the drama of Marlowe and Shakespeare. Opening by situating both conservative and New Historicist approaches in their respective historical matrices, it subjects each to devastating critique. The Golden Age model of a gallant, vulnerable virgin Queen menaced by a bullying superpower is suggestively linked to the Cold War creation of an ideological myth of <q direct="y">innocent</q> origins, sustained both by academic historiography and popular cinema; and is a myth easily exploded by noting those realms other than drama in which the 1590s achieved a new historical high: famine-levels, war-casualties and witchcraft prosecution. The New Historicist model of <q direct="y">theatrical</q> power has been founded on the axiom of an Elizabethan state substantially lacking coercive power, unequipped with standing army, police force or efficient bureaucracy: a description, argues Breight, that is deeply falsifying. He turns for his own framework to <q direct="y">restoring the cultural primacy of <emph rend="italics">realpolitik</emph>,</q> drawing on wide reading, archival research, fascinating use of Renaissance Catholic pamphleteers, and fresh readings of drama to sketch on the one hand the unfashionable realm of class-relations, poverty and seething popular disaffection, and on the other the operations of a machiavellian administration that maintained political control by terror and physical elimination of dissidents.</p>
					<p n="2">Breight's synthesis of recent work by Roger Manning, A.L.Beier, Paul Slack and others on mass destitution and its subversive voice is valuable in itself as a clearly written, cogent and powerful argument for a level of popular political dissidence generally denied or overlooked by most critics and historians, who still curiously assume that the lack of formal political <emph rend="italics">parties</emph> signifies consensual Elizabethan masses, and the absence of class-consciousness. Yet it is Breight's unequivocal model of a greatly expanded and audaciously machiavellian state power that is original, and the heart of the book. Elizabeth herself is peripheralised in this paradigm, in which the <q direct="y">new men,</q> above all the Cecils, create a systematic <q direct="y">national security state,</q> achieving efficient mass-coercion less by ideology (let alone theatrics), than by surveillance, fear and militarism. Far from being handicapped by the lack of a standing army, Breight argues, such a body would have been too dangerous. Instead the <emph rend="italics">regnum Cecilianum</emph> developed an <emph rend="italics">ideological</emph> remilitarization of England, drawing militias, highlighted by trained bands, from the ranks of the prosperous, while raising levies for overseas expeditions largely from the underclasses. <q direct="y">Beginning in 1585 some 200,000 men were coerced, literally and/ or economically, to subserve the dubious aims of foreign policy and the somewhat understandable aims of privateering</q> (172). By modern analogy, <q direct="y">Elizabethan losses during the war period [were] about <emph rend="italics">fifty</emph> times worse than American casualties in Vietnam</q> (232). Moreover levies functioned consciously as expedient mass-deportations of penurious and disaffected males, decimating domestic opposition; and thus foreign policy, far from being the scenario of a plucky victim subject to bullying, was a matter of frequent provocation of Spain as a calculated tactic of both imperial ambition and expanding state power. Drawing on the studies of Ronald Pollitt, James Heath and others, Breight further argues that the Cecilian regime developed surveillance and terror to reinforce domestic control: the extension of treason laws, creation of Provost Marshalls, expansion of judicial torture, invention of an espionage network, fabrication of pseudo-plots, staging of kangaroo-court treason trials, springing of mass house-to-house searches in London producing huge and detailed intelligence documents, and sustained promotion of both propaganda and paranoia (executions reached 800 per year by the last years of the reign), were all manifestations of an aggressively expansionist state apparatus. So much for the mythos of popular rule by a vestal Queen bereft of coercive power.</p>
					<p n="3">Into this context of Elizabethan Cold Wars against domestic dissent, and Hot Wars on the Continent, Breight places Marlowe and Shakespeare. <title level="m">The Massacre at Paris</title> is interpreted as being seditiously congruous with the depiction of an oppressed, reluctantly militarized English nation in the Catholic propaganda of such writers as Richard Verstegan, pouring out in 1592. A lengthy chapter reviewing the complex evidence on the death of Marlowe speculates, with due tentativeness, that the playwright, <emph rend="italics">pace</emph> Charles Nicholl, appears more likely to have been demonized and assassinated at the behest of Burghley than of Essex. Suggesting parallels between Gaveston in <title level="m">Edward II</title> and attacks on Burghley, it exposits that play as encoding Catholic anti-government propaganda at a time of national tension and momentous struggles at court. Three chapters on Shakespeare persuasively focus the Henriad, and most successfully <title level="m">Henry V</title>, in terms of the profound English hostility to military levies, the devastating casualties and mass desertions that would, Breight suggests, have led to the vocal execration of the Falstaff of <title level="m">2 Henry IV</title>. Theatres themselves, after all, became places of impressment. Shakespeare emerges here as centrally sympathetic to the commoners' plight and perspectives, and extensively ironic toward the ideological manoeuvrings of the kings and corrupt commanders who coerce them.</p>
					<p n="4">This study is flawed, unfortunately, by vulnerability to accusations of intemperance and polemicism. Elizabethan terror, for instance, seems to have been real enough for Catholics, vagrants and the poor, but scarcely for the propertied classes with whom the Crown worked carefully, even timidly, in negotiating parliamentary subsidies and personal loans, and for whom the regime, as Breight admits, functioned largely as a benevolent partner. The marginalization of Elizabeth, too, seems overstated, for like her grandfather, she liked to oversee a vast amount of administrative detail, and though doubtless vacillating and manipulable, jealously reserved all key decisions to herself. (Her determination to be rid of Archbishop Grindal, for instance, though it threatened to break new constitutional ground, could not be overcome even by the combined forces of Burghley, Walsingham and a Privy Council majority, who campaigned unsuccessfully over years for his re-empowerment.) Nevertheless, <title level="m">Surveillance, Militarism and Drama in the</title>
						<title level="m">Elizabethan Era</title> is genuinely a major work, providing an indispensably detailed and pugnaciously revolutionary context for the interpretation of Elizabethan drama and culture. It will be hard for the proverbial open-minded reader to conceive of power and plays in the age of Shakespeare in the same way again.</p>
					<p>
						<!--webbot bot="include" u-include="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/emls footer.html" tag="body" startspan -->[http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/EMLS footer.html]<!--webbot bot="include" endspan i-checksum="20494" -->
					</p>
					<byline>(LH, RGS, 30 March 1998)</byline>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls4-1revvoe2" n="9" type="review">
					<!-- <img src="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/header2.gif" alt="early" modern literary studies width="283" height="87"> -->
					<head>Paula Blank. <title level="m">Broken English: Dialects and the Politics of
Language in Renaissance Writings</title>. London: Routledge, 1996. viii+211pp. ISBN 0 415 13779 9 Cloth. </head>
					<opener>Review by <name>Swen Voekel</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>University of Rochester, Rochester, NY</addrLine>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href="mailto:svoekel@earthlink.net"> -->svoekel@earthlink.net<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Voekel, Swen. <title level="a">Review of <title level="m">Broken English: Dialects and the Politics of Language in Renaissance Writings</title>.</title>
						<title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 4.1 (May, 1998): 9.1-5 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/rev_voe2.html"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/rev_voe2.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;.</p>
					<p n="1">In his recent book <title level="m">Salvaging Spenser: Colonialism, Culture and Identity</title>, Willy Maley argues that <q direct="y">Spenser's texts were produced within the context of a peculiar colonial struggle in Ireland between, not just two English communities, but two concepts of Englishness, two kinds of English culture,</q> and that <q direct="y">this conflict has to be viewed within a wider British context, in relation to what historians have come to call the 'British Problem.'</q> This focus on concepts or varieties of Englishness has recently become one of the the central concerns of both literary critics and historians, who have come to question the idea of a monolithic and insular English national identity in the early modern period. In his monumental <title level="m">Forms of Nationhood</title>, Richard Helgerson revealed the faultlines that separated the versions of Englishness presented by a host of major late-Elizabethan English writers, and the tensions inherent in the period which saw both the rise of a territorial, monarchical state and of the authorial self. In <title level="m">Broken English</title>, Paula Blank addresses these concerns with metropolitan identity (<q direct="y">the Elizabethan writing of England</q>), within the context of English writers' newly emerging focus on (and representations of) the linguistic peripheries of the Tudor and Stuart kingdoms.</p>
					<p n="2">As Maley makes clear, the forging of an English (and, in the late-Elizabethan and Stuart period, British) identity has as much to do with the peripheries of the Tudor polity as with its center; while he focuses on Ireland, Blank's book takes us on a literary tour of the <q direct="y">dark corners</q> of England, and the wider Atlantic Archipelago, as seen by such canonical figures of English literature as Spenser, Shakespeare, Nashe, and Jonson. Present too are a whole host of early modern lexicographers, orthographers and writers of treatises on poetics and the vernacular such as Alexander Gill, Samuel Daniel, Richard Mulcaster and George Puttenham. As Blank makes clear early on, hers is not a philological or historical investigation of English dialects, but rather of their representation in the works of these metropolitan writers; the focus is not on the rise of English in the context of the eclipse of Latin or in relation to other national vernaculars, but rather on <q direct="y">the Renaissance discovery, and elucidation, of differences within the national vernacular</q> (1). Even in her chapter on <q direct="y">Language, Laws, and Blood: The King's English and His Empire</q> (in which the focus is on Wales, Ireland and Scotland), Blank concentrates on the <q direct="y">ways that Renaissance <emph rend="italics">English</emph> writers incorporate the speech of the Welsh, the Irish, and the Scottish into the province of <emph rend="italics">English</emph> letters</q> (128; my emphasis); there is little in this chapter on either the development of the English language in these regions, or on the Welsh and Gaelic vernaculars of the majority of the inhabitants (even considered in relation to English language and culture). As she notes, <q direct="y">my concern . . . is not with 'real' dialects. . . . The 'broken English' of my title refers only to the written language, to literary dialects</q> (2).</p>
					<p n="3">This framework is, in part, dictated by the period itself: <q direct="y">In the late sixteenth and early seventeenth centuries in England, there was no such thing as dialect literature so understood</q> (3). Sandwiched between the medieval writer who wrote in the language of his birthplace (for lack of a standard, elite and / or literary national vernacular) and the later, bilingual dialect author such as Robert Burns (<q direct="y">who may choose to write in their native dialects if it suits their interests, which may be aesthetic, or ideological</q> [3]), the early modern poet or playwright can be seen to be <q direct="y">testing the bounds of what Spenser referred to as 'a kingdom of our own language' -- not only among the local shires, but among the nations that fell within England's imperial sphere</q> (128). Indeed, this testing of the bounds went beyond the geographical: included among the provincial dialects (northern and southern English, Welsh English, etc.), and interacting with them, are the <q direct="y">dialects</q> of vagabonds (or <q direct="y">cant,</q> explored in a chapter on <q direct="y">The Thieves of Language</q>) and the man of letters (neologisms and <q direct="y">inkhorn</q> language, archaisms). As Blank repeatedly notes, <q direct="y">Renaissance authors, in effect, create social dialects to articulate the lines of social class</q> (43); even when representing provincial speech, the emphasis is on the cultural values ascribed to that speech (normally in relation to the King's English of London, the court and / or the poet) and not the evocation of a particular region of England, or of Scotland, Wales or Ireland. Thus <q direct="y">although aristocrats as prominent as Sir Walter Ralegh were said to have spoken with a broad Devonshire accent . . . literary southern English was reserved for the exclusive use of 'clownish' characters</q> (80) while northern English was <q direct="y">at once the rude dialect of ploughmen and an ancestral English, . . . prosecuted as provincial and defended as the wellspring of the national language</q> (108).</p>
					<p n="4">The representation (or production: <q direct="y">social dialects are not so much represented by early modern authors, as they are produced by them</q> [38]) of provincial and social dialect says more about the poet, and Renaissance poetics, than about regional speech or <q direct="y">real</q> social groups; indeed, it often tells us more about the poet's (and the literary elite's) ideas of decorum, social class and social mobility than about those who purportedly spoke the dialect. Thus, according to Blank, Spenser's unprecedented use of northern dialect in <title level="m">The Shepheardes Calender</title> has little to do with northern England, and more to do with the poet's self-presentation <q direct="y">as an untried poet at the height of his literary powers, as a 'northern' poet deserving of southern fame</q> (124). As Blank shows, the sometimes fierce competition to authorize a national vernacular was also one in which Renaissance authors sought to authorize themselves through a <q direct="y">discriminating</q> use of dialect: <q direct="y">Renaissance writers invented the difference of English -- not only by giving form to its dialects, but by systematically endowing those forms with cultural value and meaning. . . . Demarcating the boundaries between dialects, discriminating the 'difference of English,' was enough to confer linguistic authority on writers who claimed to be in a position to judge</q> (168). The rise of the Author is here related to a process in which, by appropriating and even creating social and regional dialects, English writers carved out a literary space for themselves, a space distinguished from both <q direct="y">the people,</q> from other writers, and often from the Court and aristocratic patron.</p>
					<p n="5">Blank's focus on the representation or appropriation of language often leads to a lack of socio-historical analysis of the <q direct="y">reality</q> behind those representations; there is, for example, little discussion of why London and the court came to define standard English (which might include a discussion of the development of a national economy, of centralized governmental and legal institutions, of an urban literary <q direct="y">public sphere,</q> etc.), or how the reality of vagabondage (changes in the poor laws, a growing rift between popular and elite culture, increasing economic disparity between rich and poor) was reflected in representations of <q direct="y">cant.</q> In the sections on Wales and Ireland, the lack of historical contextualization, and the reliance on a narrow range of modernized and abridged source material (the Irish section depends almost entirely on Myers's <title level="m">Elizabethan Ireland: A Selection of Writings by Elizabethan Writers on Ireland</title>) leads to some over-generalization. However, given the amount of ground Blank covers, the genuinely original insights into major canonical texts such as Spenser's <title level="m">Shepheardes Calender</title> or Shakespeare's <title level="m">Love's Labour's Lost</title>, and the wealth of apt citations from Renaissance orthographers, lexicographers and writers of treatises on poetic diction and the vernacular, these are relatively minor flaws; the book will be of interest to a wide range of readers, especially those interested in issues of linguistic nationalism, the <q direct="y">rise of the author,</q> the representation of marginalised groups, or the history of the English language (and especially of the construction of a hegemonic standard English constructed through representations of alternative Englishes) more generally.</p>
					<div3>
						<head>Works Cited</head>
						<p>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl>Helgerson, Richard. <title level="m">Forms of Nationhood: The Elizabethan Writing of England</title>. Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1992.</bibl>
								<bibl>Maley, Willy. <title level="m">Salvaging Spenser: Colonialism, Culture and Identity</title>. Basingstoke: Macmillan, 1997.</bibl>
							</listBibl>
							<!--webbot bot="include" u-include="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/emls footer.html" tag="body" startspan -->[http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/EMLS footer.html]<!--webbot bot="include" endspan i-checksum="20494" -->
						</p>
					</div3>
					<byline>(LH, RGS, 30 March 1998)</byline>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls4-1revcum2" n="10" type="review">
					<head>James Stokes, ed. <title level="m">Records of Early English Drama: Somerset</title>. (Including Bath, ed. Robert J. Alexander). 2 Vols. Toronto: U of Toronto P, 1996. xi+1141 pp. ISBN 0 8020 0459 8 Cloth.</head>
					<!-- <img src="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/header2.gif" alt="early" modern literary studies width="283" height="87"> -->
					<opener>Review by <name>James Cummings</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>University of Leeds</addrLine>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href="mailto:engjcc@leeds.ac.uk"> -->engjcc@leeds.ac.uk<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Cummings, James. <title level="a">Review of <title level="m">Records of Early English Drama: Somerset</title>
						</title>. <title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 4.1 (May, 1998): 10.1-11 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/rev_cum2.html"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/rev_cum2.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;.</p>
					<p n="1">The REED: Somerset volumes are another valuable addition to REED's growing collection of volumes of edited dramatic records. As all those interested in renaissance entertainment should know, the aim of the project is <q direct="y">to find, transcribe, and publish external evidence of dramatic, ceremonial, and minstrel activity in Great Britain before 1642</q> (vi). In this case the editor, James Stokes, has gathered together all the records able to be found concerning Somerset, including Bath, whose records were collected by Robert J. Alexander.</p>
					<p n="2">There are two REED: Somerset volumes. The first contains the acknowledgements, table of symbols, and the meticulously edited records. These records themselves are divided into sections on Boroughs and Parishes (from Ashcott to Yeovil), Households, the Diocese of Bath and Wells, and the County of Somerset. While these divisions clearly make sense, they are not indicated in the table of contents for that volume, which simply lists them as <q direct="y">The Records</q> and does not note the sections themselves. This might prove confusing for those not having read the ample introduction contained, unexpectedly, in the second volume. The records themselves are very carefully edited and all expansions are noted in italics. Although the <q direct="y">evidence about entertainment in Somerset begins in 1225</q> (475), the majority of the extant records are from the late sixteenth and early seventeenth centuries and seem to indicate that <q direct="y">bull- and bearbaiting must have been the most popular form of entertainment in the county</q> (594).</p>
					<p n="3">Volume Two contains all of the editorial apparatus in order to enable its simultaneous use with the other volume. It begins with an introduction that contains a useful section on the historical background to the county during the period, including summaries of the civic histories of Bath, Bridgwater, Glastonbury, and Wells. This is followed by historical examinations of the 'Diocese of Bath and Wells' and well-known <q direct="y">Private Households.</q> The introduction continues with a highly useful section on <q direct="y">Drama, Music, and Popular Customs.</q> As these topics will be of interest to most readers, it is of great benefit to have a detailed examination of these activities by the editor since he is most familiar with the context from which the records have been extracted. This section draws attention to many of the interesting discoveries and trends noticed in researching the volume. If one is interested in early entertainment then this, and similar sections in other REED volumes, prove to be an invaluable aid in understanding the dramatic context of the period. It is broadly divided into discussions of the <q direct="y">Traditional Entertainment</q> mounted by communities and the <q direct="y">Touring Professional Entertainers.</q>
					</p>
					<p n="4">Within both of these sub-sections, various communities are surveyed for their amateur and professional entertainments. Moreover, in the discussion of <q direct="y">Traditional Entertainment</q> there are general examinations of <q direct="y">Playing Places,</q>
						<q direct="y">Playing Conventions,</q> and <q direct="y">Women and Performance,</q> all of which add great detail to our knowledge of early drama not only in Somerset, but in England as a whole. <q direct="y">Playing Places</q> investigates the various locations in which entertainment took place discussing the use (and perceived abuse) of church property, guildhalls, inns, city streets, open fields, and baiting sites. <q direct="y">Playing Conventions</q> explores the techniques of representation and although they seem <q direct="y">to have been generated mainly by word, action and movement</q> (493), the properties, scenery, and especially the use of costume, are briefly surveyed. The discussion of <q direct="y">Women and Performance</q> indicates that, contrary to popular belief, women were indeed involved in early drama, and a variety of entertainments, at an early date. The sub-section discussing <q direct="y">Touring Professional Entertainers</q> examines a variety of travelling performers as they go through Bath, Bridgwater, and Wells. This is followed by a brief discussion of the <q direct="y">Waits and Local Musicians</q> in these same cities, and then the <q direct="y">Royal Visits</q> which concentrates on Queen Anne's visits to Bath and Wells.</p>
					<p n="5">The next section of the introduction is entitled <q direct="y">The Documents</q> and is a detailed document description of all the documents from which extracts have been transcribed. The meticulous descriptions are organised in the same manner as the records themselves. Moreover, as all classmarks, as well as a variety of documentary idiosyncrasies, are provided, researchers are well equipped to return to the original documents if they choose.</p>
					<p n="6">The section following the document descriptions is, rightly, a discussion of the project's <q direct="y">Editorial Procedures.</q> This describes their <q direct="y">Principles of Selection</q> for determining what to include as <q direct="y">dramatic, secular musical, and ceremonial or customal performances before 1642</q> (594). Recent REED volumes have seen a developing willingness to include more so-called <q direct="y">para-dramatic</q> activities that are not necessarily mimetic in themselves, but certainly were considered as entertainment during the period. Nevertheless, the principles of selection are one of the aspects that sometimes cause confusion for researchers and editors alike. In general, only entries which specifically mention something that falls under the guidelines have been included. Some less certain records have been gathered into the appendices; however, many references that might enable us to paint more fully a picture of the life of performers at the time have been omitted because they are not strictly references to dramatic activity in themselves. And yet, this provides a fruitful area of opportunity for later researchers who wish to return to the original documents. The section on <q direct="y">Editorial Procedures</q> continues with sub-sections on the problems and adopted conventions of <q direct="y">Dating,</q> a section detailing the workings of <q direct="y">Ecclesiastical Court Cases,</q> and concludes with a section on <q direct="y">Editorial Conventions</q> which explains the reasons for many decisions of presentation, transcription, and expansion. This introduction, which is really necessary reading before examining the records in volume one, is followed by the <q direct="y">Notes</q> for that introductory section. This should not be confused with the notes for the records or the appendices that are provided (together) after the translations. A <q direct="y">Select Bibliography</q> is provided as well as early maps for Somerset with Bath inset (1610), Wells (1735), and their own map of Somerset with locations mentioned in the records.</p>
					<p n="7">There are eleven appendices of additional material that contain extracts and discussions of material which did not strictly belong in the body of the records. These include such divergent entries as poems about, and a chronology of, the Wells Shows of 1607, extracts from Royal Household Accounts, other songs and poems, as well as extracts of <q direct="y">Post-1642 Documents</q> indicating the continuation of various folk activities well into the commonwealth period. The fourth appendix is the largest (substantially so) and includes a discussion and the records concerning <q direct="y">The Somerset Hogglers.</q> Hoggling is a gathering or fund-raising activity most likely similar to that of hogmanay found farther north in Britain. These extracts are included as an appendix because, although entertainment is known to have formed a part of the hoggling in Keynsham and it is most likely to have been the case in other locations, few documentary references have been found that explicitly connect them.</p>
					<p n="8">The appendices are followed by translations (by Abigail Ann Young) of almost all of the Latin records in volume one. The translations are well done and save a great deal of time even for those well-versed in Latin. The only possible flaw is the overuse of their symbol <q direct="y">(English)</q> which is used to denote when the English section of mixed English and Latin documents is exempted; when reading some of the depositions it was highly confusing to look back and forth between the two volumes.</p>
					<p n="9">The substantial translations are followed by the <q direct="y">Endnotes.</q> These endnotes do not include the <q direct="y">Notes</q> for the introductory matter, and moreover are followed by the list of <q direct="y">Patrons and Travelling Companies</q> (by Arleane Ralph), the extremely helpful glossaries (by Abigail Ann Young [Latin] and William Cooke [English]), and a useful and intuitive index. Although in the <q direct="y">correct</q> place, it may seem strange to some readers to have over 154 pages of material following the endnotes, and for them not to include all the notes for the volumes.</p>
					<p n="10">This confusion highlights one of my only problems with the volumes, and that is their organisation. There are many benefits to having only the records in the first volume and the entire editorial apparatus in the second volume - it allows simultaneous use of the introduction, glossaries, and notes, with the records themselves. Experienced users of REED volumes should have no problems in finding their way; nevertheless, it may prove mildly confusing to newer readers that the introduction is in volume two (starting on page 449), that there is a distinction between notes and endnotes, and that the bibliography is followed by 514 pages of editorial extras.</p>
					<p n="11">The reasons for some of the decisions are abundantly clear, and the overwhelming desire to have this simultaneity of use for both volumes is laudable, but the division seems undone with the page numbering continuing from one volume to the other. Although saving the reader from flipping backwards and forwards in one immense volume, in some cases it only adds to the confusion of needing continually to consult the table of contents. Moreover, it would be an additional benefit if the table of contents in each volume also listed the contents of the other volume. And yet, the records are so meticulously edited, and of such benefit to any scholar interested, not only in the nature of Medieval and Early-Modern dramatic activity, but the culture of the period as a whole, that its mere existence forgives any minor failings. It is a noteworthy addition to the growing collection of REED volumes.</p>
					<p>
						<!--webbot bot="include" u-include="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/emls footer.html" tag="body" startspan -->[http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/EMLS footer.html]<!--webbot bot="include" endspan i-checksum="20494" -->
					</p>
					<byline>(LH, RGS, 9 March 1998)</byline>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls4-1revlak3" n="11" type="review">
					<!-- <img src="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/header2.gif" alt="early" modern literary studies width="283" height="87"> -->
					<head>James D. Tracy. <title level="m">Erasmus of the Low Countries</title>. Berkeley, California: U of California P, 1996. ix+297 pp. ISBN 0 520 08745 3 Cloth. <emph rend="italics"> Desiderius Erasmus. <title level="m">Colloquies</title>. Translated and annotated by Craig R. Thompson. Collected Works of Erasmus, Vols. 39-40. Toronto: U of Toronto P, 1997. 2 vols. xlix+1227 pp. ISBN 0 8020 5819 1 Cloth.</emph>
					</head>
					<opener>Review by <name>Romuald Ian Lakowski</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href="mailto:romualdi@unixg.ubc.ca"> -->romualdi@unixg.ubc.ca<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Lakowski, Romuald Ian. <title level="a">Review of <title level="m">Erasmus of the Low Countries</title> and Desiderius Erasmus: <title level="m">Colloquies</title>
						</title>. <title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 4.1 (May, 1998): 11.1-10 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/[path]/[filename.html]"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/rev_lak3.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;.</p>
					<p n="1">James D. Tracy's <title level="m">Erasmus of the Low Countries</title> is a delight to read, and certainly one of the better biographies of Erasmus to appear in recent years (of which there have been many). Tracy, a Renaissance historian, who has published two books on the history of the Habsburg Netherlands and two earlier studies of Erasmus, locates Erasmus firmly within the historical and cultural context of the early modern Burgundian-Habsburg Low Countries (roughly equivalent to the modern Benelux region). Tracy's work compares favourably with the recent biography of Erasmus by the Dutch scholar Cornelis Augustijn, <title level="m">Erasmus: His Life, Works and Influence</title>, though on the whole Tracy gives a much more optimistic interpretation to Erasmus' life than Augustijn does. Tracy's biography is divided into three sections: <title level="a">Part I. <title level="m">Bonae Literae</title>: The Making of a Low Countries Humanist, 1469-1511</title>, <title level="a">Part II. <title level="m">Philosophia Christi</title>: Erasmus and the Reform of <title level="m">Doctrina</title>, 1511-1522</title>, and <title level="a">Part III. Second Thoughts, 1521-1536</title>. </p>
					<p n="2">In Part I, Tracy begins by describing the highly corporate and urbanised society of the Burgundian Low Countries. In sharp contrast to many earlier scholars, including Craig R. Thompson, who portrayed Erasmus in very European and <q direct="y">cosmopolitan</q> terms, an image that Erasmus himself deliberately cultivated, Tracy emphasises how Erasmus' religious individualism <q direct="y">can best be understood as a reaction against the highly corporatist character of civil and religious life in his native provinces. Like many who have achieved fame, Erasmus bore the stamp of his homeland even in those areas where he differed from the common opinions of his countrymen</q> (3). In the course of his study, Tracy demonstrates how certain Burgundian or Netherlandish attitudes remained with Erasmus all his life. Much of Tracy's biography naturally focuses on Erasmus' voluminous literary output. In Part I, he devotes most attention to the <title level="m">Enchiridion</title> (Handbook of the Christian Soldier) and the <title level="m">Praise of Folly</title> as embodying Erasmus' Christian Neo-Platonic vision of Christian civility and its obverse. </p>
					<p n="3">Part II focuses on Erasmus' career as a <q direct="y">Reformer of <title level="m">Doctrina</title>.</q> The Latin term encompasses both religious and theological reform on the one hand, and also the reform of <q direct="y">teaching</q> and the defence of <emph rend="italics">bonae litterae</emph> on the other. Tracy locates Erasmus within the tradition of rhetorical theology embodied for example in St. Augustine's <title level="m">De doctrina Christiana</title>, though he also notes Erasmus' ambivalence towards Augustine (55-57, 70-72, 151-154). After comparing Erasmus with three other humanist <q direct="y">reformers:</q> Lorenzo Valla, Juan Luis Vives and John Calvin, Tracy goes on to discuss Erasmus' middle period, especially his ideas on reform and his diagnosis of the evils of his own age, and his restatement or reformulation of the Evangelical <title level="m">doctrina</title> of the Gospels as the <title level="m">Philosophia Christi</title>, itself a Patristic term, and finally his call for the defence of <emph rend="italics">Bonae Litterae</emph> (not only <q direct="y">fine letters</q> but also <q direct="y">careful scholarship.</q>) </p>
					<p n="4">Part III deals with Erasmus' complex and often stormy relationships with his conservative foes in the Catholic Church, which he never left, though highly critical of its corruption and abuses, especially among the religious orders. It also describes Erasmus' equally difficult relationships with his foes among the Protestant Reformers, whom he criticized for their violence and vehemence, and for their theological excesses, even while he continued to dialogue and correspond with them. After his account of Erasmus' polemical battles with his various theological opponents, Tracy then turns to deal with Erasmus' arguments for a limited religious toleration or <emph rend="italics">concordia</emph>, and how this was frustrated by the increasing confessionalization that followed the Reformation. Then Tracy turns to the question of Erasmus' rhetorical <emph rend="italics">dissimulatio</emph>, his use of deliberately ambiguous language in an a attempt to please both Catholics and Protestants, and of how this rhetorical strategy may have backfired on Erasmus. In his final Chapter, Tracy deals with Erasmus' complex relationships with his readers in different countries and ends with the example of Poland (191-203). Tracy sees Erasmus' support for Poland in both its dealings with the Habsburg Emperors and the Ottoman invaders of Hungary as partly reflecting Erasmus' own Burgundian suspicions of Habsburg plans for world domination.  </p>
					<p n="5">It is almost impossible to do justice to a writer as voluminous and varied as Erasmus in a single volume biography. Tracy's study will be appreciated most by those who are already Erasmus scholars. For those wishing an introduction to Erasmus, the best place is to start with Erasmus' own works, many of which have now been published in excellent modern English translations, together with compendious scholarly notes, by the University of Toronto Press. (Forty volumes have appeared so far, and almost fifty more are planned.) The latest of these is a double volume of over 1200 pages containing Erasmus' <title level="m">Colloquies</title>. </p>
					<p n="6">The Toronto translation of Erasmus' <title level="m">Colloquies</title> is a revision of an earlier translation made by Craig R. Thompson, <title level="m">The Colloquies of Erasmus</title>, some of which also appeared earlier in the Library of Liberal Arts Series as <title level="m">Ten Colloquies</title>. Even before that, Thompson's earliest contribution to Erasmus scholarship consisted of an edition of one of the most important colloquies, the <title level="m">Inquisitio de Fide</title>, together with an extensive introduction and notes. The Chicago translation contained brief introductions to the individual colloquies but no commentary, which Thompson had originally planned to publish in a second volume. The revised Toronto translation includes several hundred pages of annotations, making it almost double the size of the original Chicago edition. Thompson died before he could finish the edition, but the great bulk of the notes (the longest of which extend over several pages of fine print) obviously derive from his pen. The remaining annotations were supplied by individual members of the Editorial Board of the Collected Works of Erasmus, but only Thompson's name appears on the title page. A modern critical edition of the original Latin text, with introduction and notes in French, was published in the <title level="m">Opera omnia Desiderii Erasmi Roterodami</title>, edited by L. E. Halkin, F. Bierlaire, and R. Hoven (reviewed by Thompson in <title level="j">Renaissance Quarterly</title> 27 (1974): 196-198). A modern French translation by &Eacute;tienne Wolff also exists: <title level="m">&Eacute;rasme: Colloques</title>, but it contains only the briefest of notes. </p>
					<p n="7">The <title level="m">Familiarum colloquiorum formulae</title> began as a very modest collection of <emph rend="italics">formulae</emph> or patterns for polite conversation and good Latin writing that Erasmus compiled for his students in Paris (c.1497-1500) when he was eking out a precarious living as a tutor while studying scholastic theology at the Sorbonne. He lent a manuscript copy to a friend and fellow tutor in Paris, Augustinus Vincentius Caminadus, who despite repeated pleas refused to return it. Many years later Caminadus' manuscript was published in November 1518 in an unauthorized edition by Johan Froben (Basle) with a preface by Erasmus' friend Beatus Rhenanus, and was reprinted at least thirty times before March 1522. An <q direct="y">Authorized</q> edition emended by Erasmus was published in March 1519 by Dirk Martens (Antwerp). The 1518 <title level="m">Familiar Colloquies</title> was a modest volume of 80 pages, most of which was included in the later revised editions from 1522 onwards. In Thompson's translation in the <title level="m">Collected Works of Erasmus</title> [abbreviated <title level="m">CWE</title>], this material can be found on pp. 5- 34 and pp. 118-170. In the 1522 edition some of this material was given a distinct title as <q direct="y">The Profane Feast</q> (132-163). It was followed by <q direct="y">A Short Rule for Copiousness</q> (164-170), which contains an early version of material expanded in the <title level="m">De Copia</title> (1512), one of Erasmus' most important rhetorical works. The 1518/1519 <emph rend="italics">formulae</emph> contain numerous examples of polite, idiomatic Latin greetings and conversational exchanges <q direct="y">with variations for greeting friends, inquiring after ordinary affairs of life, and making proper acknowledgments or replies required by social decorum</q> (xxiv-xxv). In addition, they also included short rudimentary dialogues. However, starting in 1522, this modest manual of Latin discourse went through an extraordinary transformation to become, eventually, one of the greatest masterpieces of Renaissance Neo-Latin literature. </p>
					<p n="8">The <title level="m">Colloquies</title> went through several major revisions and expansions in the course of Erasmus' lifetime. Beginning in 1522 Erasmus added new colloquies or dialogues to each new edition: eleven in the editions of 1522, ten more in 1523, and ten more in 1524 (all to be found in <title level="m">CWE</title> 39); with further additions in 1526, 1527, 1529, 1531 and 1533 (in <title level="m">CWE</title> 40). By the time of Erasmus' death in 1536, the work comprised some sixty odd colloquies and an appendix on <q direct="y">The Usefulness of the <title level="m">Colloquies</title>.</q> In its final form the <title level="m">Colloquies</title> became a book of dialogues in the tradition of Plato, Lucian and Plutarch, Cicero, Augustine and Boethius. (Erasmus translated many of Lucian's and Plutarch's dialogues into Latin.) The <title level="m">Colloquies</title> touch on almost every aspect of the society of Erasmus' day: a veritable Renaissance Canterbury Tales. While some of the shorter colloquies carry on the educational program of the original editions of 1518/1519, dealing with topics such as the education of youth, sport and recreation, many of the other longer colloquies deal with social and religious abuses, the beginnings of the Reformation conflicts, philosophical and philological questions, moral and political issues, marriage and the treatment of women. </p>
					<p n="9">Some of the best of these longer colloquies are like one-act plays in their plotting, comparable with the best medieval mystery pageants and renaissance interludes, as Thompson writes: <q direct="y">The author had a dramatist's eye for situations and scenes, but what he writes are not dramas in any formal sense, for the action is recalled or implied or described; we </q>see<q direct="y"> it or imagine it through the author's art in setting it forth within dialogue. None the less, like much good fiction it has the potentiality of being staged, of becoming theatre</q> (xxvii). Six of the colloquies are banquets or <emph rend="italics">convivia</emph> (133), including <title level="a">The Profane Feast</title>, <title level="a">The Godly Feast</title>, <title level="a">The Poetic Feast</title>, <title level="a">The Fabulous Feast</title>, <title level="a">A Feast of Many Courses</title>, <title level="a">The Sober Feast</title>. Another ten deal with marriage and the treatment of women. The Marriage Group (256) consists of <title level="a">Courtship</title>, <title level="a">The Girl with No Interest in Marriage</title>, <title level="a">The Repentant Girl</title>, <title level="a">Marriage</title>, <title level="a">The Young Man and the Harlot</title>, <title level="a">The Abbot and the Learned Lady</title>, <title level="a">The Epithalamium of Pieter Gillis</title>, <title level="a">The New Mother</title>, <title level="a">A Marriage in Name only</title>, and <title level="a">The Council of Women</title>. Yet another group deals often very critically with corruption and abuses within the Church, especially within monasticism and the preaching friars. These include (cf. 283) <title level="a">Rash Vows</title>, <title level="a">The Soldier and the Carthusian</title>, <title level="a">The Well-to-do Beggars</title>, <title level="a">The Shipwreck</title>, <title level="a">The Old Men's Chat</title>, <title level="a">The Abbot and the Learned Lady</title>, <title level="a">A Pilgrimage for Religion's Sake</title>, <title level="a">A Fish Diet</title>, <title level="a">The Funeral</title>, <title level="a">The Sermon</title>, <title level="a">The Seraphic Funeral</title>, <title level="a">The Girl with No Interest in Marriage</title>. And at least one of the colloquies deals with issues raised by the Protestant Reformation: <title level="a">An Examination concerning the Faith</title>. (Here Thompson refers repeatedly in his notes to his own earlier 1950 edition of this colloquy.) However, no classification scheme can do justice to the richness and variety of topics covered in the <title level="m">Colloquies</title>.  </p>
					<p n="10">Starting in Erasmus' own lifetime, numerous individual colloquies were translated into just about every different European vernacular, including even one into Old Irish. Both in the original Latin texts and through the various sixteenth and seventeenth century translations, Erasmus' <title level="m">Colloquies</title> had a widespread influence on many later Renaissance writers including Shakespeare. Among Erasmus' literary works only the <title level="m">Praise of Folly</title> has enjoyed greater fame. While not all of the colloquies can be considered great literature, many of them are delightfully witty expos&eacute;s of the vices and virtues, follies and troubles of the men and women of Erasmus' own age. Together with Erasmus' Correspondence, which is also being translated by Toronto (eleven volumes have appeared so far), the <title level="m">Colloquies</title> provide us with a view unparallelled in its richness and diversity of the life and times of early sixteenth century Europe. There is something there for anyone interested in the Renaissance period.</p>
					<div3>
						<head>Works Cited</head>
						<p>
							<listBibl>
								<bibl>Augustijn, Cornelis. <title level="m">Erasmus: His Life, Works and Influence</title>. Toronto: U of Toronto P, 1991; Paperback ed. 1995.</bibl>
								<bibl>Halkin, L. E., F. Bierlaire, and R. Hoven., eds. <title level="m">Colloquia</title> in <title level="m">Opera omnia Desiderii Erasmi Roterodami</title>. Volume 1/3. Amsterdam: North-Holland Publishing Co., 1972.</bibl>
								<bibl>Thompson, Craig, R., ed. <title level="m">Inquisitio de Fide</title>. New Haven: Yale UP, 1950.</bibl>
								<bibl>---, trans. <title level="m">Ten Colloquies</title>. New York: Liberal Arts Press, 1957.</bibl>
								<bibl>---, trans. <title level="m">The Colloquies of Erasmus</title>. Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1965.</bibl>
								<bibl>Wolff, &Eacute;tienne, trans. <title level="m">&Eacute;rasme: Colloques</title>. 2 vols. Paris: Imprimerie nationale &Eacute;ditions, 1992.</bibl>
							</listBibl>
						</p>
						<p>
							<!--webbot bot="include" u-include="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/emls footer.html" tag="body" startspan -->[http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/EMLS footer.html]<!--webbot bot="include" endspan i-checksum="20494" -->
						</p>
					</div3>
					<byline>(LH, RGS, 10 June 1998)</byline>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls4-1revgor1" n="12" type="review">
					<head>Ann Thompson and Sasha Roberts, eds. <title level="m">Women Reading Shakespeare 1660-1900: An Anthology of Criticism.</title> Manchester and New York: Manchester UP, 1997. ISBN 0 7190 4704 8 Paper; 0 7190 4703 X Cloth.</head>
					<!-- <img src="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/header2.gif" alt="early" modern literary studies width="283" height="87"> -->
					<opener>Review by <name>Christine Mack Gordon</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>College of Liberal Arts, University of Minnesota</addrLine>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href="mailto:gordo003@maroon.tc.umn.edu"> -->gordo003@maroon.tc.umn.edu<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Gordon, Christine Mack. <title level="a">Review of <title level="m">Women Reading Shakespeare 1660-1900: An Anthology of Criticism</title>.</title>
						<title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 4.1 (May, 1998):12.1-5 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/rev_gor1.html"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/rev_gor1.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;.</p>
					<p n="1">In the time period covered by this collection, few if any women were acknowledged as scholars. Nonetheless women read, discussed, acted in, and wrote about the works of Shakespeare. Thanks to editors Ann Thompson and Sasha Roberts, we now have the opportunity to read and consider the works of these neglected critics. From Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of Newcastle, who wrote what is the first critical essay on Shakespeare ever published (in 1664), through Mary Bradford-Whiting whose essay on <q direct="y">Mothers in Shakespeare</q> appeared in 1898, the work of forty-two intelligent, articulate, and provocative women gives the interested reader in the waning years of the twentieth century an opportunity to explore the ways in which criticism both reflects and transcends the concerns of a particular time and place.</p>
					<p n="2">Nearly all these writers are intensely engaged with their subject matter, whether they are preparing to play a role onstage, to re-tell the stories of the plays for a young audience, to create a previous history for some of the characters, to edit the plays for publication, or to share their enthusiasm with a general audience -- often with the members of various Shakespeare societies and clubs that flourished in the nineteenth century. Not too surprisingly, their opinions on particular issues or characters within the plays are remarkably diverse. Every reader will find her or his own favourites among these writers; I was perhaps most intrigued by the analyses offered by the actors playing the various characters, especially -- as with Adelaide Ristori's reflections on Lady Macbeth -- when the actor had difficulty sympathizing with the character she was to play.</p>
					<p n="3">The time period or the particular culture in which each woman wrote sometimes affects significantly her understanding or appreciation of a given work; this was most apparent in Mary Preston's comments on <title level="m">Othello</title>. Preston, apparently a Confederate sympathizer in the American Civil War, comments initially <q direct="y">How <title level="m">natural</title> is the origin of <title level="m">this love-match</title>! Two streams rushing from different directions find, at last, the same outlet -- the ocean.</q> But soon she admits that in studying the play, she has always imagined its hero as a white man; Shakespeare's imagination here was <q direct="y">one of the few erroneous strokes of the great master's brush, the <title level="m">single</title> blemish on a faultless work.</q> More subtly, in some of the other essays, we can see how the cultural expectations of women affect a writer's interpretation of a particular role or the whole of a play. Yet what surprises and delights is how often these writers see beyond the limitations (or what we believe these limitations to be) of their own lives and cultures; for anyone who continues to find something we daringly describe as <q direct="y">universals</q> in Shakespeare's work, these essays will offer at least some confirmation.</p>
					<p n="4">Unlike contemporary scholars, who must please the palate of their peers, these writers spoke to a more general audience, but one with a serious interest in this shared subject matter. They are able to explore issues of the day in the context of the arguments of the plays, to see both immediate and transcendent value in the creations of Shakespeare's imagination. As writers, editors, and theatre artists, they explored the multiple meanings of Shakespeare's work, and gave their own voices to the on-going cultural conversation. We should be grateful to the editors for restoring them to us.</p>
					<p n="5">In addition to the selection of work, Thompson and Roberts also provide an introduction that defines the social and cultural contexts within which these women wrote, a helpful list of quick reference topics that point readers to particular issues of interest, as well as a bibliography of primary and secondary sources, a general index, and an index of works by Shakespeare. They have also found illustrations by women of Shakespeare's work to enhance the volume. Since the work of most of these writers is out of print, this anthology offers readers an <title level="m">entr&eacute;e </title>into a substantial body of thoughtful criticism that would otherwise be lost. The editors acknowledge that the collection is <q direct="y">neither complete nor definitive,</q> and explain their criteria for inclusion, noting that they have <q direct="y">collected enough material for ten volumes of this size.</q> Nonetheless, this superb compilation will be of interest to anyone interested in Shakespeare, in the development of women as writers, critics, editors, and actors, and in the general intellectual history of women.</p>
					<p>
						<!--webbot bot="include" u-include="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/emls footer.html" tag="body" startspan -->[http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/EMLS footer.html]<!--webbot bot="include" endspan i-checksum="20494" -->
					</p>
					<byline>(LH, RGS, 30 March 1998)</byline>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls4-1revcirr" n="13" type="review">
					<!-- <img src="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/header2.gif" alt="early" modern literary studies width="283" height="87"> -->
					<head>John M. Mucciolo, Editor. Assisted by Steven J. Doloff and Edward A. Rauchut. <title level="m">Shakespeare's Universe: Renaissance Ideas and Conventions (Essays in Honour of W.R. Elton)</title>. Hampshire and Vermont: Scolar P, 1996. xii + 292 pp. ISBN 1 85928 193 1 Cloth.</head>
					<opener>Review by <name>Steve Cirrone</name>
						<address>
							<addrLine>Center for Higher Education</addrLine>
							<addrLine>
								<!-- <a href="mailto:bardsf@aol.com"> -->BardSF@aol.com<!-- </a> -->
							</addrLine>
						</address>
					</opener>
					<p rend="centre">Cirrone, Steve. <title level="a">Review of <title level="m">Shakespeare's Universe: Renaissance Ideas and Conventions (Essays in Honour of W.R. Elton)</title>.</title>
						<title level="j">Early Modern Literary Studies</title> 4.1 (May, 1998): 13.1-4 &lt;URL: <!-- <a href="http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/rev_cirr.html"> -->http://purl.oclc.org/emls/04-1/rev_cirr.html<!-- </a> -->&gt;.</p>
					<p n="1">
						<title level="m">Shakespeare's Universe</title> is a selection of essays gathered together under five categories to honour the late Shakespeare scholar-critic William R. Elton, the categories being <q direct="y">Shakespeare, Politics and Religion,</q>
						<q direct="y">Shakespeare and Gender,</q>
						<q direct="y">Shakespeare and Staging,</q>
						<q direct="y">Shakespeare and Language</q> and <q direct="y">Shakespeare and Criticism.</q> Each category is made up of three to six essays, most of which make intriguing, though at times tenuous, critiques of various aspects of Renaissance literary history. According to the editor, the text's collective critical spirit stems from a central document of Shakespeare criticism, Johnson's <title level="m">Preface</title> (1768), but I fail to see the document itself or its spirit playing any major role here. What is evident, however, is that most of the essays endeavour to construct their arguments according to the tenets of new historicism. The preface states that each essay attempts to challenge the practical application of certain Renaissance <q direct="y">truths</q> or universals by examining the microstructures (historical nuances) present in the individual and culture. The volume's preface also promises that the essays collectively set out to fashion the broader implication that <q direct="y">universal appeal cannot result from mere generality; rather, it must equally feed off the natural which, in turn, must exist primarily at the level of textual or individual specificity.</q> This implication has the sound of intelligence yet, unfortunately, what is meant by <q direct="y">the natural</q> is left unclear both in the preface and throughout the entire volume.</p>
					<p n="2">Additionally, since the text's scope seems somewhat ambitious for one volume, the essays collected herein do little but scratch the surface of the subject of each category. And although the title and categorical organization of the text plainly states that a strong Shakespeare-based thread connects the essays in the volume, none of the essays deals exclusively with the historical contextualization of Shakespeare's work, and others barely mention Shakespeare at all. Additionally, few of the essays included in this volume actually make use of the historicist arguments laid bare in Elton's monumental work, <title level="m">King Lear and the Gods</title>. Such incongruity results in a text of insightful scholarly materials collected under an umbrella title, leaving one to wonder what exactly the standard for submission and acceptance must have been. Perhaps there is an intrinsic problem in a labour of love such as this: any one text that sets out to praise a scholarly giant such as Elton is bound to come up thin.</p>
					<p n="3">This is not to say that the essays themselves are all without critical merit. Despite the rather inconsonant complexity of the text, several essays in this volume stand as works of genuine critical insight in and of themselves. Of particular interest is the essay by George Walton Williams, <q direct="y">Hamlet and the Dread Commandment,</q> which rephrases Hamlet's traditional indecisiveness into a textually based argument for seeing Hamlet's agonizing as a representation of the political and social ramifications of the plight of a son who challenges the direct commandment of his father. Williams delicately and intelligently constructs his argument by comparing Hamlet's decision-making process with those of Laertes and Fortinbras. (All three have been given injunctions by a father or father-figure.) Also recommended is the essay by T.H. Howard-Hill, <q direct="y">U and Non-U: Class and Discourse Level in <title level="m">Othello</title>,</q> which examines in somewhat Marxist fashion the way in which the linguistic differences between Cassio and Iago suggest that class remains the single most defining relationship between them and that class-clash must be considered to be part of the motivation for Iago's consuming distemper. Howard-Hill's judicious and historically specific essay sheds new light on the motivations of an enigmatic Iago that may indeed be a figure attempting to fight for, from Iago's perspective, social justice.</p>
					<p n="4">Of the other twenty-one essays collected in this volume, <q direct="y">'A Liberal Tongue': Language and Rebellion in Richard II,</q> by David Norbrook, and <q direct="y">Perspective in Troilus and Cressida,</q> by Francois Laroque, also deserve special mention, not only for their intellectual power to persuade -- though this too is evident -- but also for their adequacy in questioning the known universe of Shakespeare by a close examination of certain historical influences found in the texts themselves. Just as important, both Norbrook's and Laroque's approaches to their subject matters fit nicely with most of the promises of the volume as outlined in Mucciolo's introduction. And in the volume as a whole, many of the essays do try very hard to persuade the reader through the sheer power of well-written arguments; but I would caution the reader in closing by saying also that a number of these essays fumble through or overlook plausible historical grounds for argumentation in favour of using an abundance of critical jargon.</p>
					<p>
						<!--webbot bot="include" u-include="http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/emls footer.html" tag="body" startspan -->[http://asgard.humn.arts.ualberta.ca/emls/EMLS footer.html]<!--webbot bot="include" endspan i-checksum="20494" -->
					</p>
					<byline>(RGS, 30 March 1998)</byline>
				</div2>
				<div2 id="emls4-1revbook" type="reviewinfo">
					<!-- <img src="../header2.gif" alt="early" modern literary studies width="283" height="87"> -->
					<head>Reviewing Information, Books Received for Review, and Forthcoming Reviews</head>
					<p rend="centre">- <ref target="emls4-1revbookinformation">Reviewing Information</ref> | <ref target="emls4-1revbookreceived">Books Received for Review</ref> | <ref target="emls4-1revbookforthcoming">Forthcoming Reviews</ref> -</p>
					<div3 id="emls4-1revbookinformation">
						<div4>
							<head>Reviewing Information</head>
							<p>
								<title level="j">EMLS</title> invites reviews of recent scholarly works -- critical editions, commentaries, and theoretical, historical, literary, or interdisciplinary criticism which centres on sixteenth- or seventeenth-century English or related literary culture. We also encourage reports of all resources which are relevant to literary studies of the period, including those available exclusively in the electronic medium.</p>
							<p>Our aim is to publish reviews of a consistently high standard, which are both engaging and critically fair, written by a broad range of people at different stages of their academic careers with varied disciplinary backgrounds.</p>
						</div4>
						<div4>
							<head>Requests to Review</head>
							<p>Requests to review books listed below, or proposals for reviews of other new titles, together with a brief description of reviewers' academic qualifications, publications or research interests should be sent to Lisa Hopkins, the Associate Editor (Reviews), at <!-- <a href="mailto:l.m.hopkins@shu.ac.uk"> -->L.M.Hopkins@shu.ac.uk<!-- </a> --> or by regular mail to the School of Cultural Studies, Sheffield Hallam University, Collegiate Crescent Campus, Sheffield, UK, S10 2BP.</p>
						</div4>
						<div4>
							<head>Submission of Materials for Review</head>
							<p>Materials for review may be sent to Lisa Hopkins, the Associate Editor (Reviews), at the above address. Please note that all unsolicited materials sent to <title level="j">EMLS</title> for the purposes of review must be plainly marked with the word <q direct="y">Donation</q> on the front of the mailing cover.</p>
						</div4>
					</div3>
					<div3 id="emls4-1revbookreceived">
						<head>Books Received for Review as of May 1998:</head>
						<p>
							<list>
								<item>Beer, Anna. <title level="m">Sir Walter Ralegh and his Readers in the Seventeenth Century.</title> Basingstoke: Macmillan, 1997.</item>
								<item>Biester, James. <title level="m">Lyric Wonder: Rhetoric and Wit in Renaissance English Poetry.</title> Ithaca: Cornell UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Bulman, James. <title level="m">Shakespeare: Theory and Performance.</title> London: Routledge, 1995.</item>
								<item>Burnett, Mark Thornton. <title level="m">Masters and Servants in English Renaissance Drama and Culture: Authority and Obedience.</title> Basingstoke: Macmillan, 1997.</item>
								<item>Combe, Kirk. <title level="m">A Martyr for Sin: Rochester's Critique of Polity, Sexuality, and Society.</title> Newark: U of Delaware P, 1998.</item>
								<item>Cox, John D., and David Scott Kastan, eds. <title level="m">A New History of Early English Drama.</title> New York: Columbia UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Cox, John F. <title level="m">Much Ado About Nothing in Production.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Davis, Philip. <title level="m">Sudden Shakespeare: The Shaping of Shakespeare's Creative Thought.</title> London: Athlone P, 1996.</item>
								<item>De Grazia, Margreta, Maureen Quilligan, and Peter Stallybrass, eds. <title level="m">Subject and Object in Renaissance Culture.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1996.</item>
								<item>Demaray, John G. <title level="m">Shakespeare and the Spectacles of Strangeness: The Tempest and the Transformation of Renaissance Theatrical Forms.</title> Pittsburgh: Duquesne UP, 1998.</item>
								<item>Dillon, Janette. <title level="m">Language and Stage in Medieval and Renaissance England.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1998.</item>
								<item>Fowler, Elizabeth and Roland Greene, eds. <title level="m">The Project of Prose in Early Modern Europe and the New World.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Fonte, Moderata (Modesta Pozzo) <title level="m">The Worth of Women.</title> Ed. Virginia Cox. Trans. Virginia Cox. Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1997.</item>
								<item>Forker, Charles R., ed. <title level="m">Richard II: The Critical Tradition.</title> London: Athlone P, 1998.</item>
								<item>Garin, Eugenio, ed. <title level="m">Renaissance Characters.</title> Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1997.</item>
								<item>Hale, John K. <title level="m">The Shakespeare of the Comedies.</title> 2nd ed. Berlin: Peter Lang, 1997. </item>
								<item>Halpern, Richard. <title level="m">Shakespeare Among the Moderns.</title> Ithaca: Cornell UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Henke, Robert. <title level="m">Pastoral Transformations: Italian Tragicomedy and Shakespeare's Late Plays.</title> Newark: U of Delaware P, 1997.</item>
								<item>Hillman, Richard. <title level="m">Self-Speaking in Medieval and Early Modern English Drama.</title> Basingstoke: Macmillan, 1997.</item>
								<item>Holland, Peter. <title level="m">English Shakespeares: Shakespeare on the English Stage in the 1990s.</title> Cambridge: CUP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Honigmann, E.A.J. <title level="m">Myriad-Minded Shakespeare</title>. 2nd ed. Basingstoke: Macmillan, 1998.</item>
								<item>Innes, Paul. <title level="m">Shakespeare and the English Renaissance Sonnet.</title> Basingstoke: Macmillan, 1997.</item>
								<item>Jehlan, Myra and Michael Warner, eds. <title level="m">The English Literatures of America.</title> New York: Routledge, 1996.</item>
								<item>Kamps, Ivo. <title level="m">Historiography and Ideology in Stuart Drama.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Klein, Lisa M. <title level="m">The Exemplary Sidney and the Elizabethan Sonneteer.</title> Newark: U of Delaware P, 1998.</item>
								<item>Kronenfeld, Judy. <title level="m">King Lear and the Naked Truth.</title> Durham: Duke UP, 1998.</item>
								<item>Kuller Shuger, Debora. <title level="m">The Renaissance Bible: Scholarship, Sacrifice, and Subjectivity.</title> Berkeley: U of California P, 1998.</item>
								<item>Lewis, Cynthia. <title level="m">Particular Saints: Shakespeare's Four Antonios, Their Contexts and Their Plays.</title> Newark: U of Delaware P, 1997.</item>
								<item>Lieb, Michael. <title level="m">The Sinews of Ulysses: Form and Convention in Milton's Works.</title> Pittsburgh: Duquesne UP, 1989.</item>
								<item>Loxley, James. <title level="m">Royalism and Poetry in the English Civil Wars.</title> Basingstoke: Macmillan, 1997.</item>
								<item>Lucking, David. <title level="m">Plays Upon the Word: Shakespeare's Drama of Language.</title> Lecce: Edizioni Milella, 1997.</item>
								<item>Mallette, Richard. <title level="m">Spenser and the Discourses of Reformation England.</title> Lincoln and London: U of Nebraska P, 1997.</item>
								<item>Maquerlot, Jean-Pierre. <title level="m">Shakespeare and the Mannerist Tradition: A Reading of Five Problem Plays.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1995.</item>
								<item>Martin, Christopher. <title level="m">Policy in Love: Lyric and Public in Ovid, Petrarch and Shakespeare.</title> Pittsburgh: Duquesne UP, 1994.</item>
								<item>McFarlane, Cameron. <title level="m">The Sodomite in Fiction and Satire.</title> New York: Columbia UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Meagher, John C. <title level="m">Shakespeare's Shakespeare: How the Plays were Made.</title> New York: Continuum Books, 1997.</item>
								<item>Murray, Jacqueline, and Konrad Eisenbichler. <title level="m">Desire and Discipline: Sex and Sexuality in the Premodern West.</title> Toronto: U of Toronto P, 1996.</item>
								<item>Ogden, James, and Arthur H. Scouten, eds. <title level="m">Lear from Study to Stage: Essays in Criticism.</title> Cranbury: Associated UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Pacheco, Anita. <title level="m">Early Women Writers: 1600-1720.</title> Harlow: Longman, 1998.</item>
								<item>Platt, Peter G. <title level="m">Reason Diminished: Shakespeare and the Marvelous.</title> Lincoln: U of Nebraska P, 1997.</item>
								<item>Purkiss, Diane. <title level="m">The Witch in History.</title> New York: Routledge, 1996.</item>
								<item>Reiss, Timothy. <title level="m">Knowledge, Discovery and Imagination in Early Modern Europe.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Rhodes, Neill, ed. <title level="m">English Renaissance Prose: History, Language, Politics.</title> Tempe, AZ: Medieval and Renaissance Text Society, 1997. </item>
								<item>Rubik, Margarete. <title level="m">Early Women Dramatists 1550-1800.</title> Basingstoke: Macmillan, 1998.</item>
								<item>Rumrich, John. <title level="m">Milton Unbound: Controversy and Reinterpration.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Shakespeare, William. <title level="m">Edward III</title> and <title level="m">The First Quarto of Hamlet.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1998.</item>
								<item>Shurgot, Michael W. <title level="m">Stages of Play: Shakespeare's Theatrical Energies in Elizabethan Performance.</title> Newark: U of Delaware P, 1998.</item>
								<item>Smith, Hilda L. <title level="m">Women Writers and the Early Modern British Political Tradition.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1998.</item>
								<item>Speziale-Bagliacca, Roberto. <title level="m">The King &amp; the Adulteress: A Psychoanalytic and Literary Representation of</title> King Lear <title level="m">and</title> Madame Bovary. Durham: Duke UP, 1998.</item>
								<item>Stanwood, Paul, ed. <title level="m">Of Poetry and Politics: New Essays on Milton and his World.</title> Binghamton, NY: Center for Medieval and Early Renaissance Studies, 1995.</item>
								<item>Stanwood, Paul. <title level="m">Izaak Walton.</title> New York: Twayne, 1998.</item>
								<item>Stewart, Alan. <title level="m">Close Readers: Humanism and Sodomy in Early Modern England.</title> Princeton: Princeton UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Stewart, Stanley. <title level="m">
										<q direct="y">Renaissance</q> Talk.</title> Pittsburgh: Duquesne UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Traub, Valerie, M. Lindsay Kaplan, and Dympna Callaghan, eds. <title level="m">Feminist Readings of Early Modern Culture: Emerging Subjects.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1996.</item>
								<item>Walker, Greg. <title level="m">Persuasive Fictions: Faction, Faith, and Political Culture in the Reign of Henry VIII.</title> Aldershot: Scolar P, 1996.</item>
								<item>Walker, Julia M. <title level="m">Dissing Elizabeth: Negative Representations of Gloriana.</title> Durham: Duke UP, 1998.</item>
								<item>Walton Williams, George. <title level="m">Shakespeare's Speech Headings.</title> Newark: U of Delaware P, 1997.</item>
								<item>Warren, Austin. <title level="m">Becoming What One Is.</title> Ann Arbor: U of Michigan P, 1995.</item>
								<item>Wilcox, Helen, ed. <title level="m">Women and Literature in Britain 1500-1700.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1996.</item>
								<item>Williams, Gordon. <title level="m">Shakespeare, Sex and the Print Revolution.</title> Atlantic Highlands: Athlone P, 1996.</item>
								<item>Worthen, W.B. <title level="m">Shakespeare and the Authority of Performance.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Wright, C.J., ed. <title level="m">Sir Robert Cotton as Collector.</title> London: The British Library, 1997.</item>
							</list>
						</p>
					</div3>
					<div3 id="emls4-1revbookforthcoming">
						<head>Forthcoming Reviews:</head>
						<p>
							<list>
								<item>Albanese, Denise. <title level="m">New Science, New World. </title>Durham: Duke UP, 1996.</item>
								<item>
									<title level="m">The Arden Shakespeare CD-ROM: Texts and Sources for Shakespeare Studies</title>. Walton-on-Thames: Arden Shakespeare, 1997.</item>
								<item>Barnes, Elizabeth. <title level="m">States of Sympathy: Seduction and Democracy in the American Novel. </title>New York: Columbia UP, 1997. </item>
								<item>Bath, Michael. <title level="m">Speaking Pictures: Emblem Books and Renaissance Culture.</title> London: Longman, 1993.</item>
								<item>Beal, Peter, and Jeremy Griffiths, ed. <title level="m">English Manuscript Studies 1100-1700.</title> (Vol. 6) London: The British Library, 1997.</item>
								<item>Benedict, Barbara M. <title level="m">Making the Modern Reader: Cultural Mediation in Early Modern Literary Anthologies.</title> Princeton: Princeton UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Bishop, T.G. <title level="m">Shakespeare and the Theatre of Wonder.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1996. </item>
								<item>Brown, Cedric C., and Arthur F. Marotti. <title level="m">Texts and Cultural Change in Early Modern England.</title> Basingstoke: Macmillan, 1997.</item>
								<item>Burns, Edward. <title level="m">Reading Rochester.</title> Liverpool: Liverpool UP, 1996.</item>
								<item>Cable, Lana. <title level="m">Carnal Rhetoric: Milton's Iconoclasm and the Poetics of Desire.</title> Durham: Duke UP, 1995.</item>
								<item>Cavendish, William. <title level="m">Dramatic Works by William Cavendish.</title> Oxford: The Malone Society, 1996. </item>
								<item>Cereta, Laura. <title level="m">Collected Letters of a Renaissance Feminist.</title> Chicago: U of Chicago P, 1997. </item>
								<item>Cheney, Patrick. <title level="m">Marlowe's Counterfeit Profession: Ovid, Spenser, Counter-Nationhood.</title> Toronto: U of Toronto P, 1997.</item>
								<item>Comensoli, Viviana. <title level="m">Household Business: Domestic Plays of Early Modern England.</title> Toronto: U of Toronto P, 1996. </item>
								<item>Cook, Patrick J. <title level="m">Milton, Spenser and the Epic Tradition.</title> Aldershot: Scolar P, 1996.</item>
								<item>Cressy, David. <title level="m">Birth, Marriage and Death: Ritual, Religion, and the Life-Cycle in Tudor and Stuart England.</title> Oxford: Oxford UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Deats, Sara Munson. <title level="m">Sex, Gender, and Desire in the Plays of Christopher Marlowe.</title> Cranbury, N.J.: Associated UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Diehl, Huston. <title level="m">Staging Reform, Reforming the Stage.</title> Ithaca: Cornell UP, 1997. </item>
								<item>Doerksen, Daniel. <title level="m">Conforming to the Word: Herbert, Donne and the English Church before Laud.</title> Cranbury, N.J.: Bucknell UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Erickson, Wayne. <title level="m">Mapping</title> The Faerie Queene<title level="m">: Quest Structures and the World of the Poem.</title> New York: Garland, 1996.</item>
								<item>Fanshawe, Richard. <title level="m">The Poems and Translations of Sir Richard Fanshawe.</title> Vol. 1. Ed. Peter Davidson. Oxford: Clarendon P, 1997.</item>
								<item>Farago, Claire, ed. <title level="m">Reframing the Renaissance: Visual Culture in Europe and Latin America 1450-1650</title> Yale: Yale UP, 1996. </item>
								<item>Grantley, Daryll and Peter Roberts. <title level="m">Christopher Marlowe and English Renaissance Culture.</title> Aldershot: Scolar P, 1996.</item>
								<item>Gregerson, Linda. <title level="m">The Reformation of the Subject: Spenser, Milton, and the English Protestant Epic.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1995. </item>
								<item>Grell, Ole Peter and Andrew Cunningham. <title level="m">Religio Medici: Medicine and Religion in Seventeenth-Century England.</title> Aldershot: Scolar P, 1996.</item>
								<item>Hamilton, Donna B. and Richard Strier, eds. <title level="m">Religion, Literature and Politics in Post-Reformation England.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1996. </item>
								<item>Harvey, P.D.A. <title level="m">Mappa Mundi: The Hereford World Map.</title> Toronto: U of Toronto P, 1996. </item>
								<item>Hillman, David and Carla Mazzio. <title level="m">The Body in Parts: Fantasies of Corporeality in Early Modern Europe.</title> London and New York: Routledge, 1997. </item>
								<item>James, Heather. <title level="m">Shakespeare's Troy: Drama, Politics, and the Translation of Empire.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Kelsey McColley, Diane. <title level="m">Poetry and Music in Seventeenth-Century England.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1997. </item>
								<item>Maquerlot, Jean-Pierre and Michele Willems, eds. <title level="m">Travel and Drama in Shakespeare's Time.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1995.</item>
								<item>Marotti, Arthur. <title level="m">Manuscript, Print and the English Renaissance Lyric.</title> Ithaca: Cornell UP, 1995.</item>
								<item>Marrapodi, Michele. <title level="m">The Italian World of English Renaissance Drama.</title> Newark: U of Delaware P, 1998.</item>
								<item>MacCulloch, Diarmaid. <title level="m">Thomas Cranmer.</title> Yale: Yale UP, 1996.</item>
								<item>McRae, Andrew. <title level="m">God Speed the Plough: The Representation of Agrarian England 1500-1660.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1996. </item>
								<item>Meagher, John C. <title level="m">Shakespeare's Shakespeare: How the Plays were Made.</title> New York: Continuum Books, 1997. </item>
								<item>Moore, Lisa M. <title level="m">Dangerous Intimacies: Toward a Sapphic History of the British Novel.</title> Durham: Duke UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Parker, Douglas, ed. <title level="m">A Proper Dyaloge betwene a Gentillman and an Husbandman.</title> Toronto: U of Toronto P, 1996.</item>
								<item>Perry, Curtis. <title level="m">The Making of Jacobean Culture.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1997.</item>
								<item>Pask, Kevin. <title level="m">The Emergence of the English Author: Scripting the Life of the Poet in Early Modern England.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1996. </item>
								<item>Raymond, Joad. <title level="m">The Invention of the Newspaper: English Newsbooks 1641-1649.</title> Oxford: Clarendon P, 1996.</item>
								<item>Riddell, James A. and Stanley Stewart. <title level="m">Jonson's Spenser: Evidence and Historical Criticism.</title> Pittsburgh: Duquesne UP, 1995.</item>
								<item>Shuger, Debora Kuller. <title level="m">Habits of Thought in the English Renaissance.</title> Toronto: U of Toronto P, 1997. </item>
								<item>Tebeaux, Elizabeth. <title level="m">The Emergence of a Tradition: Techincal Writing in the English Renaissance, 1475-1640.</title> Amityville, N.Y.: Baywood, 1997.</item>
								<item>Vendler, Helen. <title level="m">The Art of Shakespeare's Sonnets.</title> New Haven: Harvard UP, 1996. </item>
								<item>Wiseman, Susan. <title level="m">Drama and Politics in the English Civil War.</title> Cambridge: Cambridge UP, 1998.</item>
								<item>Woudhuysen, Henry. <title level="m">Sir Philip Sidney and the Circulation of Manuscripts 1558-1640.</title> Oxford: Oxford UP, 1996.</item>
								<item>Yachnin, Paul. <title level="m">Stage-Wrights: Shakespeare, Jonson, Middleton, and the Making of Theatrical Value.</title> Philadelphia: U of Pennsylvania P, 1997.</item>
							</list>
						</p>
						<p>
							<!-- <a href="../emlshome.html"> -->
							<!-- <img src="../button.gif" width="124" height="47"> -->
							<!-- </a> -->
							<!-- <a href="../emlscopy.html"> -->&copy;<!-- </a> --> 1998-, R.G. Siemens (Editor, <title level="j">EMLS</title>).</p>
						<byline>(LH, RGS, 10 June 1998)</byline>
					</div3>
				</div2>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="issuesection">
				<head>Readers' Forum</head>
				<div2 type="forum">
					<p>
						<list>
							<item>Responses to articles, reviews, and notes appearing in this issue that are intended for the Readers' Forum may be sent to the Editor at <!-- <a href="mailto:emls@ualberta.ca"> -->EMLS@UAlberta.ca<!-- </a> -->.</item>
						</list>
					</p>
				</div2>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
